export let singles = [
  {
    "question": "The arrangement of these things was the subject of Michel Chevreul's [mee-shel shev-rahl's] \"law of simultaneous contrast.\"  These things were put on a \"sphere\" by Philipp Otto Runge [RUN-guh] after correspondence with an author who proposed a \"theory\" of them in his book Zur Farbenlehre [FAR-ben-leh-ruh].  An \"additive\" method for the (*) \"mixing\" of these things is commonly known by the initialism \"RGB.\"  For 10 points -what things appear on a \"wheel\" including primary ones such as blue?",
    "answer": "colors (accept color sphere or color wheel or Theory of Colors or primary colors; accept farben or Zur Farbenlehre before \"Farbenlehre\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This organization demanded a provision of indemnity in the \"Solemn Engagement.\"  The Earl of Essex was prevented from leading this force by the Self-Denying Ordinance.  Men opposed to this force were removed from office in Pride's Purge.  Thomas (*)  Fairfax led this group to victory at Naseby [NAYZ-bee] against Charles I [\"the first\"].  Oliver Cromwell was a cavalry commander in -for 10 points-what Roundhead army that won the First English Civil War?",
    "answer": "New Model Army (prompt on \"parliamentary army\" or \"Parliamentarian army\"; prompt on \"Roundhead(s)\" before \"Roundhead\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "A population of cells from this tissue with stem cell properties is called the stromal vascular fraction.  The protein HSL [\"H-S-L\"] \"mobilizes\" the contents of this tissue, which regulates its composition by secreting the hormone (*) leptin [LEP-tin].  Because infants can't shiver, they are born with sizeable amounts of this tissue's \"brown\" form behind their shoulders.  Obesity is an excess of -for 10 points-what tissue that stores lipids?",
    "answer": "fat (or adipose tissue)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This country controls the western half of the island of Usedom [OO-seh-dom], the site of many nudist beaches.  This country planned to build the colossal beach resort of Prora as part of its state -sponsored \"Strength Through Joy\" program.  The island of (*)  Rügen [RUR-ghen] is controlled by this country, which allowed North Sea shipping to bypass Jutland [YOOT-lund] by building the Kiel Canal.  For 10 points -name this country where the Elbe [EL-buh] flows past Hamburg [HAHM-boorg].",
    "answer": "Germany (or Federal Republic of Germany or Bundesrepublik Deutschland; accept Nazi Germany)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This poem mentions a \"valley of dying stars\" where \"there are no eyes.\"  In its last section, stanzas are interspersed with the italicized [ih-TAL-uh-\"sized\"] words \"for Thine is the Kingdom.\"  This poem alters a nursery rhyme to state \"here we go (*) round the prickly pear.\"  The \"kingdoms\" of Death are described in this poem, which claims the world will end \"not with a bang but a whimper.\"  T. S. Eliot wr ote-for 10 points-what poem about empty people?",
    "answer": "The Hollow Men"
  },
  {
    "question": "After Spain re-occupied this country with help from Pedro Santana, rebels began its War of Restoration.  Desiderio Arias [day-zee-DAIR-ee-oh AH-ree-ahss] forced the resignation of this country's president Juan Isidro Jimenes [wahn ee-SEE-droh hee-MEH-nez] in 1916, leading the U.S. to occupy it.  This country's mi litary killed over 12,000 people asked to say the word (*) perejil [\"pay-ray-HEEL\"] in the anti-immigrant Parsley Massacre.  Rafael Trujillo [troo-HEE-yoh] once governed-for 10 points-what country on Hispaniola?",
    "answer": "Dominican Republic (or República Dominicana; prompt on \"DR\"; do not accept or prompt on \"Dominica\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this field of study, the theory of structuration was advanced by Anthony Giddens.  An 1895 text that argues for applying the scientific method to the study of discrete \"facts\" is titled for \"rules\" of this field's \"method.\"  The structural functionalist  approach to this discipline was advocated by (*) Émile Durkheim [ay-MEEL dur-kem], who practiced this field along with Erving Goffman and Max Weber [VAY-bur].  For 10 points-name this study of society.",
    "answer": "sociology [soh-see-AH-luh-jee] (or sociological study or method; accept New Rules of Sociological Method or Rules of Sociological Method)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This film's villain quips \"that wasn't very sporting, using real bullets\" after his henchman is shot.  A photograph shows this film's protagonist grabbing a knife that killed diplomat Lester Townsend.  After being mistaken for the fake (*) spy George Kaplan in this film, Roger Thornhill is chased in a field by a crop-dusting plane.  Cary Grant stars in -for 10 points-what Alfred Hitchcock film featuring a chase on Mount Rushmore?",
    "answer": "North by Northwest"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 1940s play a prostitute from this country adopts a male alter ego to protect herself after being favored by the gods.  Bertolt Brecht drew his concept of the \"distancing effect\" from this country, and adapted its 14th-century play Circle of Chalk.  Th is country briefly permitted (*) dissident literature during the \"Hundred Flowers Campaign.\"  For 10 points -what country is the setting of Brecht's The Good Person of Szechwan [SETCH-wahn]?",
    "answer": "China (or People's Republic of China or PRC or Zhongguo or Zhonghua Renmin Gongheguo; do not accept or prompt on \"Republic of China\") [The first sentence refers to Brecht's play The Good Person of Szechwan.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "The borders of these regions are below the ascending portion of the Ferrel [\"FAIR\"-ul] cells.  Noctil ucent [NOK-tuh-LOO-sint] clouds are seen primarily above these geographic regions, whose namesake stratospheric clouds are also called \"nacreous\" [NAY-kree-uss] due to their colorful appearance.  Jet stream (*)  meanders result from the weakening of a namesake \"vortex\" of low-pressure air that circles-for 10 points-what regions where auroras may be seen over the ice caps?",
    "answer": "polar regions (or circumpolar regions; or poles; accept descriptive answers such as above the Arctic Circle and below the Antarctic Circle; accept polar stratospheric clouds)"
  },
  {
    "question": "During SETI [SEH-tee] observations of this star in 2019, the radio signal BLC1 was detected.  In 2019 Meredith MacGregor observed unprecedented millimeter-range flares coming from this star.  In Apri l 2020 the New Horizons probe took images of Wolf 359 and this star.  In 2020 the (*)  \"d\" exoplanet orbiting this star was discovered about four light-years from Earth.  For 10 points -name this nearest known extra-solar star to the Earth.",
    "answer": "Proxima Centauri (or Alpha Centauri C; prompt on \"Alpha Centauri\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This town was where the first issues of The Lily, the first woman-edited newspaper in the U.S., were printed.  While living in this town, Amelia Bloomer popularized the women's garment now called \"bloomers.\"  In this town, a two-day (*) conference partly organized by Elizabeth Cady Stanton produced the Declar ation of Sentiments.  For 10 points -what upstate New York town hosted a landmark 1848 women's rights convention?",
    "answer": "Seneca Falls, New York (accept Seneca Falls Convention or Seneca Falls Conference)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this country, girls wear red and white martenitsa [mar-TAY-neet-sah] threads on March 1, Baba Marta day.  From top to bottom, the three horizontal stripes on this country's flag are white, green, and red.  A dissident from this country, Gyorgy (*) Markov, was killed by a ricin pellet fired from an umbrella.  This country's yogurt is usually less thick than that of neighboring Greece.  For 10 points -what Balkan nation's capital is Sofia?",
    "answer": "Bulgaria (or Republic of Bulgaria or Republika Balgariya)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a theory of this phenomenon that takes path integrals over a \"spin foam,\" space is quantized on the Planck scale.  This phenomenon is mediated by a hypothetical massless spin-2 gauge boson [gayj BOH-zahn].  Adding an explanation of this phenomenon to (*) Grand Unified Theory would produce a \"theory of everything.\"  General relativity explains-for 10 points-what fundamental force that causes attraction between massive objects?",
    "answer": "gravity or gravitational force (accept loop quantum gravity)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A man in this play complains about not having his toothbrush after noticin g there are no mirrors nearby.  This play ends with a character remarking \"Let's get on with it.\"  A valet with no eyelids brings people to a room of (*) Second Empire-style furniture in this play, in which Estelle reveals she killed her child resulting fr om an affair.  Garcin [gar-san] remarks \"hell is other people\" in-for 10 points-what play by Jean-Paul Sartre [sar-truh]?",
    "answer": "No Exit (or Huis Clos [wee kloh]; accept In Camera or No Way Out or Dead End)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Expanding this system was the primary goal of the Program for Action created by John Lindsay.  This system uses circles and diamonds to distinguish between local and express services.  Massimo Vignelli [veen-YELL-ee] created an iconic modernist (*) map for this system that was first operated by the IRT company, which built the 1 and 2 lines to South Ferry.  For 10 points -what public transit system stops at Grand Central and Times Square?",
    "answer": "New York subway (system) (or New York City subway; accept New York subway (system) map; accept metro in place of subway; prompt on \"subway\" by asking \"where?\"; prompt on \"MTA\" or \" New York railroads\" or \"New York public transportation\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 2022 a former president of this country was convicted in absentia of murdering his leftist predecessor in 1987.  The Patriotic Movement for Safeguard and Restoration led a 2022 coup [koo] in this Mooré [moo-ray]- and French-speaking country, causing its suspension from ECOWAS [\"ECHO\"-woss] and the African Union.  In 1987 (*) Blaise Compaoré [kom-pow-ray] toppled and killed Thomas Sankara in-for 10 points-what landlocked West African country led from Ouagadougou [hwa-gah-DOO-goo]?",
    "answer": "Burkina Faso [bur-KEE-nah FAH-soh]"
  },
  {
    "question": "A set of these artworks, which appear in the background of John Singleton Copley's [COP-lee's] painting The Death of the Earl of Chatham [CHAT-um], depicted the British defeat of the Spanish Armada.  The first known depiction of Halley's Comet appears in one of these artworks that was likely commissioned by (*)  Odo for his half-brother, who won the Battle of Hastings.  For 10 points -identify these woven artworks, one of which is named for Bayeux [bye-yoo].",
    "answer": "tapestries (accept Armada Tapestries or Bayeux Tapestry; prompt on \"embroidery\" or \"textile(s)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Highlands in what is now this country were home to a 13th -century trickster commonly depicted riding backward on a donkey, the sufi [SOO-fee] Nasreddin Hodja [nahs-reh-DEEN HOH-jah].  This nation's city of Konya [KAWN-yah] was the capital of the Sultanate of (*) Rum [\"SULTAN-ate of room\"], while in the 11th century most of its territory was conquered by the Seljuks [SEL-jooks].  For 10 points -what country's city of Edirne [eh-DEER-nuh] served as the capital of the Ottoman Empire before the fall of Constantinople?",
    "answer": "Turkey (or Republic of Turkey or Türkiye Cumhuriyeti)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This ethnic group's beliefs hold that spirits enter the underworld from Cape Reinga [RAYNG-ah].  A mythical ancestor of these people escaped his brother's plot to drown him by summoning a whale.  In another of their myths, Tane [TAH-nay] separates the sky father (*) Rangi [RAHN-ghee] from the earth mother Papa.  Ceremonial dances called hakas [HAH-kahz] are performed by-for 10 points-what Polynesian people, whose hero Maui [MAO-ee] fished up the North Island of New Zealand?",
    "answer": "Maori [MAO-ree] (do not accept or prompt on \"Polynesian(s)\" or \"Hawaiian(s)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "When using this number as a base, the standard form is to avoid the sequence \"11\" [\"one-one\"].  This number equals twice the cosine of 36 degrees.  The continued fraction \"1 plus 1 over 1 (*)  plus 1 over 1\" and so on equals this number. This number is the larger root of \"x squared minus x minus 1\" and is also the limiting ratio of consecutive Fibonacci [fib-uh-NAH-chee] numbers.  \"1 plus root 5 all over 2\" equals -for 10 points-what supposedly \"beautiful\" number?",
    "answer": "golden ratio or golden mean or golden number (or golden section; prompt on \"phi\"; do not accept or prompt on \"pi\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This vessel and its counterpart the Galena engaged with on-shore batteries at Drewry's Bluff.  John Ericsson designed the body of this vessel, which was commanded by John Worden.  Theodore Timby created a revolving two-gun (*) turret for this vessel, which sank in a storm off Cape Hatteras nine months after an indecisive engagement at Hampton Roads.  The CSS Virginia fought to a draw with-for 10 points-what Union ironclad?",
    "answer": "USS Monitor"
  },
  {
    "question": "A character in this novel jokes about wishing he owned \"half\" of an unpleasantly loud dog, so he could kill his half.  This novel was originally titled Those Extraordinary Twins and centered on Luigi and Angelo Capello.  This novel's protagonist uses (*)  fingerprints to prove that \"Tom Driscoll\" both committed a murder and was switched at birth.  For 10 points -what Mark Twain novel is titled for a lawyer who is considered stupid?",
    "answer": "Pudd'nhead Wilson (accept The Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson and the Comedy of Those Extraordinary Twins) [The joke falls flat, leading the townspeople of Dawson's Landing to nickname Wilson \"Pudd'nhead.\"]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Some devices used in this technique possess projections called weirs [weers] and downcomers, which isolate material into many discrete equilibrium stages.  In this technique, increasing the reflux ratio produces no benefit when working with mixtures called (*) azeotropes [AY-zee-oh-trohps].  A condenser is used to isolate \"fractions\" of material in-for 10 points-what chemical technique that separates a mixture based on differences in boiling point?",
    "answer": "(fractional) distillation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The chief deity of Sesesh [SEH-sesh] had this animal form and was named Bat [baht].  In the Pyramid Texts, the pharaoh meets two black examples of this animal after he is reborn.  A goddess with this form was worshiped at Dendera and wore a menat necklace.  The eight Heh gods are shown supporting Nut [noot], who takes this form, in a (*) \"book\" titled for a \"heavenly\" one.  The lion -headed Sekhmet is a form of Hathor, who has the head of-for 10 points-what animal, allowing her to hold a uraeus [yoo-REE-uss] between her horns?",
    "answer": "cow(s) (accept cattle; accept The Book of the Heavenly Cow; prompt on \"bovine(s)\"; do not accept or prompt on \"bull(s)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Betty Meggers argued that civilization was impossible in this  region in a book calling it a \"counterfeit paradise.\"  That book claims this region's várzeas [VAR-zay-ahs] were densely populated.  Plants adapted to poor soil live in this biome's [\"BY\"-ohm's] campinarama [cahm-pee-nah-RAH-mah] areas.  A 4,000 -kilometer highway spanning this region passes through (*) Tocantins [toh-CAHN-teens] and ends at Paraíba [pah-rah-EE-bah] in the east.  The tea-like color of a river in this biome led Francisco de Orellana [oh-ray-YAH-nuh] to name it the Río Negro.  For 10 points-Manaus [mah-NAH-oos] is a city in what rainforest?",
    "answer": "Amazon rainforest (or Amazonia or Amazonas or Amazon basin; accept Amazonia: Man and Culture in a Counterfeit Paradise or Trans-Amazonian Highway; prompt on \"(tropical) rainforest\" before \"rainforest\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "After Robert LaFollette and George W. Norris, this man was the third presidential candidate from the Farmer-Labor Party, running in 1932 and 1936.  This man's earlier followers sought the passage of a \"Non-interest Bearing Bond Bill\" and \"Good Roads Bill.\"  This head of the (*) \"Commonweal of Christ\" joined with Carl Browne to lead a group of unemployed men on a 300 -mile march from Massillon [MASS-ih-lun] to Washington, D.C.  For 10 points -name this Ohio businessman whose namesake \"army\" protested the Panic  of 189",
    "answer": "Jacob Coxey (accept Coxey's Army)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A character asks his \"master\" why this figure appears upside-down and how the \"sun made his transit\" so quickly.  Dorothy Sayers suggested that this figure's red, yellow, and black coloration represents the human races.  The waist of this lord of Giudecca [joo-DEK-kah] is surrounded by the (*) icy river Cocytus [koh-\"SIGH\"-tuss].  Two men grasp this figure's hair and climb down his body, emerging in the Southern Hemisphere.  In Canto 34 of the Inferno, Dante [DAHN-tay] and Virgil [VUR-jil] encounter-for 10 points-what three-faced giant arch-traitor?",
    "answer": "Lucifer (or Lucifero; or Dis; or Beelzebub; accept Satan; prompt on \"(the) Devil\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "An album titled for this musician \"in Wonderland\" features two tracks he wrote for the John Cassavetes [\"CASS\"-uh-VEH-teez] film Shadows.  In 1989 Gunther Schuller revised and premiered a this artist's two -hour long composition Epitaph.  This bandleader worked with Horace Parlan and D annie Richmond in his \"Jazz Workshop.\"  He mocked the (*)  racist governor of Arkansas in \"Fables of Faubus,\" but the lyrics were removed from an album whose title follows his name with the words \"Ah Um.\"  For 10 points -name this jazz bassist.",
    "answer": "Charles Mingus (accept Jazz Portraits: Mingus in Wonderland or Mingus, Ah Um)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Unidentified Falling Objects cause losses in one of these things and lead it t o be dumped by dilution kickers that sweep it in a Lissajous [LIH-suh-zhoo] figure.  The total momentum over the total charge of these things is their rigidity, a measure of how easily they can be guided by magnets.  Wigglers periodically (*)  deflect these things that are kept circulating in storage rings, as seen at the Tevatron [TEV-uh-tron] and LHC.  A fixed target may be struck by-for 10 points-what collimated streams in particle accelerators?",
    "answer": "particle beams (before \"dumped,\" accept particle colliders or particle accelerators; after \"dumped\" and before \"rigidity,\" prompt on \"(particle) collider(s)\" or \"(particle) accelerator(s)\"; before \"Tevatron,\" accept proton beams or ion beams; before \"streams,\" prompt on \"(charged) particles\" with \"the particles are moving as part of what things?\"; before \"Tevatron,\" prompt with \"the particles are moving as part of what things?\" on \"protons\" or \"ions\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In one episode of this show, a woman tells a joke on a telephone that ends with God being killed by a brick.  A character on this show spells out the message \"save me daughter\" using the corpses of his servants.  The backstory to this show involves a massacre known as the \"White (*) Night\" carried out by the Seventh Kavalry, a white supremacist group.  The city of Tulsa, where police officers wear costumed disguises, is the setting of-for 10 points-what HBO series based on an Alan Moore graphic novel?",
    "answer": "Watchmen"
  },
  {
    "question": "An early turning point in this conflict was the Day of the Barges.  This conflict ended with the sack of the city of al-Mukhtara [ahl mook-TAH-ruh] by the general al-Muwaffaq [ahl mooh-WAH-fahk].  Despite claiming to be descended from the first Shia imam, the leader of this conflict's losing side adopted the ideology of the (*)  Kharijites [KAR-ee-jytes] because they believed even a slave could become caliph.  Ali ibn Muhammad led hundreds of thousands of rebel slaves in-for 10 points-what revolt against the Abbasids named for a region of East Africa?",
    "answer": "Zanj Rebellion (accept Zanj Uprising)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Section one of this essay argues that even Bernard Mandeville understood the power of compassion by citing Mandeville's description of a child eaten alive by a pig.  Section two of this essay opens by decrying the first man who set off land with stakes and declared \"this is mine.\"  This essay argues that humans are distinguished from animals by (*) \"perfectibility,\" which allows for the rise of amour-propre [ah-moor-PROP-ruh].  For 10 points-what Jean-Jacques Rousseau [roo-SOH] essay discusses the emergence of social hierarchy?",
    "answer": "Discourse on Inequality (or Discourse on the Origin and Basis of Inequality Among Men; A Dissertation On the Origin and Foundation of the Inequality of Mankind; or Discours sur l'origine et les fondements de l'inégalité parmi les hommes; accept Rousseau's Second Discourse)"
  },
  {
    "question": "An enzyme inhibited by zaragozic acid ligates two pyrophosphate [PYE-roh-\"phosphate\"] derivatives of one of these compounds.  The \"10\" in coenzyme Q10 refers to one of these compounds attached to the quinone [KWY-nohn] ring.  Derivatives of these compounds  are synthesized, then later converted to (*) steroids, in the mevalonate [meh-VAL-uh-nayt] pathway.  Examples of these compounds with 15 carbons are given the prefix \"sesqui [sess-kwih].\"  Pinene [\"PINE\"-een], limonene [LIH-moh-neen], and squalene [SKWAY-leen] are examples of-for 10 points-what class of lipids formed from multiple isoprene [\"EYE-so-preen\"] units?",
    "answer": "terpenes (accept terpenoids; accept isoprenoids before \"isoprene\"; accept farnesene or farnesyl before \"coenzyme Q10\"; prompt on \"alkenes\" or \"lipids\" or \"hydrocarbons\" or \"prenyl\" or \"isoprenyl\" before \"sesqui\"; prompt on \"isoprenoids\" after \"isoprene\"; do not accept or prompt on \"polyisoprene\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an operetta, a character in this city tells a tale free from \"all possible doubt whatever\" in \"I Stole the Prince.\"  In this city, a character gives a rosary to a woman who saved her from being burned for witchcraft in the aria \"Voce di donna\" [VOH-chay dee DOH-nuh].  Gamelan -like music accompanies a mute young male dancer in a (*) Benjamin Britten opera set in this city.  The \"Dance of the Hours\" appears in the opera La Gioconda [lah joh-KAWN-duh], set in-for 10 points-what Italian city, the setting of Gilbert and Sullivan's The Gondoliers?",
    "answer": "Venice (or Venezia) [The Benjamin Britten opera is Death in Venice.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Responses to this concept from several \"value spheres\" are examined in a Lawrence Scaff paper on \"fleeing\"  it.  A 1983 sociology paper on the \"institutional isomorphism\" of similar organizations, by Paul DiMaggio and Walter Powell, is titled for this concept \"revisited.\"  This concept replaced a (*)  \"light cloak\" of care for material goods according to Talcott Parsons's translation of a 1905 book.  For 10 points -what metaphor in Max Weber's [VAY-bur's] The Protestant Ethic likens modern rationalization to a prison?",
    "answer": "iron cage (of rationality) (or stahlhartes Gehäuse; accept steel-hard shell or shell as hard as steel or steel-hard casing; accept Fleeing the Iron Cage or The Iron Cage Revisited)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A woman in this play rejects a bribe of a jewel from her disguised brother, but a bribe of gold is taken by her mother.  A man in this play asks \"does the silkworm expend her yellow labors / f or thee?\" while holding a skull.  Gratiana is the mother of this play's protagonist, who goes by the name of Piato while working for Lussurioso, the son of the duke who poisoned his lover. (*) Vindice [vin-DEE-chay] is the title figure of-for 10 points-what play attributed once to Cyril Tourneur but now to Thomas Middleton?",
    "answer": "The Revenger's Tragedy"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 1D model of this body can be constructed using the Herglotz-Wiechert [HUR-glahts-VEE-kurt] inversion on travel-time curve data, assuming there are no LVZs [L V zees].  The Jeffreys -Bullen model of this body was a precursor to the PREM [prem] or \"preliminary reference model\" for this body.  Cold slabs sometimes sink from this body's surface past the (*) 660 kilometer discontinuity and go all the way to the CMB or Gutenberg [GOO-tin-burg] discontinuity, as revealed by seismic tomography [tuh-MAH-gruh-fee].  For 10 points -name this tectonically active planet.",
    "answer": "Earth"
  },
  {
    "question": "This man gave 35 defenses of God's existence in his Quaestiones [kwai-stee-OH-nays] on the Book of Genesis.  Like Johannes Kepler, this Minim [MIH-nim] friar wrote extensively against Robert Fludd.  For connecting and distributing the works of such thinkers as René Descartes [reh-nay day-kart], this man was called the (*) \"post-box of Europe.\"  The Euclid -Euler [YOOK-lid-OY-lur] theorem relates perfect numbers to numbers named for this man, the first four of which are 3, 7, 31, and 127.  For 10 points -what Frenchman names primes that are one less than a power of two?",
    "answer": "Marin Mersenne (or Marin Mersennus; accept Mersenne primes)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The protagonist of this book defies his principal by giving his own valedictorian address at his 1925 graduation.  In the first chapter of this  book, its narrator hallucinates giant udders when he is beaten by his mother for setting (*) fire to his grandmother's house.  This book's second section, \"The Horror and the Glory,\" relates how its narrator joins the John Reed Society and the Communist P arty in Chicago.  For 10 points -name this memoir about American race relations by Richard Wright.",
    "answer": "Black Boy"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a concurrence in this case, Tom Clark wrote that anyone \"emerging from the rash of opinions\" in it might suffer from \"mental blindness.\"  In an opinion in this case, which overturned Colegrove v. Green, William Brennan described six factors that determine whether a case presents a (*)  \"political question.\"  This case considered Tennessee's failure to perform a certain action for six decades.  For 10 points -name this 1962 Supreme Court decision holding that federal courts may hear redistricting cases.",
    "answer": "Baker v. Carr"
  },
  {
    "question": "This disorder and the related Miller-Fisher syndrome both exhibit albumin-cytological [al-BYOO-min \"SIGH-toe-logical\"] dissociation.  Campylobacter jejuni [\"CAMP-ill-oh-back\"-tur jih-JOO-nee] can provoke this disorder due to molecular mimicry creating anti-ganglioside [anti-GAN-glee-oh-side] antibodies.  Unlike botulism [BAH-choo-LIH-zum], this disorder produces an ascending paralysis, and unlike (*) multiple sclerosis [skleh-ROH-siss], this autoimmune disorder affects the peripheral nervous system.  Viral infections and the influenza vaccine have been linked to-for 10 points-what polyneuropathy named for two Frenchmen?",
    "answer": "Guillain-Barré [GEE-yan bah-RAY] syndrome (accept GBS)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A story collection about old age by this author ends with a story about Jean Sibelius [ZHAHN sih-BAY-lee-us] wishing to be buried with the title fruit.  In a novel by this author of The Lemon Table, Tony is told \"you don't get it\" by a woman who he repeatedly emails to ask for Adrian's diary.  This author included exam questions in the back of a novel in which (*) Geoffrey Braithwaite tries to determine which stuffed bird inspired \"A Simple Heart.\"  For 10 points -name this author of The Sense of an Ending and Flaubert's Parrot.",
    "answer": "Julian (Patrick) Barnes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ten of these people with different names form a single supply pile in the Dominion expansion Dark Ages.  A \"mage\" one of these people names the first collectible miniatures game, whose system was la ter used for HeroClix.  Along with cities, these people name an expansion to The (*) Settlers of Catan.  In a common chess opening, white moves a piece of this name on their second turn from g1 [\"G one\"] to f3 [\"F three\"].  For 10 points-what people name a chess piece that can jump over other pieces and move in an 'L' shape?",
    "answer": "knights (accept Mage Knight or Catan: Cities and Knights or King's knight opening)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The extent of this region can be defined by place names known as \"Grimston hybrids\"  and the spread of land divisions called \"wapentakes\" [WAH-\"pen-takes\"].  The \"Five Boroughs\" of this region, such as Lincoln and Derby [dar-bee], were conquered by Edward the Elder.  This was the region north and east of a line that ran up the River (*) Ouse [\"ooze\"] to Watling Street, according to the treaty between Guthrum and King Alfred.  For 10 points-what region of 10th-century England took its name from the prevalence of Scandinavian judicial custom?",
    "answer": "(the) Danelaw"
  },
  {
    "question": "This city's main legislative building has an enameled ceremonial door, whose lower half depicts the Tree of Knowledge on green tiles.  Open rectangular sections show solar movement in this city's Tower of Shadows.  Sculptures made of recycled waste are found in this city's rock garden, founded by Nek (*) Chand.  Albert Mayer and Maciej Nowicki [MAY-shitch NOH-vuh-kee] worked on this planned city, which includes the Open Hand Monument.  Le Corbusier [luh kor-boo-zee-ay] helped to design-for 10 points-what capital of Haryana [HAH-ree-AH-nah] and Punjab [POON-jahb] in India?",
    "answer": "Chandigarh [CHUN-dee-gur]"
  },
  {
    "question": "The U.S. special envoy to this country, Daniel Lewis Foote, resigned in 2021, citing the \"inhumane\" policies of the Biden administration.  In a resignation letter , State Department official Harold Koh criticized the use of Title 42 against people from this country.  Thousands of migrants, mostly from this country, (*)  camped under a bridge in Del Rio, Texas in September 2021.  For 10 points -name this country whose nationals were given temporary protected status in the U.S. after a 2010 earthquake.",
    "answer": "Haiti (or Republic of Haiti or Republique d'Haïti or Repiblik d' Ayiti)"
  },
  {
    "question": "People of this ethnicity built walled villages with tulou [\"too-low\"] houses.  These people's \"hill songs,\" also called \"nine airs and 18 tunes,\" reflect a likely origin in the Central Plain.  Coasts depopulated by imperial edict were re-settled by these people, giving them the name \"guest families\" during the (*)  Kangxi [kahng-shee] era.  Immigrants of this ethnicity in Mauritius and Singapore feuded with countrymen who spoke Cantonese.  Sun Yat-Sen [soon-yaht-sen] and Hong Xiuquan [hong shoo-chwahn] were members of-for 10 points-what Southern Chinese ethnicity?",
    "answer": "Hakkas (or Hakka Han; accept guest families or guest family or guest households before \"guest\"; prompt on \"Chinese\" or \"Han Chinese\" before \"Chinese\"; do not accept or prompt on \"Hokkien\" or \"Cantonese\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This man chaired the Freedom Fund Drive for the NAACP and founded the Freedom National Bank to advance his theory of \"the ballot and the buck.\"  After John F. Kennedy told this man \"I haven't had a chance to know many negroes,\" he resigned from the (*)  New York Post and Chock Full O' Nuts to campaign for Richard Nixon.  For 10 points -name this civil rights activist who, on April 15, 1947, took the field for the Brooklyn Dodgers.",
    "answer": "Jackie Robinson (or Jack Roosevelt Robinson)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the first chapter of a memoir, this author hallucinates giant udders when he is beaten by his mother for setting fire to his grandmother's house.  That memoir's second section, \"The Horror and the Glory,\" relates how this author joined the John (*) Reed Society and the Communist Party in Chicago.  In a novel by this author, Mary Dalton is smothered by Bigger Thomas.  For 10 points -name this author of Black Boy and Native Son.",
    "answer": "Richard (Nathaniel) Wright"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this city, a character gives a rosary to a woman who saved her from being burned for witchcraft in the aria \"Voce di donna\" [VOH-chay dee DOH-nuh].  Gamelan -like music accompanies a mute young male dancer in a Benjamin Britten opera set in this city.  A n opera set in this city depicts various times of day in the (*) \"Dance of the Hours.\"  La Gioconda [lah joh-KAWN-duh] is set in-for 10 points-what Italian city, the setting of Gilbert and Sullivan's The Gondoliers?",
    "answer": "Venice (or Venezia) [The Benjamin Britten opera is Death in Venice.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This performer describes being \"stuck with my fam, I can't get out\" in a music video co-directed by his mother.  He berates men named Martin, Ben, and John, who form the group Please Don't Destroy, in a song featuring Taylor Swift titled \"Three Sad Virgins.\"  This man was slapped by (*)  Questlove while performing an annoying rap with Timothée Chalamet [\"timothy SHALL-uh-may\"] in a 2020 sketch.  For 10 points -name this tattooed star of Saturday Night Live.",
    "answer": "Pete Davidson (or Peter Michael Davidson)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This man wrote in favor of \"value-free\" research in an essay on \"Objectivity in the Social Sciences.\"  A distinction between \"instrumental rationality\" and \"value rationality\" was first mad e by this man, who described politics as \"the slow (*) boring of hard boards\" in an 1919 essay analyzing politics as Beruf [\"be-ROOF\"], or a \"vocation.\"  For 10 points -name this German sociologist who wrote The Protestant Ethic and the Spirit of Capitalism.",
    "answer": "Max Weber [VAY-bur] (or Maximilian Karl Emil Weber)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The oxidation of volatile organic compounds like tree resin generates the secondary organic type of these systems.  In the atmosphere, these systems scatter sunlight and create nuclei for cloud (*) condensation. Particulate matter is one of these suspensions that causes air pollution.  For 10 points -name these colloids [KAH-loyds] which consist of solids or liquids suspended in a gas, which are produced by spray cans.",
    "answer": "aerosols (prompt on \"colloids\" before \"colloids\"; prompt on \"suspensions\" before \"suspensions\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dorothy Sayers suggested that this figure's red, yellow, and black coloration represents the human races.  The waist of this lord of Giudecca [joo-DEK-kah] is surrounded by the icy river Cocytus [koh-\"SIGH\"-tuss].  Two men grasp this figure's hair and (*) climb down his body, emerging in the Southern Hemisphere.  In Canto 34 of the Inferno, Dante [DAHN-tay] and Virgil [VUR-jil] encounter-for 10 points-what three-faced giant arch-traitor who was expelled from Heaven?",
    "answer": "Lucifer (or Lucifero; or Dis; or Beelzebub; accept Satan; prompt on \"(the) Devil\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the 1670s, this number of \"feudatories\" rebelled against the Kangxi [kahng-shee] Emperor of China's Qing [ching] Dynasty.  The minister Charlie Soong had this number of daughters, who all married powerful men in the Republic of China.  \"Minsheng,\" or social welfare, is among this many (*)  principles put forth by Sun Yat-Sen.  After the Han Dynasty, Cao Cao [tsow tsow] lived while-for 10 points-what number of \"kingdoms\" feuded, as told in a classical Romance?",
    "answer": "3 (or san; accept Revolt of the Three Feudatories or Three Principles of the People or Three Kingdoms period or Romance of the Three Kingdoms or sanguo yanyi)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ten of these people with different names form one supply pile in the Dominion expansion Dark Ages.  The first collectible miniatures game is named for a \"Mage\" variety of these people.  Cities and these people name an expansion to The Settlers of (*) Catan.  In a common chess opening, white moves a piece of this name on their second turn from g1 [\"G one\"] to f3 [\"F three\"].  For 10 points -what people name a chess piece that moves in an 'L' shape?",
    "answer": "knights (accept Mage Knight or Catan: Cities and Knights or King's knight opening)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a play whose title ends in this word, Gratiana is the mother of the protagonist, who uses the name Piato while working for Lussurioso, the son of the duke who poisoned his lover.  A play whose title ends in this word was attributed once to Cyril Tourneur but now to (*) Thomas Middleton.  Don Andrea is avenged in an Elizabethan play whose title ends in-for 10 points-what word that follows \"Spanish\" in a Thomas Kyd title?",
    "answer": "tragedy (accept The Revenger's Tragedy or The Spanish Tragedy)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The U.S. special envoy to this country, Daniel Lewis Foote, resigned in 2021, citing the \"inhumane\" policies of the Biden administration.  Thousands of migrants, mostly from this country, camped under a bridge in Del Rio, (*) Texas in September 2021.  This country's nationals were given temporary protected status in the U.S. after a 2010 earthquake.  For 10 points -name this Caribbean nation that is led from Port-au-Prince [\"port-oh-PRINCE\"].",
    "answer": "Haiti (or Republic of Haiti or Republique d'Haïti or Repiblik d' Ayiti)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This substance's namesake \"basic protein\" is mutated in shiverer mice, which model leukodystrophy.  This substance, whose major components include galactocerebrosides, is attacked in AIDP, a form of Guillain - (*) Barré [GEE-yan bah-RAY] syndrome.  This substance is contained by oligode ndrocytes and Schwann cells, and gaps in it allow saltatory conduction.  White matter is rich in -for 10 points-what substance that insulates axons?",
    "answer": "myelin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The extent of this region can be defined by place names known as \"Grimston hybrids\" and the spread of land divisions called \"wapentakes\" [WAH-\"pen-takes\"].  This region's \"Five Boroughs\" were conquered by Edward the Elder.  This was the region (*)  north and east of a line defined in the treaty between Guthrum and King Alfred.  For 10 points-what region of 10th-century England took its name from the prevalence of Scandinavian judicial custom?",
    "answer": "(the) Danelaw"
  },
  {
    "question": "This country is home to a building with open rectangular sections showing solar movement, the T ower of Shadows.  Albert Mayer and Maciej Nowicki [MAY-shitch NOH-vuh-kee] worked on a planned city in this country that includes the Open Hand Monument designed by Le (*) Corbusier [luh kor-boo-zee-ay].  In a building in this country, a white marble dome covers the tomb of a woman named Mumtaz [MOOM-tahz].  For 10 points-Chandigarh [CHUN-dee-gur] is in what country, the site of the Taj Mahal [TAHZH muh-\"HALL\"]?",
    "answer": "India (or Republic of India or Bharat(iya) Ganarajya)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Jeffreys-Bullen model of this body was a precursor to the PREM [prem] or \"preliminary reference model\" for this body.  84% of this body's volume is in a layer that contains the 660 kilometer (*)  discontinuity and 410 kilometer discontinuity.  Cold slabs sometimes sink from this body's surface all the way to the CMB or Gutenberg [GOO-tin-burg] discontinuity, as revealed by seismic tomography [tuh-MAH-gruh-fee].  For 10 points -name this tectonically active planet.",
    "answer": "Earth (accept Jeffreys-Bullen Earth model or Preliminary Reference Earth Model)"
  },
  {
    "question": "At this battle, fighting took place at Sari Bair [sah-REE bah-YEER] and Chunuk Bair [CHOO-nuk bah-YEER] during the August Offensive, during which John Monash led a key attack.  The Lone Pine was a landmark in this battle, which included landings at Cape Helles [hel-ESS] and Suvla [SOOV-lah] Bay.  April (*)  25, this battle's first day, is commemorated as ANZAC Day in New Zealand and Australia.  For 10 points -name this World War I battle fought for a Turkish peninsula.",
    "answer": "Battle of Gallipoli [guh-LIH-puh-lee] (or Gallipoli campaign, accept Battle of Canakkale or Canakkale Savasi; accept Dardanelles campaign)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the U.S., the siku is often known as this country's namesake \"pan flute.\"  This country was the birthplace of the cajón [kah-\"HONE\"], a box-like percussion instrument that is sat on and slapped.  Chinese immigrants invented chifa [CHEE-fah] cuisine in this country, which disputes the invention of the seafood dish (*) ceviche [seh-VEE-chay] with its northern neighbor, Ecuador.  For 10 points -name this country whose cultural hubs are Cusco [KOOZ-koh] and Lima [LEE-mah].",
    "answer": "Peru (or Republic of Peru or República del Perú)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A goddess with this creature's form was worshiped at Dendera and wore a menat necklace.  The eight Heh gods are shown supporting Nut, who carries Ra on her back as she takes this creature's form, in a book titled for a \"heavenly\" one.  The (*)  lion-headed Sekhmet is identified with Hathor, who has the head of-for 10 points-what animal, allowing her to hold a uraeus [yoo-REE-uss] between her horns?",
    "answer": "cow (accept The Book of the Heavenly Cow; prompt on \"cattle\" or \"bovine\"; do not accept or prompt on \"bull\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "The total momentum over the total charge of these things is their rigidity, a measure of how easily they can be guided by magnets.  Wigglers periodically deflect these things that are kept circulating in storage rings, as seen at the (*) Tevatron [TEV-uh-tron] and LHC.  A fixed target may be struc k by-for 10 points-what collimated streams of particles in accelerators, which share their name with the output of a laser?",
    "answer": "particle beams (before \"Tevatron,\" accept proton beams or electron beams or positron beams or ion beams; accept antiproton beams before \"LHC\"; before \"streams,\" prompt on \"(charged) particles\" with \"the particles are moving as part of what things?\"; before \"Tevatron,\" prompt with \"the particles are moving as part of what things?\" on \"protons\" or \"electrons\" or \"positrons\" or \"ions\"; before \"LHC,\" prompt on \"antiprotons\" with \"the particles are moving as part of what things?\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1989 Gunther Schuller revised and premiered a two-hour long work by this musician called Epitaph.  This bandleader formed a rhythm section with Horace Parlan and Dannie Richmond in his  \"Jazz Workshop.\"  He mocked the racist governor of Arkansas in \"Fables of (*) Faubus,\" but the lyrics were removed on an album that follows his name with the words \"Ah Um.\"  \"Goodbye Pork Pie Hat\" was written by -for 10 points-what jazz bassist?",
    "answer": "Charles Mingus (accept Mingus, Ah Um)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A narrator works with the arthritic Russian ex-soldier Boris in one of these two cities before befriending the tramp Paddy Jacques in the other.  After spending 18 years imprisoned in one of these cities, a former doctor obsessed with shoemaking travels to the other with his daughter (*) Lucie Manette.  George Orwell wrote a memoir titled \"down and out in\"-for 10 points-what settings of Charles Dickens's A Tale of Two Cities?",
    "answer": "Paris   London (accept answers in either order; accept Down and Out in Paris and London)"
  },
  {
    "question": "One essay by this thinker argues that even Bernard Mandeville understood the power of compassion by citing Mandeville's description of a child eaten alive by a pig.  This thinker argued that humans are distinguished from animals by \"perfectibility,\" which allows for the rise of (*) amour-propre [ah-moor PROP-ruh], in his Discourse on Inequality.  For 10 points -name this Swiss-born 18th-century philosopher who also wrote The Social Contract.",
    "answer": "Jean-Jacques Rousseau [roo-SOH]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Due to worsening dementia, this man routinely sent William Day in his place to Cabinet meetings, which, along with his anti-interventionism, precipitated his resignation as Secretary of State at the start of the Spanish-American War.  Earlier, this (*)  Ohio senator sponsored a bill targeting \"restraint of trade\" that was severely weakened in the E. C. Knight case.  For 10 points -identify this namesake of an 1890 antitrust law.",
    "answer": "John Sherman (accept Sherman Antitrust Act)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This man served as the so-called \"post-box of Europe\" in distributing the works of René Descartes [reh-nay day-kart].  This man's treatise Harmonie universelle [arr-moh-NEE oo-nee-vair-SELL] earned him the title \"father of acoustics.\"  The Euclid - (*) Euler [YOOK-lid-OY-lur] theorem relates perfect numbers to numbers named for this man that are searched for by the GIMPS project, the first four of which are 3, 7, 31, and 127.  For 10 points -what Frenchman names primes one less than a power of two?",
    "answer": "Marin Mersenne (or Marin Mersennus; accept Mersenne primes)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The corpse of a man who held this position was exhumed by Stephen VI [\"the sixth\"] and put on trial in the Cadaver Synod.  The \"Babylonian Captivity\" began in 1309 when (*)  Clement V [\"the fifth\"] took this post.  During the Western Schism, both Avignon [ah-veen-yohn] and Rome claimed to host-for 10 points-what Catholic leadership role?",
    "answer": "pope (accept papacy or leader of the Papal States)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This character sees a group of men playing \"nine-pins\" who may be part of Henry Hudson's old crew.  This man is surprised to discover that villagers no longer honor George III [\"the third\"] and that his beard is a (*) foot long.  For 10 points -what character in a Washington Irving story sleeps for 20 years?",
    "answer": "Rip Van Winkle (accept either underlined portion)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This island's namesake strait was the focus of two \"crises\" in the 1950s.  The Penghu [PUNG-hoo] Islands are directly west of this island, which was given a name by Portuguese explorers meaning \"beautiful island.\" (*)  Formosa [fore-MOH-suh] is an alternate name of-for 10 points-what island home to Taipei [TYE-pay] 101?",
    "answer": "Taiwan (accept Formosa before \"Formosa\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This civilization created the \"priest king\" and \"dancing girl\" statues, which were found at a city whose name means \"mound of the dead.\"  Mohenjo -Daro [moh-HEN-joh-DAR-oh] and (*) Harappa [huh-RAH-puh] were major cities of-for 10 points-what ancient civilization that developed along the course of a river in what is now Pakistan?",
    "answer": "Indus (River) Valley Civilization (or Indus Valley Culture; accept Harappan Civilization or Culture before \"Harappa\"; prompt on \"IVC\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "As this novel begins, the narrator recalls how Buddy Willard once showed her a corpse.  Doreen works with this novel's protagonist at Ladies' Day magazine.  After sinking into a depression, (*)  Esther Greenwood is given electroshock treatment in-for 10 points-what novel by Sylvia Plath?",
    "answer": "The Bell Jar"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pencil and paper ready.  Alan needs to know t he value of x, given that the mean average of the three numbers [read slowly] 55, 62, and x equals 60.  Since the mean is the sum of the values divided by the number of values, he knows 55 plus 62 plus x equals 3 times 60. (*) For 10 points-find the value of x.",
    "answer": "x = 63 [M = (55 + 62 + x)/3 = 60, so 117 + x = 180, and x = 63]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This island group includes the Andreanof Islands, which are home to Adak, the southernmost town in the state to which these islands belong.  Kiska [KIS-kuh] and Attu [AH-too], islands in this group, were occupied by the (*) Japanese in World War II.  For 1 0 points-what island chain extends southwest from Alaska?",
    "answer": "Aleutian Islands"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this game, the player can fight the spider-like Nosk in the dark area of Deepnest.  This game's character Hornet was announced as the protagonist of this game's sequel, (*)  Silksong.  The player uses a nail  to fight insects in-for 10 points-what 2017 Metroidvania game set in Hallownest?",
    "answer": "Hollow Knight"
  },
  {
    "question": "This body is the larger of the two bodies at the center of the Theia [THAY-uh] hypothesis.  This planet's axial tilt of (*) 23.4 degrees is stabilized by one tidally locked moon, which orbits it every 27 days.  A nitrogen -rich atmosphere surrounds-for 10 points-what third-closest planet to the Sun?",
    "answer": "Earth"
  },
  {
    "question": "A petition urging Congress to \"move on\" from this process inspire d the name of MoveOn.org [\"move on dot org\"].  Under Article 1, this process involves a Senate trial at which a (*)  two-thirds majority can convict.  \"High crimes and misdemeanors\" may trigger-for 10 points-what process of forced removal from office?",
    "answer": "impeachment (or impeaching the president; accept answers indicating impeachment of Bill Clinton)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This president criticized defense spending in his Chance for Peace speech  and, in a farewell address, warned of the military-industrial complex.  This president created NASA after the U.S.S.R. launched (*)  Sputnik in 1957.  The Korean War ended under -for 10 points-what president and general?",
    "answer": "Dwight D(avid) Eisenhower [\"EYE\"-zen-how-ur] (prompt on \"Ike\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Surgical removal of this C cell-containing organ risks damage to the recurrent laryngeal nerve.  Hundreds of tyrosine residues in a protein in this organ react with (*)  iodine to form the hormones T3 and T4.  Goiter is enlargement of-for 10 points-what butterfly-shaped gland in the neck?",
    "answer": "thyroid gland"
  },
  {
    "question": "The last work in this composer's Opus 10 features long descending runs of sixteenth notes for the left hand.  A prelude [PRAY-lood] by this man featuring repeated A flats has the nickname (*)  \"Raindrop.\"  The \"Revolutionary\" Étude [ay-TOOD] is by-for 10 points-what piano virtuoso and composer born in Poland?",
    "answer": "Frédéric (François) Chopin [fray-day-REEK shoh-PAN] (or Fryderyk Franciszek Szopen)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Robert Peel refused to become prime minister because this ruler would not fire six courtiers in the Bedchamber Crisis.  This ruler always wore black after her husband, Prince (*)  Albert, died.  E dward VII [\"the seventh\"] succeeded her in 1901.  For 10 points -who was Britain's queen for most of the 1800s?",
    "answer": "Queen Victoria (or Alexandrina Victoria Hanover)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Harold Thomas designed a flag representing these people whose copyright was purchased by a national government in 2022.  The \"history wars\" debate concerned the effect of colonization on these people and the (*) Torres Strait Islanders.  For 10 points -name these indigenous people of Australia.",
    "answer": "Aboriginal Australians (or Aboriginals or Australian Aborigines)"
  },
  {
    "question": "These numbers are the opposite of their own conjugate.  These nu mbers are shown on the y-axis of an Argand diagram.  The solutions to \" x squared equals (*) -4\" are this type of number.  For 10 points -name these numbers that are added to a real number to form a complex number.",
    "answer": "(purely) imaginary numbers (accept imaginary parts; prompt on \"multiples of i\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This event's start was signaled by a declaration that \"This meeting can do nothing further to save the country.\"  After this event, Lord North's government passe d the (*) Intolerable Acts.  The Sons of Liberty led-for 10 points-what 1773 event in which British goods were dumped into a harbor?",
    "answer": "Boston Tea Party (prompt on \"Tea Party\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This author described the vacationing Anna, who walks her Pomeranian [pah-muh-RAIN-ee-un] along the seaside, in his story \"The Lady with the Dog.\"  In a 1904 play by this author, the servant Firs [feerz] collapses while axes hack down the title (*) fruit trees.  For 10 points -what Russian dramatist wrote The Cherry Orchard?",
    "answer": "Anton (Pavlovich) Chekhov [\"CHECK-off\"]"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an alternating current circuit, the peak value of this quantity is double its time -averaged value since it goes as the square of the sinusoidal current or voltage.  For a resis tor, current times (*) voltage gives-for 10 points-what rate of energy transfer measured in watts?",
    "answer": "power"
  },
  {
    "question": "The governor of New Mexico, Michelle Lujan [LOO-hahn] Grisham, became licensed in this profession in January 2022.  In 2021 Miguel (*)  Cardona advised officials to use federal funding to address shortages in-for 10 points-what profession, in which staffing issues have increased the need for substitutes?",
    "answer": "teacher (or educator or teaching or education; accept elementary school teacher or substitute teacher)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In ancient Greece, these animals were the most common sacrifice to the god Hecate [HEK-uh-tee].  One of these animals named Argos dies shortly after recognizing Odysseus [oh-DIH-see-uss] in the Odyssey.  A (*)  three-headed one of these animals guards the Greek Underworld.  Cerberus [SUR-buh-russ] is-for 10 points-what type of canine?",
    "answer": "dogs (accept Canis familiaris; prompt on \"canine(s)\" before \"canine\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This letter, followed by \"dot com,\" originally named the company that became PayPal.  Barr bodies are inactive forms of a (*) chromosome named for this letter, which names a \"generation\" between Baby Boomers and Millennials.  For 10 points -name this letter that, on a treasure map, \"marks the spot.\"",
    "answer": "X (accept X.com or X chromosome or Generation X or X marks the spot)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this play, a comedic servant imagines himself the \"porter of hell-gate\" after hearing persistent knocking.  A woman in this play tries to wash off imaginary bloodstains while (*)  sleepwalking.  For 10 points -name this Shakespeare play in which king Duncan is murdered by a Scottish general.",
    "answer": "Macbeth (or The Tragedy of Macbeth)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1987, to prevent this animal species' extinction, all surviving members in the wild were captured.  These long-lived birds in genus Gymnogyps [\"GYM-no-jips\"], which are black except for white patches under their wings, feed on (*) carrion.  For 10 points -what \"California\" birds are North America's largest?",
    "answer": "California condor(s) (accept Gymnogyps californianus)"
  },
  {
    "question": "At the end of this novel, its protagonist admonishes his sons that \"it is the end of a family when they begin to sell the land.\"  A girl in this novel, who is mentally -challenged because she was starved as an infant, is called \"Poor Fool.\"  This novel's protagonist pulls a (*)  rickshaw after he is forced to move to the city with his wife, O-Lan.  For 10 points -name this novel about the farmer Wang Lung, written by Pearl S. Buck.",
    "answer": "The Good Earth"
  },
  {
    "question": "This religion inspired Nanban [nahn-bahn] art.  Bernard Petitjean [peh-tee-zhawn] discovered so-called \"hidden\" practitioners of this faith who worshiped a figure disguised as a Buddhist Bodhisattva [boh-dih-SUT-vuh] Kannon.  Suspected practitioners of this faith were made to step on images calle d (*) fumi-e [foo-mee ay]. The 26 Martyrs practiced this faith, which was outlawed by the Tokugawa [toh-koo-gah-wah] shogunate [\"SHOW-gun\"-ate].  For 10 points-what faith was spread to Japan by Francis Xavier, a Jesuit?",
    "answer": "Christianity (accept Roman Catholicism)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In myths from this civilization, two \"sycamores of turquoise\" stand at the eastern gate of heaven.  In various cities, these people prayed to sets of gods called the Ogdoad [AHG-doh-ad] and the Ennead.  These people held that in the underworld Du'at [doo-AHT], the serpent (*) Apep [AY-pep] fought nightly with the driver of the solar barge.  The scarab [\"SCARE\"-ub] beetle was sacred to-for 10 points-what ancient society that believed descendants of Ra ruled as pharaohs?",
    "answer": "(Ancient) Egypt(ians) (accept Old Kingdom or Middle Kingdom or New Kingdom)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This element's chloride salt forms an orange mineral called sylvite [SIL-vyte] left over as evaporite [uh-VAP-uh-\"rite\"] in extremely dry conditions.  The decay of a radioisotope of this element to argon [AR-gahn] is used in radioactive dating of rocks.  This element's nitrate [\"NITE-rate\"] salt, called (*) saltpeter, is an oxidizer found in gunpowder.  For 10 points -what alkali [AL-kuh-lye] metal below sodium on the periodic table is found in bananas?",
    "answer": "potassium (or K)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This character is more skilled at making clothes than \"those of Ypres [eep] and of Ghent.\"  In one speech, this character notes that both Jacob and Abraham married more than once.  This character describes a knight whom Queen Guinevere gives a year and a day to discover what (*)  women most desire, and who finds the answer is \"sovereignty\" [SAHV-run-tee].  Alyson is one possi ble name of-for 10 points-what character from The Canterbury Tales?",
    "answer": "The Wife of Bath (accept Alyson or Alys before \"Alyson\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 20th-century composer from this country called for a player to scrape piano strings  in his piece The Banshee.  Henry Cowell was a composer from this country, where Erich [\"Eric\"] Korngold wrote Captain Blood and other (*) film scores after leaving Austria.  A composer from this country wrote a ballet that begins and ends on \"The Open Prairie.\"  For 10 points -what country was home to the composer of Billy the Kid, Aaron Copland?",
    "answer": "United States of America or U.S.A. (accept any underlined portion)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Combining the Standard Model with a quantum mechanical explanation of this force would produce a \"theory of everything.\"  Curvature of light by this force causes its namesake \"lensing.\"  In 2016, the (*)  LIGO [\"LIE-go\"] experiment announced the detection of waves named for this force produced by a black hole merger.  Objects on Earth accelerate at 9.8 meters per second -squared as a result of-for 10 points-what attractive force?",
    "answer": "gravity or gravitational force (accept gravitational lens(ing) or gravity waves or gravitational waves or gravitational radiation)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This country contains the namesake type site of the Iron Age La Tène [\"ten\"] culture, which is along the coast of its Lake Neuchâtel [noo-shah-TELL].  This country's land corresponds to most of the ancient homeland of the Helvetii [hel-VEE-shee-\"eye\"] people.  With its western neighbor, this country owns the (*)  Jura [JOO-rah] Mountains, the namesake of the Jurassic Period and of this country's canton of Jura.  Bern [\"burn\"] and Zurich [ZOO-rik] are cities in-for 10 points-what Alpine country?",
    "answer": "Switzerland (or Swiss Confederation or Schweiz or Schweizerische Eidgenossenschaft or Confederation Suisse or Confederazione Svizzera or Confederaziun Svizra)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Jean [zhahn] de Metz guarded this person on a journey to Chinon [shee-nahn] to meet with a king.  In the siege of Compiegne [kom-p'yen], this commander was captured by Burgundians.  This person carried no we apons except a banner during a campaign in which Charles VII [\"the seventh\"] retook (*) Rheims [rem] and lifted the siege of Orleans [or-lay-AHN].  At this age 16, this person received a vision telling her to \"go to France.\"  For 10 points-what female saint fought in the Hundred Years' War?",
    "answer": "(Saint) Joan of Arc (or Jeanne d'Arc; prompt on \"Joan\" or \"Jeanne\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This artist showed himself in a brown coat and black hat, holding a paintbrush, in his Self-Portrait with Palette.  This painter created a scene in which a server seemingly stares at the viewer, creating an impossible image in a mirror behind her.  In a canvas by this man, a (*)  nude woman and two men sit beside a spilled basket.  A Bar at the Folies-Bergère [foh-lee-bair-ZHAIR] is by-for 10 points-what French painter of Luncheon on the Grass?",
    "answer": "Édouard Manet [ayd-WAR man-AY] (do not accept or prompt on \"Monet\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This play ends by warning \"we cannot call a mortal being happy / before he's passed beyond life free from pain.\"  The title character of this play uses gold pins taken from the clothes of his dead wife to (*) blind himself.  In this play, Creon reports an oracle told him a plague ravages Thebes because Laius's killer is unknown.  For 10 points -name this Sophocles [SAH-fuh-kleez] tragedy about a king who killed his father and married his mother.",
    "answer": "Oedipus Rex [EH-duh-puss \"wrecks\"] (or Oidipous Tyrannos or Oedipus the King)"
  },
  {
    "question": "While this politician was minister of finance in 2020, his ministry was plagued by the Wirecard scandal.  This politician formed the most recent \"traffic light\" coalition involving the Free Democratic Party and the Greens.  This member of the (*)  Social Democratic Party took office on December 8, 2021, succeeding a woman who had led her country since 2005.  For 10 points -who succeeded Angela Merkel [AHN-geh-lah MAIR-kul] as chancellor of Germany?",
    "answer": "Olaf Scholz"
  },
  {
    "question": "This period titles a book by historian Diarmaid MacCulloch [dee-AR-mayd muh-KULL-uh] that won the 2004 Wolfson Prize.  This period was launched in part by conflict over the illegitimacy of the Treasury of Merit and the sola scriptura doctrine that (*) biblical text is the only source of religious truth.  The 1517 posting of the 95 Theses by Martin Luther is generally said to start-for 10 points-what period during which Protestantism began?",
    "answer": "Protestant Reformation (accept The Reformation: A History; do not accept or prompt on \"Reform (Period)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Irving Wardle suggested that this category of plays has a subtype filled  with \"menace\" in a review of Harold Pinter's play The Birthday Party.  This term appears in the title of a Shakespeare play about two pairs of twins, whose similarities lead to many (*) \"errors.\"  The \"Old\" type of this play includes The Clouds and other plays by Aristophanes [air-ih-STAH-fuh-neez].  For 10 points -what type of theater is defined by happy endings and humor?",
    "answer": "comedy (or comedies; accept comedy or comedies of menace or The Comedy of Errors or Old Comedy)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In machine learning, models that fit test data too closely have low values of bias and high values of this property in a namesake \"tradeoff.\" For a Poisson [pwah-sawn] distribution, this property is equal to both the expected value and mean.  In general, this property is the (*)  expected value of the squared differences from the mean.  This property equals the standard deviation squared.  For 10 points -name this measure of spread.",
    "answer": "variance (prompt on \"sigma squared\"; do not accept or prompt on \"sigma\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 1995 film, this actor's character is called \"Sonny Jim\" by a villain who resembles Samuel Parrish, the hunter Van Pelt.  In a 1992 film, his character's first line is announcing that 10,000 years gives you \"such a crick in the neck.\"  This actor played the adult version of Alan, who grows up while trapped in a (*)  board game in the film Jumanji [joo-MAHN-jee].  For 10 points -what comedian voiced the Genie in the animated film Aladdin?",
    "answer": "Robin (McLaurin) Williams"
  },
  {
    "question": "This city's \"Soccer City\" stadium hosted the final match of the 2010 World Cup.  In the 1950s this city's majority-Black suburb of Sophiatown was destroyed and rebuilt as \"Triomf\" [TREE-ahmf].  It is the most-populous city in the Witwatersrand [VIT-vah-turz-rahnd] region.  In 1976 this city's suburb of (*)  Soweto [soh-WAY-toh] was the site of an uprising protesting the use of Afrikaans [af-rih-KAHNZ] in education.  For 10 points-what most-populous city in South Africa is nicknamed \"Jo'burg\"?",
    "answer": "Johannesburg [joh-HAH-nuss-burg] (or eGoli; accept Jo'burg before \"Jo'burg\"; prompt on \"Jozi\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Robert Bellah used this adjective to group many American social rituals as a type of \"religion.\"  This adjective partly titles an 1849 essay claiming \"That government is best which governs not at all,\" which recounts a night spent in jail for refusal to pay (*) taxes.  Torts are legal wrongs in this type of law.  Henry David Thoreau praised-for 10 points-what form of \"disobedience,\" which also names a type of equalizing \"rights\"?",
    "answer": "civil (accept Civil Religion in America; accept Civil Disobedience; accept civil law; accept civil rights; accept American before \"American\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pencil and paper ready.  Miranda needs to know the te nth term of the arithmetic [\"air\"-ith-MET-ik] sequence whose fourth term is 8 and whose sixth term is 16.  She can either write out the entire sequence up to the tenth term, or realize that the sequence must increase by 8 every (*) two terms.  For 10 point s-find the tenth term of the arithmetic sequence whose fourth term is 8 and whose sixth term is 16.",
    "answer": "32 [Since the sequence went up by 16 - 8 = 8 between the fourth and sixth terms, it must have a similar increase between the sixth and eighth terms, and the eight and tenth terms, respectively-yielding a tenth term of 16 + 8 + 8 = 16 + 16 = 32.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "A ship named for this state was sunk by the USS Kearsarge [keer-SAR-jee] near Cherbourg [shair-borg] and was a commerce raider that took 65 Union ships.  Before moving to Richmond, the capital of the Confederacy was this state's capital city.  During a battle in this sta te, David (*) Farragut shouted \"Damn the torpedoes, full speed ahead!\" while capturing a port on the Gulf of Mexico.  For 10 points -in what state did the Battle of Mobile Bay take place?",
    "answer": "Alabama (accept AL [\"A-L\"])"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aaron Director founded a \"journal of law and\" this other field whose frequent contributors have included Richard Posner and Gary Becker.  This field provides the name of the most popular textbook by Paul Samuelson.  David (*)  Card won half of the 2021 Nobel Memorial Prize given in this field.  The \"dismal science\" is a nickname of-for 10 points-what field whose grounding concepts include supply and demand?",
    "answer": "economics (accept economic science or econ; accept Journal of Law and Economics; accept Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In June 2021 thousands of pages of this person's emails were released after The Washington Post and BuzzFeed News made FOIA [F-O-I-A] requests.  Marjorie Taylor Greene sponsored a 2021 act to reduce this person's salary to $0.  Since (*)  1984 this man has served as the director of NIAID [NYE-ad], the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases.  For 10 points -name this doctor who serves as chief medical advisor to Joe Biden.",
    "answer": "Anthony (Stephen) Fauci"
  },
  {
    "question": "U.S. victory in this battle is an attributed miracle of Our Lady of Prompt Succor.  Edward Pakenham [PAY-ken-ham] died leading one side in this battle.  U.S. allies at this battle included the Choctaw [\"CHALK\"-taw] chief Pushmataha [\"push\"-MAH-tuh-HAH] and the pardoned pirate Jean (*) Lafitte [zhawn lah-FEET].  This battle was fought weeks after the Treaty of Ghent formally ended the War of 1812.  For 10 points -in what battle did Andrew Jackson defeat a British attack on a Louisiana city?",
    "answer": "Battle of New Orleans"
  },
  {
    "question": "These proteins attack surface molecules on red blood cells durin g the autoagglutination [\"auto\"-uh-GLOO-tuh-NAY-shun] triggered by blood transfusion rejection.  During a type I [\"one\"] hypersensitivity reaction, the IgE [\"I-G-E\"] isotype [\"EYE-suh-type\"] of these proteins binds to (*) allergens [AL-ur-jens].  These pro teins are secreted by plasma B cells as part of the adaptive immune system.  For 10 points -name these Y-shaped proteins that trigger an immune response by binding to antigens.",
    "answer": "antibodies or antibody (or immunoglobulins)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This event supposedly began in Europe because of a tactic used by Mongol forces at the siege of Caffa.  While fleeing this event, Boccaccio [boh-KAH-choh] wrote The Decameron [dih-KAM-uh-run]. (*) Yersinia pestis [yur-SIH-nee-uh PES-tiss] caused this event, which killed up to 50% of Europe's population.  F or 10 points-name this 14th-century pandemic.",
    "answer": "Black Death or bubonic plague (or Great Plague or Great Pestilence; accept pneumonic plague or septicemic plague or Black Plague; prompt on \"plague\") [While besieging Caffa, Mongol troops supposedly fl ung plague-infected animal corpses over the city's walls.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "A location on this body that was named after Octavia Butler in 2021 is within the Jezero [JEZ-uh-roh] crater.  A vehicle that has been on this body for more than 300 sols [\"souls\"] carried the (*) robotic helicopter Ingenuity.  In 2021 NASA's Perseverance rover landed-for 10 points-on what \"red planet\"?",
    "answer": "Mars"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"societies\" of this class of animals were the subject of a 1971 book by biologist E. O. Wilson.  Within this class, eusociality [\"you-sociality\"] is characteristic of orders like Hymenoptera [HY-muh-NAHP-tuh-ruh] and can be seen in their (*) colonies.  For 10 points -what class of six-legged invertebrates includes bees and ants?",
    "answer": "insects (or Insecta)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Before this president's inauguration, his life was threatened in the Baltimore Plot.  This man won the presidency by defeating John Breckinridge, the southern Democrats' nominee, and his old (*)  Illinois rival, Stephen Douglas.  For 10 points -what 16th president led the Union in the Civil War?",
    "answer": "Abraham Lincoln (or Abe Lincoln)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This activity nicknames a four-day war in 1969 between Honduras and El Salvador.  A 2015 investigation into corruption in this activity led Sepp Blatter to resign as head of an (*)  international governing body of it.  For 10 points-name this activity organized by CONCACAF [KAHN-kuh-kaff] and FIFA [FEE-fuh].",
    "answer": "soccer (or association football; accept Soccer War or Football War or playing soccer)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This character utters his final words, \"look at me,\" after failing to escape from an \"enchanted cage\" with in the Shrieking Shack.  He becomes alienated from his childhood friend Lily (*)  Evans when he calls her a \"Mudblood.\"  For 10 points -name this Slytherin [\"SLITHER-in\"] who teaches Harry Potter about potions.",
    "answer": "Severus [SEH-vuh-russ] Snape (accept either underlined portion) [Snape says \"look at me\" to Harry, whose green eyes are nearly identical to those of Harry's mother, Lily.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Princedoms without strong heirs were absorbed into this colony via the doctrine of lapse.  Grease -coated cartridges sparked the Sepoy [SEE-poy] Mutiny in this colony during its (*) \"Raj\" [rahzh] period.  For 10 points-name this \"jewel in the crown\" of the British Empire, which governed it until 1947 from Calcutta [kal-KUH-tuh].",
    "answer": "British India (accept the British Raj before \"Raj\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This actor played a detective who rescues Dan Marino from a kidnapper haunted by a missed kick in a Super Bowl.  This man played Stanley Ipkiss, who gains superpowers by putting a (*)  green object on his face.  For 10 points-what comedic actor starred in The Mask and the Ace Ventura films?",
    "answer": "Jim Carrey (or James Eugene Carrey)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This state contains a hockey rink nicknamed \"The Whale\" that was designed by Eero Saarinen [\"arrow\" SAR-uh-nun].  This state's flags hip university is in the city of Storrs. (*) New Haven [new HAY-vin] is home to the campus of Yale University in-for 10 points-what New England state whose cities include Bridgeport and Hartford?",
    "answer": "Connecticut (accept CT [\"C-T\"]) [Saarinen designed the hockey rink at Yale.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This function of n is the number of permutations of n distinct items.  For the integers from 1 to 5, this function outputs 1, 2, 6, (*) 24, and 120.  For 10 points -what function denoted by an exclamation mark gives the product of 1 times 2 times 3 times 4 and so on up through the input?",
    "answer": "(n) factorial function"
  },
  {
    "question": "A painting by this artist shows a home he shared with Paul Gauguin [goh-gan] and is called The Yellow House.  A cypress tree and swirling clouds feature in a nightscape he painted in an (*)  asylum.  For 10 points -what Dutch-born painter who mostly worked in late 19th-century France created Starry Night?",
    "answer": "Vincent (Willem) van Gogh [\"van GO\"]"
  },
  {
    "question": "A man in this play states that \"our little life / is rounded with a sleep\" after musing, \"We are such stuff / as dreams are made on.\"  In this play, the spirit Ariel and the monstrous slave (*)  Caliban [KAL-ih-ban] serve the sorcerer Prospero [\"prosper\"-oh].  For 10 points -what Shakespeare play begins with the title storm?",
    "answer": "The Tempest"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 2021 this MLB team won a record five Gold Gloves, including the ninth straight for newly acquired third baseman Nolan Arenado [\"AIR\"-uh-NAH-doh].  This team won 17 straight games in September 2021. (*)  Yadier [YAH-dee-air] Molina is a catcher on-for 10 points-what National League team based at Busch Stadium in Missouri?",
    "answer": "St. Louis Cardinals (accept either underlined portion; accept Cards)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pencil and paper ready.  Anirudh [ah-nee-\"rude\"] is randomly drawing a single card from a standard deck of 52 playing cards, and needs to know the probability that the card will be a red queen.  Since the deck has 4 equal suits, 2 of which are (*) red, he finds-for 10 points-what probability of a red queen?",
    "answer": "1/26 or 1 in 26 [There are 2 red queens (the queen of hearts and the queen of diamonds); 2/52 = 1/26.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This was the first war in which the U.S. funded its military by selli ng liberty bonds.  During this war, the A.E.F. was commanded by General \"Black Jack\" Pershing.  The (*)  sinking of the Lusitania by Germany was a factor leading the U.S. to enter-for 10 points-what global war in 1917?",
    "answer": "World War I (or First World War; prompt on \"Great (War)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "From 2012 to 2013 this country was led by an affiliate of the Muslim Brotherhoo d.  Protests often take place in this country's Tahrir Square, including those that toppled Hosni (*)  Mubarak [HAHZ-nee moo-BAH-rahk].  The former general Abdel Fattah el-Sisi [ahb-DEL fah-TAH el-SEE-see] is the president of-for 10 points-what country led from Cairo?",
    "answer": "Egypt (or Arab Republic of Egypt or Gumhuriyat Misr al-Arabiyah)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This character has his face painted blue and is called a \"sick Arab\" by the \"duke\" and the \"dauphin\" [doh-FAN].  When this man is held in a shed on the Phelps plantation, Tom (*)  Sawyer devises a rescue plan.  For 10 points-what slave sails on a raft with a boy in Mark Twain's Adventures of Huckleberry Finn?",
    "answer": "Jim"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bragg's law is used in a technique based on this type of radiation used to determin e the structure of DNA.  Wilhelm Röntgen [VIL-helm RENT-gen] is credited with discovering this type of radiation.  It has frequencies below those of (*) gamma rays.  For 10 points -name this form of radiation used to image bones.",
    "answer": "X-rays (or X-radiation; accept X-ray crystallography or X-ray diffraction; accept X-rays after \"rays\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This country's coat of arms partially depicts its namesake mountain, which is the second tallest in Africa.  This country's flag shows a shield in front of two crossed spear s of the (*) Maasai [mah-\"SIGH\"] people.  The father of Barack Obama was born in-for 10 points-what country whose capital is Nairobi [nye-ROH-bee]?",
    "answer": "Kenya (or Republic of Kenya or Jamhuri ya Kenya)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This emperor began building the Domus Aurea [DOH-mus AW-ree-uh] on the Oppian Hill.  This Roman emperor's suicide in AD 68 began the \"Year of the Four Emperors\" and may have been accompanied by the line \"what an (*) artist dies in me.\"  For 10 points -what Roman emperor legendarily played his fiddle while Rome burned?",
    "answer": "Nero (Claudius Caesar Augustus Drusus Germanicus)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This element, nitrogen, and oxygen comprise the most common form of saltpeter, an ingredient in gunpowder.  This element's name refers to its historic extraction from ashe s soaked in a (*) pot of water.  For 10 points-what element with atomic symbol \"K\" may be obtained nutritionally in bananas?",
    "answer": "potassium (accept K before \"K\"; accept potassium nitrate) [Potassium was historically extracted from potash.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This country controls the Isthmus of Kra [KRAH], a narrow region that extends southward into the Malay [MAY-lay] Peninsula.  The Mekong [MEE-kong] River forms much of this country's eastern border with (*) Laos [lowss].  Siam [\"sigh\"-AM] was the former name of-for 10 points-what southeast Asian country whose capital is Bangkok?",
    "answer": "Thailand (or Kingdom of Thailand or Prathet Thai or Ratcha Anachak Thai)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Chrysus [KRIS-us] was a minor god of this substance.  The Hesperides [heh-\"SPARE\"-ih-deez] guarded a tree that produced fruit made of this substance.  Dionysus [\"die\"-oh-NYE-siss] gave a king of (*) Phrygia [\"FRIDGE\"-ee-uh] the ability to turn objects into this substance.  Being touched by Midas [\"MY\"-duss] turned objects into-for 10 points-what precious metal?",
    "answer": "gold"
  },
  {
    "question": "This force balances the centrifugal [sen-TRIH-\"few\"-gul] force at Lagrange [luh-GRAHNZH] points.  General relativity explains this force as the warping of (*) spacetime.  On Earth's surface, this force causes an acceleration of 9.8 meters per second squared.  For 10 points -name this attraction between objects with mass.",
    "answer": "gravity (or gravitational force)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 1386 treaty of this name established the oldest alliance in the world between England and Portugal.  St. George's Chapel is in a castle of this name in Berkshire [BARK-shur].  The House of Saxe -Coburg and Gotha [GOH-tuh] (*) changed its name to-for 10 points-what name of the current royal house of Britain?",
    "answer": "Windsor (accept Treaty of Windsor or Windsor Castle or House of Windsor or Windsors)"
  },
  {
    "question": "At the end of this novel, Granger recalls the myth of the phoenix after observing a nuclear strike.  After reciting \"Dover Beach,\" this novel's protagonist is told to destroy his house by Captain (*) Beatty [BAY-tee].  Guy Montag works as a \"fireman\" who burns books in-for 10 points-what Ray Bradbury novel?",
    "answer": "Fahrenheit 451"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 2018 this country unveiled the largest statue in the world, a depiction of a former deputy prime minister called the Statue of Unity in its state of (*) Gujarat [GOO-juh-raht].  Shah Jahan [juh-HAHN] used marble in a mausoleum [maw-zuh-LEE-um] complex for his wife near Agra [AH-gruh] in-for 10 points-what country that contains the Taj Mahal [TAHZH muh-\"HALL\"]?",
    "answer": "India (or Republic of India or Bharat(iya) Ganarajya) [The Statue of Unity depicts Vallabhbhai Patel.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This president ordered the firing of special prosecutor Archibald Cox in the \"Saturday Night Massacre.\"  Carl Bernstein and Bob Woodward (*) investigated this president with help from the informant \"Deep Throat.\"  For 10 points-what president resigned in 1974 as a result of the Watergate scandal?",
    "answer": "Richard M(ilhous) Nixon"
  },
  {
    "question": "This team set a NFL playoff record with 28 first-quarter points in a January 2021 win over the Pittsburgh Steelers.  This team reached the playoffs in 2020 three years after it lost (*)  all 16 games it played in 2017.  Baker Mayfield is the quarterback of-for 10 points-what NFL team in Ohio?",
    "answer": "Cleveland Browns (accept either underlined portion)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This plant family includes a night-blooming cereus [SIR-ee-uss] pollinated by bats.  Plants in this New World family are mostly succulents [\"SUCK-you-lints\"] to help them (*) conserve water.  The saguaro [suh-WAH-roh] belongs to-for 10 points-what family of plants which often have spines instead of leaves and usually grow in dry areas?",
    "answer": "cactuses (or cacti; accept Cactaceae)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The final stanza of this poem notes that \"all the world wondered\" at the achievement of the title group, which is ordered to move \"half a (*) league onward.\"  \"Into the valley of Death / rode the six hundred\" is a refrain in-for 10 points-what poem by Alfred Tennyson set during the Crimean War?",
    "answer": "The Charge of the Light Brigade"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the shores of this lake, the Nordhouse Dunes Wilderness is in Manistee National Forest.  A strait connecting to this lake which is called \"Death's Door\" is the namesake of Door (*)  County, Wisconsin.  For 10 points-the shores of what Great Lake are home to the cities of Milwaukee and Chicago?",
    "answer": "Lake Michigan"
  },
  {
    "question": "The SI base unit for this quantity is defined in terms of the hyperfine [\"hyper-fine\"] transition of cesium-133 [SEE-zee-um \"one thirty-three\"].  Special relativity is set in a four -dimensional manifold that combines (*) space and this quantity.  Distance traveled equals speed multiplied by -for 10 points-what quantity measured in seconds?",
    "answer": "time (accept spacetime after \"space\"; do not accept or prompt on \"second(s)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This hero gave up control of Argos [AR-gohss] to his cousin Megapenthes [\"mega\"-PEN-theez] after accidentally killing his own grandfather Acrisius [uh-KRIH-see-us] with a discus.  This hero carried a helm of (*)  invisibility and a reflective shield when he decapitated a Gorgon.  For 10 points -name this hero who slew Medusa.",
    "answer": "Perseus [PUR-see-uss]"
  },
  {
    "question": "After this monarch's envoys were killed by Shah Muhammad II, this man's general Subutai [SOO-buh-\"tie\"] brutally conquered the Khwarazmian [kwah-REZ-mee-un] Empire.  This man's third son, (*)  Ogedei [OH-guh-dye], finished off the conquest of the Jin Dynasty that this man started in 12  For 10 points -name this founder of the Mongol Empire.",
    "answer": "Genghis Khan [GENG-giss kahn] (or Chingis Khan or Jenghiz Khan or Borjigin Temüjin [TEM-oo-jin] or Yuan Taizu or Fatian Qiyun Shengwu)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This type of mathematical construct can be called \"telescoping\" if most of its terms can be canceled.  If the partial sums of this type of construct approach a (*) limit, it is called \"convergent.\"  For 10 points -name this type of mathematical construct formed by adding the terms of a sequence.",
    "answer": "infinite series (accept telescoping series; do not accept or prompt on \"sequence\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 2022 unrest spread from this country's city of Zhanaozen [ZAH-\"now\"-ZEN] after it ended price caps on gas.  Kassym-Jomart Tokayev's [kah-SEEM yoh-MART TOH-kah-yev's] regime shot protesters in this country who opposed its ex-president (*) Nursultan Nazarbayev [noor-sul-TAHN nah-zar-\"BYE\"-eff].  For 10 points -name this central Asian nation led from a city once named Astana [ah-stah-NAH].",
    "answer": "Kazakhstan [KAH-zak-stan] (or Republic of Kazakhstan or Qazaqstan Respublikasy) [Kazakhstan's capital is now known as \"Nur-Sultan\" to honor former president Nazarbayev.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This constitutional amendment is the only ratified one to be signed by the president.  This amendment banned practices like peonage [PEE-uh-nidge] \"except as a punishment for (*) crime.\"  The first \"Reconstruction\" amendment was-for 10 points-what 1865 amendment that abolished \"involuntary servitude\" and slavery?",
    "answer": "Thirteenth Amendment (or Amendment 13; accept 13th)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pencil and paper ready.  Amy needs to know how many nickels she has, given she has 3 times as many pennies as nickels, and the total value of her coins is 48 cents.  By expressing the number of nickels as x and the number of pennies as 3x, she computes (*) -for 10 points-what number of nickels?",
    "answer": "6 nickels (and 18 pennies) [One nickel and its accompanying 3 pennies are worth 5 + 3 = 8 cents; there must be 48/8 = 6 such groups, and thus 6 nickels.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "In one game, this character fights robots called EMMIs [\"Emmys\"] and Raven Beak, a Chozo [CHO-zoh] leader.  The planet Zebes [ZEE-beez] explodes after a fight between Mother (*) Brain and this woman, whose Power Suit can form a Morph Ball.  A 2021 game partly named Dread stars-for 10 points-what hero of the Metroid series?",
    "answer": "Samus Aran [SAM-iss \"AIR\"-in] (accept either underlined portion; accept Zero Suit Samus)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This animal's \"dynamism\" [DYE-nuh-mizm] titles a Futurist painting by Giacomo Balla [JAH-koh-moh BAH-lah].  One of these animals sleeps at the feet of the Venus of Urbino.  A (*) Friend in Need is one of a series that anthropomorphizes these animals.  For 10 points -Cassius Marcellus Coolidge painted what animals \"playing poker?\"",
    "answer": "dogs (accept Dynamism of a Dog on a Leash or Dogs Playing Poker)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Studies of this body led to predictions of an unseen body by John Couch Adams and Urbain Le Verrier [oor-BAN luh vair-YAY].  Shakespearean characters name many of this planet's (*)  moons, such as Miranda and Oberon [OH-bur-ahn].  An axial tilt of over 90 d egrees is exhibited by-for 10 points-what seventh planet from the Sun?",
    "answer": "Uranus [Adams and Le Verrier independently predicted the existence of Neptune before its discovery, based on its gravitational effects on Uranus's orbit.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this city, Ellen Gates Starr founded a charitable institution based on London's Toynbee Hall that was later led by Jane Addams. (*) Hull House formed in this city in 1911, 40 years after it was mostly destroyed in a disaster blamed on Mrs. O'Leary's cow.  For 10 points -name this Midwest city.",
    "answer": "Chicago, Illinois (accept Great Chicago Fire)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 2021 scientists proposed using this body to store an \"ark\" with the DNA of 6.7 million species.  The billionaire Yusaku Maezawa [yoo-sah-koo mah-eh-zah-wah] plans to use a (*) SpaceX [\"space-X\"] craft to fly around this body.  In 2020 China's Chang'e [chang-uh] 5 spacecraft landed on-for 10 points-what natural satellite of Earth?",
    "answer": "(Earth's) Moon (or Luna)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 1748 work, this man divided governments into republics, monarchies, and despotisms.  This man's treatise The Spirit of the Laws influenced the structure of the U.S. Constitution.  A (*)  separation of powers into three branches of government was proposed by-for 10 points-what French baron?",
    "answer": "Montesquieu [MAHN-tess-\"skew\"] (or Charles-Louis de Secondat, baron de la Brède et de Montesquieu)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This adjective describes \"love\" in the title of a 1964 John Coltrane album.  In the title of the head of state of Iran, this adjective modifies \"leader.\"  In the name of a Taco Bell menu item, this adjective follows (*)  \"Crunchwrap.\"  For 10 points -what adjective describes the U.S.'s highest court?",
    "answer": "supreme (accept A Love Supreme or Supreme Leader or Crunchwrap Supreme or Supreme Court)"
  },
  {
    "question": "While developing a numerical model to perform this task, Edward Lorenz [loh-RENZ] pioneered chaos theory and proposed the \"butterfly effect.\"  \"Nowcasting\" is a short -term form of this task.  It is often aided by data from (*) NOAA [\"noah\"] supercomputers.  For 10 points -identify this predictive task in meteorology.",
    "answer": "weather forecasting (accept atmospheric modeling; accept answers indicating forecasting the weather or predicting the weather or modeling the atmosphere; prompt on partial answers; prompt on \"meteorology\" before \"meteorology\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This book's protagonist finds a stick that is \"just right for smacking\" a tree before he goes sliding.  Its collage [koh-LAHZH] illustrations received a 1963 Caldecott [\"CALL-duh-cot\"] Medal, a first for a book with a (*) Black protagonist.  Peter plays outdoors in -for 10 points-what Ezra Jack Keats book set during winter?",
    "answer": "The Snowy Day"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of these reactions initiates the alternative pathway of the complement system. By adding an ADP-ribose group, the cholera toxin prevents this kind of reaction, which acts as a \"molecular timer\" for G protein signaling.  One of these reactions occurs through an S N1 substitution to (*) creatine phosphate during exercise. This type of reaction releases phosphate and 7.3 kilocalories per mole of energy when it occurs to ATP.  For 10 points-what kind of reaction splits a molecule in two using water?",
    "answer": "hydrolysis (or hydrolytic reactions or hydrolytic cleavage; prompt on \"cleavage\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Prior to the election in this year, a minor party spun off the \"National Party\" after losing its \"Broad Ga ugers.\"  Another party nominated the champion of \"rural free delivery,\" Tom Watson, as a vice presidential candidate in this year.  Mark Hanna ran a (*)  \"front porch campaign\" for the Republican who won this election over a man who accepted Democratic and Populist Pary nominations after giving the \"Cross of Gold\" speech.  For 10 points-what election did William Jennings Bryan lose to William McKinley?",
    "answer": "(U.S. presidential election of) 1896 (prompt on \"96\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This river flows through the enormous Onitsha [oh-NEET-shuh] Market, which became the nexus for a genre of pulp fiction in the 1960s.  This river's valley provides the historic pasture lands of the riverrine Zarma ethnic group.  Extensive palm oil producti on led its delta to be nicknamed the (*) Oil Rivers.  This river also has a massive \"Inner Delta,\" after which it takes an unusually sharp southern turn near Timbuktu [tim-buk-TOO].  For 10 points-what West African river shares its name with a country whose capital is Niamey [nee-AH-may]?",
    "answer": "Niger [nee-ZHAIR or NYE-jur] River (or fleuve Niger)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This two-word phrase denotes the title object of a novel about Condor Oil by The Treasure of the Sierra Madre author B. Traven [TRAH-ven].  This two -word phrase denotes an object tended \"in July as in January\" for both a \"cruel person\" and a \"sincere friend.\"  This two -word phrase identifies the object (*) \"cultivated\" in that José Martí poem, which may have inspired Hans and Sophie Scholl's name for a Munich student resistance group in Nazi Germany.  The House of York's symbol was -for 10 points-what pale flower?",
    "answer": "white rose(s) (accept The White Rose or Weisse Rose or (cultivo una) rosa blanca; do not accept or prompt on \"rose(s)\" or \"flower(s)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "A poem set in this city that praises the \"strange unheavenly glare\" of fresh snow is by Robert Bridges.  A poem titled for this city describes people whose faces bear \"marks of weakness, marks of woe\" and whose voices evoke \"mind-forg'd manacles.\"  A sonnet titled for this city says \"thy (*)  soul was like a Star, and dwelt apart\" to a poet who \"shouldst be living at this hour.\"  A Wordsworth poem set in 1802 is named after -for 10 points-what title city of a William Blake poem set near \"the charter'd Thames [temz]\"?",
    "answer": "London (accept London Snow or London, 1802)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 2021 interview, this man likened himself to the \"man with wax wings\" who was \"flying just enough, not too close to the Sun, not too close to the water.\"  This man, who co -founded an advocacy group known as \"100 Blacks,\" became a vegan after a diabetes diagnosis and advocated for (*) city schools to avoid processed meats via the \"ban the baloney\" resolution.  This former police officer and Brooklyn borough president defeated Curtis Sliwa [SLEE-wuh] in a 2021 election.  For 10 points -name this mayor of New York.",
    "answer": "Eric (Leroy) Adams"
  },
  {
    "question": "This composer gave performers a choice of pitches to open \"Free-style Events,\" the first movement of his Concerto for Orchestra.  A choral piece by this man opens with the motif B -flat, F, high E-flat, A-flat, B-flat, on the words \"Urah, hanevel\" [oo-RAH hah-NAY-vel].  In a sympho ny by this man, a narrator tells (*) God \"let me invent Your dream,\" interrupting a chorus singing Hebrew prayers.  The Chichester Psalms and the Kaddish Symphony are by-for 10 points-what long-time conductor of the New York Philharmonic?",
    "answer": "Leonard Bernstein [BURN-styne]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This church created a multi-denominational body to prepare for theocracy known as the Council of Fifty.  This church's priestly offices include a proselytizing position held by \"seventies.\"  This church includes subdivisions called \"stakes,\" which are divided into \"wards.\"  In this church, (*)  \"quorums\" are groups of people ordained to the same office of the priesthood, whose two main orders are the Aaronic [air-AH-nik] priesthood and the Melchizedek [mel-CHIH-zuh-dek] priesthood.  For 10 points -name this church founded by Joseph Smith.",
    "answer": "Church of (Jesus Christ of) Latter-Day Saints (or Mormon Church; accept answers identifying Mormons or the church of Mormonism, or the LDS or Latter-Day Saints movement)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This property, which is directly measurable and independent of distance, has a namesake \"excess\" defined as the difference in extinction in two passbands.  Vega [VAY-guh] is defined as having a value of zero for this property's \"U minus B\" and \"B minus V\" indices, which are differences in magnitude measured through (*) filters.  This property or wavelength is linked by Wien's [veen's] displacement law to a star's effective temperature.  For 10 points -what property is the subject of the mnemonic ROYGBIV [\"roy\" jee biv]?",
    "answer": "color (or color index; accept color excess or star color; accept color of non-stellar astronomical objects, such as galaxies, before \"Wien's displacement law\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This city's \"Da Hinab\" [dah hee-NAHB] gate is named for the legend that Christoph Langenmantel [\"LONG\"-en-MAHN-tul] aided in an escape after a meeting with Thomas Cajetan [CADGE-uh-tun].  An \"apology\" named for this city was issued in response to the Confutatio [kahn-foo-TAH-tee-oh].  Three years after Maurice of Saxony led the (*)  Princes' Revolt, a peace in this city affirmed \"cuius regio, eius religio\" [KWEE-oos \"reggie\"-oh AY-oos reh-LIJ-ee-oh].  A 1530 \"confession\" by Philipp Melanchthon [muh-LANK-thun] is named after-for 10 points-what city, which names a 1555 treaty that allowed German princes to choose Catholicism or Lutheranism?",
    "answer": "Augsburg (accept Augsburg Confession or Peace of Augsburg; prompt on answers mentioning \"Augusta\" or \"Augustana\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This nascent art movement's development in Cos Cob was aided by an an older artist's friendship with Theodore Robinson.  A museum named for James Michener houses many works from this movement's \"New Hope School.\"  This movement coalesced after the  Society of American Artists was abandoned by J. Alden Weir and other founders of the (*) \"Ten American Painters.\"  John Henry Twachtman [TWOCK'T-mun] and Childe Hassam founded-for 10 points-what art movement that put an American gloss on a style developed  by Claude Monet?",
    "answer": "(American) Impressionism (accept American Impressionists or Impressionist painting) [Robinson was friends with Monet and helped American Impressionists correspond with him.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two parameters psi and delta are measured from a change in this property in a non-destructive technique to determine a thin film's refractive index and thickness.  Changes in this property are measured in ellipsometry.  States of this property are denoted s for senkrecht [SEN-krekt] and (*) p for parallel.  Representations of this property include Stokes parameters and Jones vectors.  Circular and linear are types of this property.  For 10 points -what property is the orientation of a light wave?",
    "answer": "polarization (or polarized; do not accept or prompt on \"polar\" or \"polarizing\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 2021 special episode of this TV show featured the host of the podcast Uncomfortable Conversations with a Black Man, Emmanuel Acho.  The first Latino star of this show was the Venezuelan soccer player Juan Pablo Galavis [gah-lah-VEECE].  The host of this show and its spinoffs (*) stepped down in 2021 after defending Rachael Kirkconnell for attending an antebellum plantation-themed ball.  Chris Harrison once hosted -for 10 points-what reality show, in which a man presents roses to potential love interests?",
    "answer": "The Bachelor (do not accept or prompt on \"The Bachelorette\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this city, Lala Levy is criticized by her mother for putting a star on top of a Jewish Christmas tree in the play The Last Night of Ballyhoo.  In a novel, a man bids 150 dollars for a dance with a widow during a ball in this city.  Alfred Uhry wrote a trilogy of plays named for this city, inclu ding (*) Driving Miss Daisy.  This city is where Scarlett finds Rhett Butler in jail in part four of Gone with the Wind.  Margaret Mitchell was born in -for 10 points-what large city in Georgia?",
    "answer": "Atlanta, Georgia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The capital of this country contains a monument to a 1763 slave revolt led by an Akan [ah-KAHN] man known as Cuffy.  In 1997 this country's presidency was assumed by a U.S. -born woman named Janet, the widow of left-wing president Cheddi Jagan [CHEH-dee JAG-un].  This c ountry's historical (*) sugar-producing regions of Berbice [bur-BEESS] and Demerara [dem-uh-RAH-ruh] are home to many descendants of Indian indentured laborers.  In 1978 over 900 members of the Peoples Temple died at Jonestown in-for 10 points-what English-speaking country in South America?",
    "answer": "Guyana [\"guy\"-AN-uh] (or Cooperative Republic of Guyana)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A \"fiscal\" version of this system was developed by Wallace Oates.  A report by Morton Grodzins contrasts \"layer cake\" and \"marble cake\" models of this system, corresponding to conceptions of it as \"dual\" or \"cooperative.\"  The phrase \"ambition must be made to (*)  counteract ambition\" is from a set of essays named for this system that also analyze how to stop the emergence of \"factions.\"  Power is split between national and local governments in-for 10 points-what system that titles 85 pro-Constitution \"papers\"?",
    "answer": "federalism (or federalist system or federal system or federalists; accept fiscal or layer-cake or marble-cake or dual or cooperative federalism; accept The Federalist Papers)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Glaciers can limit this quantity's maximum value through denudation [DEE-new-DAY-shun] under the \"buzzsaw hypothesis.\"  Paleoclimates can be reconstructed by measuring the \"equilibrium line\" form of this quantity, which separates the accumulation zone from the ablation [uh-BLAY-shun] zone.  \"Digital (this quantity) models\" are generated by GIS [\"G-I-S\"] tools.  The reference geoid [JEE-oyd] has a value of (*) zero for this quantity whose contours appear on topographical maps.  For 10 points -what quantity names a \"sickness\" experienced by mountain climbers?",
    "answer": "elevation (accept altitude or height; accept digital elevation model; prompt on \"length\" or \"distance\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This character has a dream in which three birds arrive with beaks full of honey and leave with beaks full of blood.  This figure, who died after jumpin g out of a chariot, was raised in seclusion by the wise woman Leabharcham [LEV-ur-KUM] on the orders of a man who ignored a prophecy from (*) Cathbad [KAHTH-vahd].  J. M. Synge died before finishing a play titled for this woman, who eloped with Naoise [NEE-shuh], enraging Conchobar mac Nessa [KON-nur mak NESS-uh].  For 10 points -name this Irish woman whose tragic fate earned her the epithet \"of the Sorrows.\"",
    "answer": "Deirdre [DEER-druh] (or Derdriu; accept Deirdre of the Sorrows)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This city was not along major trade routes according to a \"revisionist\"  1987 book by Patricia Crone.  A term that either means \"memorable,\" or signifies literal suspension in this city, identifies seven \"hanging poems.\"  This city, which swelled with migrants after the collapse of the Marib dam, was invaded by (*)  Himyarite [HIM-yuh-rite] general Abraha [ah-BRAH-hah] in a campaign to destroy its religious center with elephants.  During the \"age of ignorance,\" pagan idols were arrayed in-for 10 points-what Arabian trading city's Kaaba [KAH-bah]?",
    "answer": "Mecca (or Makkah)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A member of this group says \"hello void, long time watcher, first time callin' in\" in a song whose chorus features Mavis Staples declaring \"there's a grenade in my heart.\"  The line \"look at all these slave masters posin' on your dollar\" is repeated on this group's 2020 song \"JU$T\" [\"just\"].  The (*)  Black Panther trailer featured this group's 2016 song \"Legend Has It.\"  The \"pistol and fist\"  hand gesture appears on the cover of all four self-titled albums by-for 10 points-what hip-hop duo made up of El-P [\"L-P\"] and Killer Mike?",
    "answer": "Run the Jewels (or RTJ) [The song described in the first sentence is \"Pulling the Pin.\"]"
  },
  {
    "question": "In Romance of the Three Kingdoms, Zuo Ci [z'woh tsih] magically serves Cao Cao [tsao tsao] some of these animals from 500 miles away.  Four of them chant a couplet beginning \"come back and so will I!\" after a girl bursts through a wall and pokes them with a rod.  In The (*) Recognition of Shakuntala, Dushyanta's [doosh-YAHNT-uhs] ring is found in one of these animals.  A man who makes his living from these animals discovers a jinni in a pot in a tale from the Arabian Nights that depicts-for 10 points-what animals being caught in a magic pond?",
    "answer": "fish (accept River Song perch; accept carp)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This state was the longtime home of Richard Kuklinski [kuh-KLIN-ski], whose family had no idea he was a contract killer known as \"the Iceman.\"  A 1916 barge explosion caused by German sabotage occurred on this state's Black Tom island.  This state's police  superintendent, Norman Schwarzkopf Sr., investigated the (*) \"Crime of the Century,\" in which Bruno Hauptmann broke into a home in this state to kidnap Charles Lindbergh's baby.  For 10 points -in what state was Alexander Hamilton killed in a duel with Aar on Burr?",
    "answer": "New Jersey (accept NJ [\"N-J\"])"
  },
  {
    "question": "This structure forms in a namesake gland after a process called \"plumping.\"  Its formation begins around the red isthmus, forming cone-shaped mammillary knobs, the palisade layer, and the crystal layer.  The medullary bone serves as a reservoir for the formation of these structures.  Protoporphyrin [\"proto-POUR-fur-in\"] is deposited in (*) brown examples of these structures, which calcify over a 20-hour period in the uterus of the left oviduct.  Hatchlings use a namesake tooth to crack -for 10 points-what hard coverings?",
    "answer": "eggshell(s) (accept answers indicating shells of eggs; prompt on \"egg(s)\" or \"shell(s)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an argument in her room, this character vengefully tells her sister that she could never go back to a man \"who has cared for another woman.\"  This character becomes suddenly pious while on a spa trip in Germany, until she learns that Madame Stahl is faking her leg illness.  This woman writes (*)  initials in chalk to communicate with a suitor, whom she had earlier rejected because she expe cted Vronsky to propose.  Dolly is the sister of-for 10 points-what woman who marries Levin [LEH-vin] in Anna Karenina [AH-nuh kah-REH-nih-nuh]?",
    "answer": "Kitty Shcherbatsky (or Kitty Levin; or Ekaterina Alexandrovna Shcherbatskaya; prompt on \"Shcherbatsky\" or \"Shcherbatskaya\"; prompt on \"Levin\" before \"Levin\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vega [VAY-guh] is defined as having a value of zero for this property's \"U minus B\" and \"B minus V\" indices, which are differences in magnitude measured through filters.  This property or wavelength is linked by Wien's [veen's] displacement law to a star's effective (*) temperature, thus different values of this property label the supergiants Rigel [RYE-jul] and Betelgeuse [\"Beetlejuice\"].  For 10 points -what property is the subject of the mnemonic ROYGBIV [\"Roy G\" biv]?",
    "answer": "color (or color index; prompt on \"wavelength\" before \"wavelength\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 2021 special episode of this TV show featured the host of the podcast Uncomfortable Conversations with a Black Man, Emmanuel Acho.  The former host of this show and its spinoffs stepped down in 2021 after he defended Rachael (*) Kirkconnell for attending an antebellum plantation-themed ball.  Chris Harrison once hosted-for 10 points-what reality show on ABC, in which a man presents roses to potential love interests?",
    "answer": "The Bachelor (do not accept or prompt on \"The Bachelorette\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of these objects is tended \"in July as in January\" in a José Martí  poem in which it is \"cultivated.\"  Hans and Sophie Scholl used a \"white\" one to name a Munich student resistance group in Nazi Germany.  These objects named a conflict that began at the First Battle of (*) St. Albans, where Henry VI [\"the sixth\"] was captured.  The houses of York and Lancaster were symbolized by-for 10 points-what flower that named a series of British \"wars\"?",
    "answer": "rose(s) (accept The White Rose or Weisse Rose or (cultivo una) rosa blanca or War(s) of the Roses; prompt on \"flower\" before \"Munich\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In The Recognition of Shakuntala, Dushyanta's [doosh-YAHNT-uhs] ring is found inside one of these animals.  A man who makes his living from these animals discovers a jinni in a pot in the Arabian Nights.  A king with a festering (*) wound, who can only be healed by a certain question, attempts to catch these animals while guarding the Holy Grail in Arthurian legend.  For 10 points -name these animals that may be caught in a magic pond.",
    "answer": "fish (accept River Song perch; accept carp)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A museum named for James Michener houses many works from this art movement's \"New Hope School.\"  \"Ten American Painters,\" including J. Alden Weir and Childe Hassam [HAS-um], were part of a U.S. branch of this movement, whose other American members include an artist who was painted \"seated, holding (*)  cards,\" and who herself painted The Child's Bath.  For 10 points -name this movement of Mary Cassatt [kuh-SAT], who moved to France and met Claude Monet [moh-NAY].",
    "answer": "Impressionism (accept American Impressionism or (American) Impressionists or Impressionist painting) [Edgar Degas painted the work Mary Cassatt Seated, Holding Cards.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This city provides the alternate name for the English-Dutch-Austrian \"Grand Alliance\" of 1689.  This base of the Welser [VEL-zur] and Fugger [FUG-gur] families names Philipp Melanchthon [muh-LANK-thun]'s 1530 Lutheran \"Confession.\"  An agreement signed in this city is often summarized as (*) \"Cuius regio, eius religio\" [kwee-us REE-jee-oh AY-us ruh-LIH-jee-oh].  The 1555 treaty that allowed German princes to choose Catholicism or Lutheranism in each realm was the \"Peace of\"-for 10 points-what Bavarian city?",
    "answer": "Augsburg (accept League of Augsburg or Augsburg Confession or Peace of Augsburg)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This river flows through the enormous Onitsha [oh-NEET-shuh] Market.  Extensive palm oil production led its delta to be nicknamed the Oil Rivers.  This river also has a massive \"Inner Delta\" near the city of Mopti.  It subsequently flows through Diré, (*) Gao, and Timbuktu.  This third longest river of Africa empties into the Gulf of Guinea.  For 10 points -what West African river shares its name with a country whose capital is Niamey [nee-AH-may]?",
    "answer": "Niger [nee-ZHAIR or NYE-jur] River (or fleuve Niger)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cholera toxin uses an ADP-ribose [\"RYE\"-bohss] group to prevent this kind of reaction, which acts as a \"molecular timer\" for G protein signaling.  This reaction follows an S N1 [\"S-N one\"] mechanism when it happens to creatine phosphate [KREE-uh-teen FAHSS-\"fate\"] during (*) exercise.  This reaction releases a phosphate group and 7.3 kilocalories per mole of energy when it is performed on ATP.  For 10 points -what kind of reaction splits a molecule in two using water?",
    "answer": "hydrolysis [\"hi\"-DRAH-luh-siss] (or hydrolytic reactions)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Models of this system as a \"layer cake\" and \"marble cake\" correspond to conceptions of this system as \"dual\" or \"cooperative.\"  The phrase \"ambition must be made to counteract ambition\" is from a set of essays named for this system, whose tenth entry discusses (*) \"factions\" and was written by James Madison.  Power is split between national and local governments in-for 10 points-what system that titles 85 pro-Constitution \"papers\"?",
    "answer": "federalism (or federalist system or federal system or federalists; accept fiscal or layer-cake or marble-cake or dual or cooperative federalism; accept The Federalist Papers)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This state was the longtime home of Richard Kuklinski [kuh-KLIN-skee], who was secretly a contract killer known as \"the Iceman.\"  In 1932 Bruno Hauptmann sneaked into a home in this state to kidnap Charles Lindbergh's infant son.  Herbert Morrison's cry of (*)  \"Oh, the humanity!\" came during the Hindenburg disaster near Lakehurst in this state.  For 10 points -what state was linked in 1927 to a city to the east by the Holland Tunnel?",
    "answer": "New Jersey (accept NJ [\"N-J\"])"
  },
  {
    "question": "This character has a dream in which three birds arrive with beaks full of honey and leave with beaks full of blood.  This figure was raised in seclusion by the wise woman Leabharcham [LEV-ur-\"COME\"] on the orders of a man who ignored a prophecy from Cathbad [KAHTH-vahd].  This (*)  daughter of Fedlimid eloped with Naoise [NEE-shuh], enraging Conchobar mac Nessa [KON-nur mak NESS-uh].  For 10 points -name this Irish woman whose tragic fate earned her the epithet \"of the Sorrows.\"",
    "answer": "Deirdre [DEER-druh] (or Derdriu; accept Deirdre of the Sorrows)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hypsometry [hip-SAH-muh-tree] is the measurement of this quantity, values of which are stored in a namesake \"digital model\" generated by GIS [\"G-I-S\"] tools.  In meteorology the rate of change of temperature as a function of this quantity is the lapse (*) rate.  In some high -latitude environments, a change in flora occurs at a value of this quantity known as the tree line.  For 10 points -what quantity's contours appear on topographical maps?",
    "answer": "elevation (accept altitude or height; accept digital elevation model; prompt on \"length\" or \"distance\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this year, Georgia's Tom Watson was nominated as a vice presidential candidate by one faction instead of shipbuilder Arthur Sewall.  John Palmer represented the National Democrats in this election year, opposing the \"16-to-1\" policy of the (*) Populists.  The \"cross of gold\" speech favoring free silver was given in -for 10 points-what year in which William Jennings Bryan first lost the presidency to William McKinley?",
    "answer": "1896 (accept election of 1896)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A woman in this novel becomes suddenly pious while on a spa trip to Germany, until she learns that Madame Stahl is faking a leg illness.  This novel describes a steeplechase event that fatall y injures the horse Frou-Frou. (*) Kitty marries Levin [LEH-vin] in this novel after being infatuated with Count Vronsky [VRAHN-skee].  The claim \"happy families are all alike\" is made in-for 10 points-what Leo Tolstoy novel named for an adulterous woman?",
    "answer": "Anna Karenina [AH-nuh kah-REH-nih-nuh]"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a beam with this property passes through a device named for this property, its intensity is multiplied by the cosine squared of the orientation angle, according to Malus's law.  This property can be described by Stokes parameters or Jones (*) vectors.  Some sunglasses red uce glare by filtering light with the horizontal form of this property.  For 10 points -what property is the orientation of a light wave's electric field?",
    "answer": "polarization (accept answers indicating light is polarized; do not accept or prompt on \"polarity\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "A term that either means \"memorable,\" or signifies literal suspension in this city, identifies seven \"hanging poems.\"  This city swelled with migrants after the collapse of the Marib [MEH-rib] dam.  This city was i nvaded by the Himyarite [HIM-yuh-\"right\"] general (*) Abraha [ah-BRAH-hah] using war elephants in AD 570, the year its most famous native was born.  For 10 points -what Arabian trading city was the birthplace of the Prophet Muhammad?",
    "answer": "Mecca (or Makkah)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a poem named for this city, the speaker sees \"marks of weakness, marks of woe\" in every face, and hears \"mind-forg'd manacles\" [MAN-uh-kulz] in every voice.  The declaration \"thy soul was like a Star\" is made to a poet who should \"be (*) living at this hour\" in a sonnet named for this city in the year 1802.  Poems by William Blake and William Wordsworth depict-for 10 points-what setting of Wordsworth's poem \"Composed upon Westminster Bridge\"?",
    "answer": "London (accept London, 1802) [\"London, 1802\" addresses the poet John Milton.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This composer claimed to present \"fear and faith, interlocked\" in a setting of \"The L ord is my shepherd\" in his Chichester Psalms.  He included a speaker telling God, \"Dream softly.  Let me invent Your dream\" in his Kaddish [KAH-dish] (*) Symphony and composed a musical whose songs include \"Something's Coming\" and \"Maria.\"  For 10 points -name this man who directed the New York Philharmonic during the 1960s and wrote the music for West Side Story.",
    "answer": "Leonard Bernstein [BURN-styne]"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1997 this country's presidency was assumed by the U.S.-born widow of Cheddi Jagan [CHEH-dee JAG-un].  This country's historical sugar-producing region of Demerara [dem-uh-RAH-ruh] is home to many descendants of Indian indentured laborers.  U.S. Congressman (*)  Leo Ryan was killed in this country, where in 1978 over 900 members of the Peoples Temple drank cyanide-laced Flavor Aid.  The Jonestown massacre occurred in -for 10 points-what South American country?",
    "answer": "Guyana [\"guy\"-AN-uh] (or Cooperative Republic of Guyana)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this city, Lala Levy is criticized by her mother for putting a star on top of a Jewish Christmas tree in the play The Last Night of Ballyhoo.  Alfred Uhry wrote a trilogy of plays named for this city, including Driving Miss Daisy.  This city is where (*)  Scarlett O'Hara finds Rhett Butler in jail in part four of Gone with the Wind.  Margaret Mitchell was born in-for 10 points-what capital city of Georgia?",
    "answer": "Atlanta, Georgia (accept Atlanta Trilogy)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the chorus of a song by this group, Mavis Staples declares \"there's a grenade in my heart.\"  Th e line \"look at all these slave masters posin' on your dollar\" is repeated on this group's 2020 song \"JU$T\" [\"just\"].  The Black Panther trailer featured this group's 2016 song (*) \"Legend Has It.\"  The \"pistol and fist\" hand gesture appears on the cover of all four self-titled albums by-for 10 points-what hip-hop duo made up of El-P [\"L-P\"] and Killer Mike?",
    "answer": "Run the Jewels (or RTJ) [The song described in the first sentence is \"Pulling the Pin.\"]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This structure begins to form around the red isthmus, forming cone -shaped mammillary [MAM-ih-\"Larry\"] knobs, the palisade layer, and the crystal layer.  The medullary [MED-yuh-\"Larry\"] bone serves as a reservoir for the formation of these structures.  Prot oporphyrin [\"proto-PORE-fur-in\"] is deposited in brown examples of these structures, which (*) calcify over a 20 hour period in the uterus of the left oviduct.  Hatchlings use a tooth to crack-for 10 points-what hard coverings?",
    "answer": "eggshell(s) (prompt on \"shell(s)\" by asking \"What type of shell?\"; prompt on \"egg(s)\" by asking \"What part of the egg?\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the 1950s this church reformed its worldwide administration to better mirror the structure found in a \"corridor\" between St. George and Logan.  David McKay regularized this church's system of \"stakes,\" which are divided into \"wards.\"  In this church, (*)  \"quorums\" are groups of people ordained to either the Aaronic [\"air-ON-ick\"] priesthood or the Melchizedek [mel-KIH-zuh-dek] priesthood.  For 10 points -name this church founded by Joseph Smith and based in Utah.",
    "answer": "Mormon Church (or The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints or LDS Church)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 2021 interview, this man likened himself to the \"man with wax wings\" who was \"flying just enough , not too close to the Sun, not too close to the water.\"  This man became a vegan after a diabetes diagnosis and advocated for (*) schools to avoid processed meats via a \"ban the baloney\" resolution.  For 10 points -what former police officer and borough president defeated Curtis Sliwa [SLEE-wuh] in 2021 to become mayor of New York City?",
    "answer": "Eric (Leroy) Adams"
  },
  {
    "question": "These compounds, whose properties are affected by their tacticity [\"tack\"-TISS-ih-tee], undergo a phase transition at the glass transition temperature.  Synthesis of these compounds, which often use Ziegler -Natta [ZEEG-lur NAH-tah] catalysts [\"CAT-uh-lists\"], can occur by radicalization [RAD-ih-kuh-lye-ZAY-shun] or (*) step-growth mechanisms.  Examples of these compounds include proteins and DNA, as well as Kevlar and nylon.  For 10 points -name these compounds formed from repeating monomers [MAH-nuh-murz].",
    "answer": "polymers [PAH-lih-mur] (or polymeric materials; prompt on \"macromolecules\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This country promised to curtail interference in its client states in the \"Sinatra [suh-NAH-truh] Doctrine.\"  Congressman Larry McDonald died when this country mistook Korean Air Lines Flight 007 [\"oh-oh-seven\"] for a spy plane and shot it down.  A general secretary of this country enacte d policies of (*) \"reconstruction\" and \"openness\" in the 1980s.  A nuclear meltdown at Chernobyl [chur-NOH-bul] hastened the collapse of-for 10 points-what country led by Mikhail Gorbachev [mih-KYLE GOR-buh-chawf]?",
    "answer": "Soviet Union (or USSR or Union of Soviet Socialist Republics or Sovietsky Soyuz or S.S.S.R. or Soyuz Sovietskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik; prompt on \"Russia\" before \"collapse\") [\"Reconstruction\" and \"openness\" are the common translations of Gorbachev's policies of perestroika and gl asnost.]"
  },
  {
    "question": "A woman with this first name was the model for the title figure of the 1849 painting The Girlhood of Mary Virgin, which was made by her brother, the Pre-Raphaelite [pree RAF-ee-uh-\"light\"] Dante [DAHN-tay] Gabriel.  This name appears in the title of a 1948 painting that depicts the Olson [OHL-sun] House and a woman in a pink dress, whose (*) muscular disorder causes her to crawl across a field.  For 10 points -a painting by Andrew Wyeth [\"WHY\"-eth] is named after what woman's \"world\"?",
    "answer": "Christina (accept Christinas; accept Christina (Georgina) Rossetti or Christina's World; do not accept or prompt on \"Anna (Christina Olson)\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this play, a man who is aware of a hidden observer lowers his voice when saying the name of the prostitute Bianca [bee-AHNK-uh], who subsequently enters the scene and angrily refuses to copy the embroidery on a handkerchief.  This play's protagonist claims he \"loved not wisely but too well\" after learning that (*)  Michael Cassio [KASS-ee-oh] did not have an affair with Desdemona [dez-duh-MOH-nuh].  For 10 points -in what Shakespeare play does Iago [ee-AH-goh] dupe the title Moor?",
    "answer": "Othello (or The Tragedy of Othello, the Moor of Venice)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A function-like concept denoted by this letter, which is the derivative of the Heaviside [\"HEAVY-side\"] step function, takes an infinite value at 0 and is 0 elsewhere.  It denotes small variations in the input when formally defining continuity and limits.  This (*)  Greek letter's capital form precedes y and x in the formula for a line's slope.  For 10 points -what Greek letter's capital form represents change, and is shaped like a triangle?",
    "answer": "delta (accept answers that additionally specify case; accept Dirac delta function)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This man's frequent collaborator Oscar Wisting [VISS-ting] was chief officer on this man's ship Maud [\"mode\"].  This man disappeared while leading a rescue mission for the downed airship Italia [ee-TAHL-yuh].  He captained the Gjøa [YOH-uh] during the first transit of the (*) Northwest Passage.  This man's team used sled dogs in an expedition that beat Robert Scott by a month.  For 10 points -in 1911 what Norwegian explorer's team became the first to reach the South Pole?",
    "answer": "Roald Amundsen [ROH-ahl AH-mun-sun] (or Roald Engelbregt Gravning Amundsen)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This author wrote about a boastful man who hides from dinner guests within the title vehicle in his story \"The Carriage.\"  A disloyal son named Andriy [AHN-dray] is killed by the title Cossack [KAH-\"sack\"] in this author's historical novella Taras Bulba [TAH-rahss BOOL-buh].  In a novel by this author, the former government official (*)  Pavel Chichikov [PAH-vul CHEE-chee-kawf] schemes to buy the rights to deceased peasants.  For 10 points -what Russian-language author wrote the novel Dead Souls?",
    "answer": "Nikolai (Vasilievich) Gogol [GOH-gul]"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this state, restaurant entrepreneur Fred Harvey built the El Tovar [el toh-VAR] Hotel near a popular national park.  In 1968 L ondon Bridge was bought and rebuilt in this state near Lake Havasu [HAV-uh-soo].  Tourists can visit Boothill [\"boot-hill\"] Graveyard, which includes the graves of three men killed during the (*)  gunfight at the O.K. Corral, in this state's town of Tombstone.  For 10 points -what Southwestern state contains Grand Canyon National Park?",
    "answer": "Arizona (accept AZ [\"A-Z\"])"
  },
  {
    "question": "During this dynasty, female historian Ban Zhao [bahn jao] described proper women's behavior in the Lessons for Women.  The Records of the Grand Historian were written during this dynasty by Sima Qian [sih-mah chee-en].  The reign of Wang Mang [wahng mahng] interrupted this dynasty, which was founded by former (*) peasant Liu Bang [lee-oh bahng].  This dynasty that arose in 202 BC followed the Qin [chin].  For 10 points -what dynasty lends its name to China's majority ethnic group?",
    "answer": "Han [hahn] dynasty (or Hàn cháo)"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of this company's board members, the Moroccan-born Moncef Slaoui [MAHN-sif SLAO-ee], divested from it to become head of a government program that awarded this company over 1.5 billion dollars.  This company worked with BARDA [\"BAR\"-duh] and NIAID [\"NYE-ad\"] to produce a product sold under the brand name (*) \"Spikevax\" [\"spike-vax\"].  Operation Warp Speed funded mRNA [\"M-R-N-A\"] research by-for 10 points-what U.S. company that, like Pfizer [FYE-zur] and Johnson & Johnson, makes a COVID vaccine?",
    "answer": "Moderna [muh-DUR-nuh] (or Moderna, Inc.)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Sun, a \"zone\" named for this process undergoes differential rotation and is found right below the photosphere [\"photo-sphere\"].  A form of this process may occur in two layers, and involves downward -moving \"slabs\" and upward-moving \"plumes.\"  This process in Earth's (*)  mantle drives the motion of tectonic [tek-TAH-nik] plates.  For 10 points -what type of heat transfer requires the movement of a fluid medium, unlike radiation and conduction?",
    "answer": "convection (accept convective zone or convection layer(s) or mantle convection or convective heat transfer)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This country's town of Tarxien [\"TAR-shin\"] contains several ancient megalithic [meg-uh-LITH-ik] temples, including a noted underground hypogeum [\"HYPE\"-oh-JEE-um] from the Saflieni [sahf-lee-AIN-ee] era.  From 1530 to 1798 this country was the base of the (*) Knights Hospitaller [HAH-spit-uh-lur].  Only two peo ple live on this country's third-largest island, Comino [koh-MEE-noh], which is south of its island of Gozo [GOH-zoh].  A Semitic [seh-MIT-ik] language is spoken in-for 10 points-what Mediterranean island country south of Sicily?",
    "answer": "Malta (or Republic of Malta or Repubblika ta' Malta)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This man considered humanity's \"propensity [pruh-PEN-suh-tee] to evil\" in his book Religion Within the Boundaries of Mere Reason.  In response to a critique from Benjamin Constant [ben-zhuh-MEEN kawn-STAHNT], he argued that everyone has a \"duty\" to be (*) truthful, and thus one should not lie even to a murderer.  His Groundwork of the Metaphysics of Morals discusses the categorical imperative [kat-uh-GOR-ih-kul im-PER-uh-tiv].  For 10 points-what 18th-century German philosopher wrote Critique of Pure Reason?",
    "answer": "Immanuel Kant [kahnt]"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a 2021 film by this director, Scott Ward is hired to break into a casino vault right before a nuclear strike will destroy Las Vegas.  This director of Army of the Dead intended to feature characters such as Ryan Choi and Darkseid [\"dark-side\"] in a 2017 film on which he was replaced by (*) Joss Whedon [jahss WEE-dun].  For 10 points-in 2021 a four-hour director's cut version was released of what man's original vision for the film Justice League?",
    "answer": "Zack Snyder (or Zachary Edward Snyder; accept the Snyder Cut or Zack Snyder's Justice League)"
  },
  {
    "question": "These particles interacted with the protons [PROH-tahnz] of water in the Cowan-Reines [KOH-en \"rains\"] experiment, which was the first experimental detection of them.  These particles may shift between flavor eigenstates [\"EYE-gun-states\"] in their namesake (*) \"oscillations\" [AH-suh-lay-shunz].  In one second, about 100 trillion of th ese particles pass unimpeded through each person.  For 10 points -identify these nearly massless particles whose name is Italian for \"little neutral one.\"",
    "answer": "neutrinos [\"new-TREE-no\"] (accept neutrino flavor oscillations)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this decade, the Hart-Celler Act ended the National Origins Formula that had restricted immigration to the U.S. from Asia.  The Office of Economic Opportunity was created in this decade as part of the \"War on Poverty,\" which also included the early childhood program (*) Head Start.  Both Medicaid [MED-uh-kayd] and Medicare [MED-uh-\"care\"] were created in this decade.  For 10 points -in what decade was the Great Society initiative begun by Lyndon Johnson?",
    "answer": "1960s (prompt on \"Sixties\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "This deity created three goddesses after chewing and spitting out her brother's sword.  After a brother of this goddess killed a food god, she split from him to separate the night from the day.  A mirror was used to lure this goddess out of the Heavenly Rock Cave, where she hid after a dead horse was thrown at her by her brother (*) Susanoo [soo-sah-noh-oh].  The emperors of Japan are descended from -for 10 points-what Shinto sun goddess?",
    "answer": "Amaterasu(-omikami) [ah-mah-teh-rah-soo]"
  },
  {
    "question": "The narrator of this novel dreams about going with his grandfather to the circus, where he opens envelopes and finds a message indicating that he will be kept \"running.\"  Boys in this novel pick up fake coins  on an electrified rug after fighting a (*) \"battle royal.\"  This novel's narrator lives in an underground room filled with lights.  Ralph Ellison wrote -for 10 points-what novel whose African-American narrator feels unseen?",
    "answer": "Invisible Man (do not accept or prompt on \"The Invisible Man\")"
  },
  {
    "question": "An essay named for this sensation describes a boy throwing a cotton reel out of a crib, and saying versions of the words \"fort\" and \"da.\"  The same essay posits [PAH-zitz] that the \"principle\" of this sensation is balanced with a \"death drive\" in motivation.  According to Sigmund Freud [froyd], the (*) id is governed by the pursuit of this sensation.  Anhedonia [an-hee-DOH-nee-uh] is a reduced ability to experience-for 10 points-what sensation contrasted with pain?",
    "answer": "pleasure (accept lust; accept pleasure principle or Lustprinzip; accept Beyond the Pleasure Principle or Jenseits des Lustprinzips)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This is the number of \"smokes\" in the name of a valley filled with volcanic ash in the Katmai [\"cat-my\"] National Park of Alaska.  This number of ancient Greek mercenaries made up a group that fought for Cyrus [\"SIGH\"-russ] the Younger during the (*) Anabasis [uh-\"NAB\"-uh-suss].  A 2019 collaborat ion between the musicians Dan + Shay [\"dan and shay\"] and Justin Bieber [BEE-bur] is named for this number of \"hours.\"  For 10 points -give this number equal to ten to the fourth power, or 100 squared.",
    "answer": "10,000 (accept Valley of Ten Thousand Smokes or 10,000 Hours)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this novel, a man interrupts his own discussion of Zeno's [ZEE-noh'z] paradox to play a Swedish hip-hop song.  This novel's protagonist discusses \"infinities\" of different sizes at a \"prefuneral\" [\"pre-funeral\"].  The ambiguous ending of a book titled An (*) Imperial Affliction drives this novel's protagonist to visit the reclusive author Peter Van Houten [HOW-ten] in Amsterdam.  The teenagers Gus and Hazel battle cancer in -for 10 points-what novel by John Green?",
    "answer": "The Fault in Our Stars"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a Futurama [\"future\"-AH-muh] episode that is partly named for this place, Fry becomes his own grandpa.  An \"incident\" named for this place occurs after Quark causes a time warp on Star Trek: Deep Space Nine.  Roger on American Dad! visited this place in (*) 1947.  Liz is shot at the Crashdown Cafe and healed by the alien Max in a CW show named for this city.  For 10 points -name this New Mexico city linked to conspiracy theories about UFOs.",
    "answer": "Roswell [RAHZ-wel] (accept Roswell (UFO) incident; accept Roswell That Ends Well or Roswell, New Mexico)"
  },
  {
    "question": "This structure is overriding and lies over a septal defect in one of the symptoms in Tetralogy of Fallot [teh-TRAH-luh-jee \"of\" fuh-LOH].  Marfan syndrome is a risk factor for the dilatat ion [dil-uh-TAY-shun] of this structure, whose upper section is called \"thoracic\" [thuh-RASS-ik].  It ascends in an arch, then descends to the (*)  abdomen from its origin at the left ventricle [VEN-trih-kul].  It carries oxygen -rich blood away from the heart.  For 10 points-in the human body, what is the largest artery [\"ART\"-uh-ree]?",
    "answer": "aorta [ay-ORT-uh]"
  },
  {
    "question": "This composer's third symphony concludes with bells playing fading minor triads [\"TRY-ads\"] in a movement titled \"Communion.\"  The Alcotts are represente d in the third movement of this man's second piano sonata [suh-NAH-tuh].  A work by this composer depicts the (*)  Housatonic [HOO-suh-TAH-nik], Putnam's Camp, and the Robert Gould [goold] Shaw Memorial.  For 10 points -name this modernist composer of the Concord [\"CONK\"-urd] Sonata and Three Places in New England.",
    "answer": "Charles (Edward) Ives [rhymes with \"hives\"]"
  }
]
export let multis = [
  {
    "prompt": "According to Plutarch [PLOO-tark], this object-having been removed-was used as a prop representing Pentheus in a performance of The Bacchae [\"BACK\"-ee].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this object.  Molten gold was legendarily poured into an orifice of this object as a mockery of greed and wealth following Surena's [soo-RAY-nuh'z] decisive victory in a 53 BC battle.",
      "answer": "head of Crassus [\"CRASS\"-uss] (or Marcus Licinius Crassus's head (or skull or cranium); accept all answers indicating Marcus Licinius Crassus and the notion of a head or equivalent; prompt on answers that only specify \"a head\" or equivalent alone and do not mention Crassus; do not accep t or prompt on answers indicating a \"mouth\" or \"throat\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Crassus was killed following this battle, in which a Parthian army destroyed seven Roman legions.",
      "answer": "Battle of Carrhae [KAR-ee]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The death of Crassus ended the First Triumvirate [\"try\"-UM-vih-rut], which also included Pompey [PAHM-pee] and this man who conquered Gaul and was assassinated on the Ides of March.",
      "answer": "(Gaius) Julius Caesar (accept either underlined portion)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Andrei Linde [LIN-deh] has argued that the structure of the universe can be described by this type of shape.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "The Mandelbrot [man-dul-brawt] set is an example of what self-similar shapes?",
      "answer": "fractals"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "According to Linde, this process may create a self-reproducing fractal universe.  The epoch of this extremely rapid process is proposed to have lasted for 10-36 [\"ten-to-the-negative-36\"] seconds after the Big Bang.",
      "answer": "cosmic inflation (accept inflationary epoch)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Other physicists have argued that inflation explains why the universe has this property, defined as appearing the same in all directions.",
      "answer": "isotropy [\"eye\"-SAH-truh-pee] (or isotropic [\"eye\"-suh-TRAH-pik]; do not accept or prompt on \"anisotropic\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2016 three of this man's sons, all under age 12, competed in an illegal televised MMA match.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this \"head\" of a European republic who, since 2017, has denied that his regime imprisons LGBT people in concentration camps.  In March 2022 Vladimir Putin made him a lieutenant general.",
      "answer": "Ramzan (Akhmadovich) Kadyrov [rahm-ZAHN kah-DEE-roff]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Kadyrov is the head of this majority-Muslim republic in the Caucasus, which Russia regained control of in a 2003 war.  Its capital is Grozny [GROHZ-nee].",
      "answer": "Chechnya [CHECH-nee-ah] (or Chechen Republic or Chechenskaya Respublika or Noxçiyço or Noxçiyn Respublika)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Kadyrov claimed Chechnya did not have any gay people in a 2017 interview with this journalist, who hosts the HBO series Real Sports.  His brother Greg is also a sportscaster.",
      "answer": "Bryant (Charles) Gumbel (accept Real Sports with Bryant Gumbel)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2010 this country's former president Evo Morales [AY-voh moh-RAH-lays] declared it to be a \"plurinational state.\"  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this landlocked South American country that shares Lake Titicaca [tee-tee-KAH-kah] with its western neighbor.",
      "answer": "Bolivia (or Plurinational State of Bolivia or Estado Plurinacional de Bolivia)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Pirai [pee-RYE] River flows through this city in the country's central eastern lowlands, Bolivia's most populous.  Its full name includes \"de la Sierra.\"",
      "answer": "Santa Cruz de la Sierra"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Bolivia's population includes around 3 million Quechua [KESH-wuh] people and over 1.5 million of these indigenous people, of which Evo Morales is a member.",
      "answer": "Aymara [\"eye\"-MAR-uh] (or Aimara)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This city was the capital of the princely state of Awadh [ah-wahd] before its annexation by the British East India Company.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Identify this city where the Indian National Congress and the Muslim League signed a short -lived namesake cooperation pact in 1916.",
      "answer": "Lucknow [\"LUCK-now\" or LAHK-\"now\"] (or Lakhnau)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Henry Lawrence died during a siege of the British Residency in Lucknow during this co nflict sparked by the introduction of greased rifle cartridges.",
      "answer": "Sepoy Rebellion (or Sepoy Mutiny or Indian Rebellion of 1857 or Indian Mutiny of 1857 or Rebellion of 1857 or Revolt of 1857 or Uprising of 1857)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Lucknow is today the capital of this most populous state in India.  This state's chief minister is Yogi Adityanath [YOH-gee uh-DEET-yuh-nath].",
      "answer": "Uttar Pradesh [OO-tar PRAH-desh]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This opening sentence is followed by a paragraph that describes a \"great python\" spitting \"venomous kerosene.\"  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "What six-word sentence begins a novel about the fireman Guy Montag?",
      "answer": "It was a pleasure to burn."
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "\"It was a pleasure to burn\" opens this novel by Ray Bradbury titled for the temperature at which books catch fire.",
      "answer": "Fahrenheit 451"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "At the end of Fahrenheit 451, Montag recites a verse about a \"tree of life\" whose leaves are for \"healing the nations\" drawn from this book of the New Testament.",
      "answer": "Book of Revelation (of Saint John the Divine) (accept Apocalypse of John or Revelation to John; do not accept or prompt on \"Revelations\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2018 this player broke the record for having played the most career games before his first MLB All -Star appearance.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this outfielder of Greek descent who played from 2015 to 2020 with the Braves.  He retired before the 2021 season.",
      "answer": "Nick Markakis [mar-KAY-cuss] (or Nicholas William Markakis)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Markakis was drafted by, and spent nine seasons with, this AL East team from Maryland.",
      "answer": "Baltimore Orioles (accept either underlined portion; prompt on \"O's\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Upon joining the Braves, Markakis adopted number 22, which this five -time Gold Glove winner vacated when he joined the Cardinals.  Since 2016 this former Rookie of the Year has played for the Cubs.",
      "answer": "Jason (Alias) Heyward"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Pencil and paper ready. Consider a dihybrid [\"die-hybrid\"] cross between two pea plants, one with round, yellow seeds and the other with wrinkled, green seeds.  For 10 poin ts each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "The genotypes [JEEN-uh-\"types\"] of the resulting offspring can be visualized by drawing what kind of \"square\" named for a British geneticist?",
      "answer": "Punnett [PUN-it] square (accept R(eginald) C(rundall) Punnett)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Given that the round-seed and yellow-seed alleles [uh-LEELZ] are dominant, what proportion of the offspring will have round, yellow seeds?  You have 10 seconds.",
      "answer": "9/16 or 0.5625 [The dominant phenotype occurs if at least one allele is dominant, with a probability of 1 - ((1/2) * (1/2)) = 1 - 1/4 = 3/4.  Since both traits are independent, the overall probability is 3/4 * 3/4 = 9/16.]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "What proportion of the offspring will have wrinkled, green seeds, given that both traits are recessive?",
      "answer": "1/16 or 0.0625 [The recessive phenotype only occurs if both inherited alleles are recessive, with a probability of 1/2 * 1/2 = 1/4.  Since both traits are independent, the overall probability is 1/4 * 1/4 = 1/16.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the Oregon Trail:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The trail formally began in Independence, a town in this state.  This state's Gateway Arch honors western expansion.",
      "answer": "Missouri (accept MO [\"M-O\"])"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Settlers who traveled the trail often stopped at this major fort in Wyoming, located where its namesake river meets the North Platte River.",
      "answer": "Fort Laramie [\"LAIR\"-uh-mee] (accept Laramie River)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The trail ended in this fertile valley in Oregon, home to the cities of Salem, Eugene, and Portland.",
      "answer": "Willamette [wil-LAM-et] Valley"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the proposed colony of Vandalia [van-DAY-lee-uh]:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Vandalia would have occupied the land just south of this river, which also marked the southern boundary of the Northwest Territory.",
      "answer": "Ohio River"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Vandalia was named in honor of this wife of George III [\"the third\"], who was thought to be a descendant of ancient Vandal tribesmen.",
      "answer": "Queen Charlotte (or Charlotte of Mecklenburg-Strelitz)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Vandalia's lands eventually became part of West Virginia and this other state, which was represented in the senate by Henry Clay.",
      "answer": "Kentucky (or Commonwealth of Kentucky; accept KY [\"K-Y\"])"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the atmosphere of Mars:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The thin atmosphere of Mars is made largely of this gas, whose year-average concentration in Earth's atmosphere hit a record 416 parts per million in 2021.",
      "answer": "carbon dioxide or CO2 [\"C-O two\"]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Nanophase compounds in which these two elements are bonded contribute to the reddish haze of Mars's atmosphere, and the color of its surface.  Give both elements.",
      "answer": "iron (or Fe)   oxygen (or O) (accept answers in either order; accept ferric oxide as a substitute for both answers; do not accept or prompt on partial answers)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "About 2 percent of Mars's atmosphere consists of this gas, which is used along with potassium in a method of radioactive dating that does not involve carbon.",
      "answer": "argon (or Ar; accept potassium-argon dating)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In A Room of One's Own, Virginia Woolf claimed that this author earned womankind \"the right to speak their minds.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Restoration author of the play The Rover, who often wrote under the pseudonym Astrea [uh-STRAY-uh].",
      "answer": "Aphra Behn [AA-fruh BEN]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Behn's 1688 work Oroonoko [OH-roo-NOH-koh] is one of the earliest examples of this literary form in English, other examples of which include Robinson Crusoe and Pamela.",
      "answer": "novels"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Among Behn's literary friends was this playwright of All for Love and Marriage á la Mode.  He became England's first poet laureate in 1668.",
      "answer": "John Dryden"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This composer led the \"Second Viennese School,\" which included Alban Berg and Anton Webern [VAY-burn].  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Austrian composer who developed the twelve-tone method for composition in the 1920s.",
      "answer": "Arnold (Franz Walter) Schoenberg [SHURN-bairg]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Schoenberg's composition Transfigured Night calls for an ensemble of this many string players, one more than the number of lines in a staff.",
      "answer": "six (accept string sextet)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Schoenberg's Second String Quartet unusually calls for one of these musicians in its third and fourth movements.  One of these musicians is accompanied by an orchestra in Schoenberg's Erwartung [\"air\"-VAR-toong].",
      "answer": "vocalist or singer (accept soprano; accept clear equivalents indicating a vocal performer or someone who sings)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A philosopher who wrote in this language argued for the existence of God using the \"proof of the truthful.\"  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this language used by Avicenna [AH-vuh-SEH-nuh], who wrote during the first half of the 11th century.",
      "answer": "Arabic"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Avicenna argued for the existence of the soul with a thought experiment about this type of \"man,\" who has self-knowledge despite not having any sense-perceptions.",
      "answer": "floating man (accept flying man or falling man or answers referring to a man who is suspended in air)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Avicenna wrote an encyclopedic \"canon\" of this discipline, which was influenced by Galen's [GAY-len'z] work in this area.",
      "answer": "medicine (accept medical science or healing; accept The Canon of Medicine)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "After France's defeat at the Battle of Rossbach [ROSS-bahk], this woman reportedly comforted the king by saying, \"After us, the deluge.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this woman whose abilities as a royal advisor secured her place at the French court even after her tim e as official mistress ended in 1751.",
      "answer": "Madame de Pompadour [PAWM-puh-DOOR] (or Jeanne Antoinette Poisson)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Madame de Pompadour served this king, who reigned until 1774.  His grandson -who shared his regnal name, but was one number higher-was guillotined in 1793.",
      "answer": "Louis XV [LOO-ee \"the 15th\"] of France (accept Louis the Beloved or Louis le Bien Aimé; prompt on \"Louis\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 1756 Louis and Madame de Pompadour allied France with Austria, part of this realignment of European alliances in the wake of the War of the Austrian Succession.",
      "answer": "Diplomatic Revolution (prompt on \"stately quadrille\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A speedrunning technique in this game called \"divine travel\" locates endgame structures using the random placements of fossils or animals.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this sandbox game developed by Mojang.",
      "answer": "Minecraft (accept Minecraft: Java Edition)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Minecraft speedrunners must find a stronghold and enter the End dimension before battling this creature, which functions as the \"final boss\" of the game.",
      "answer": "Ender [IN-dur] dragon (prompt on \"dragon\" or \"Ender\" alone)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Instead of building them the usual way, Minecraft speedrunners usually \"cast\" these structures using water and lava buckets.",
      "answer": "Nether [NEH-thur] portals (or Nether portal frames; prompt on \"portal(s)\" or \"portal frame(s)\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Pencil and paper ready.  For 10 points each -answer these questions about the parabola [puh-RAB-uh-luh] defined by the equation y equals x squared minus 2x:",
    "A": {
      "question": "What is the x-coordinate of the parabola's vertex?",
      "answer": "x = 1 (accept (1, -1)) [x = -b/2a = -(-2)/(2 * 1) = 2/2 = 1]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "One of the two roots of the parabola is at the origin.  What is the x-coordinate of the other root?",
      "answer": "x = 2 (accept (2, 0)) [Roots occur where y = 0, so 0 = x2 - 2x, so 0 = x(x - 2), so x = 0 or x - 2 = 0, and x = 0 or x = 2.]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "What is the area of the region that lies above the parabola and below the x-axis?  You have 10 seconds, and should recall the roots are at zero and 2.",
      "answer": "4/3 or 1 1/3 (accept -4/3 or -1 1/3) [Int(x2 - 2x) = x3/3 - x2, so, from x = 0 to x = 2, ((23/3) - 22) - ((03/3) - 02) = ((8/3) - 4) - 0 = (8/3) - (12/3) = -4/3; the negative sign indicates the region is below the x-axis.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "María Josefa [hoh-SAY-fah] warns this play's title character that her daughters' hearts will turn to dust if they are not set free.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this play in which Angustias [ahn-GOO-stee-us] plans to marry Pepe el Romano [PAY-pay el roh-MAH-noh], who never appears on stage.",
      "answer": "The House of Bernarda Alba (or La Casa de Bernarda Alba)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The House of Bernarda Alba is part of this playwright's \"Rural Trilogy.\"",
      "answer": "Federico García Lorca (or Federico (del Sagrado Corazón de Jesús) García Lorca; accept either underlined portion)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The House of Bernarda Alba premiered just months before Lorca's death in this country's civil war.",
      "answer": "Spain (or Kingdom of Spain or Reino de España)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This professor's off-campus meetings during the COVID pandemic were the focus of a scandal mockingly called \"Dinner-party-gate.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "The 2018 book Political Tribes is by what Asian-American professor at Yale Law School?",
      "answer": "Amy (Lynn) Chua"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Chua is best known for a 2011 memoir that likened Chinese-American mothers who demand perfection from their children to these big cats.",
      "answer": "Tiger Mother (or Tiger Mom; accept Battle Hymn of the Tiger Mother)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Chua's controversial book The Triple Package linked the upward mobility of members of this religious group with greater impulse control gained from a required two-year mission.",
      "answer": "Mormon church (or Mormonism or Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints or LDS Church)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This style of art includes the black and white paintings of Bridget Riley.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Victor Vasarely was a leader of what art movement that makes use of illusions?  It rose to prominence with the 1965 MoMA exhibition \"The Responsive Eye.\"",
      "answer": "op art (or optical art)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Op artist Wen-Ying Tsai [\"sigh\"] created one of these things that seems to be \"upward falling.\"  A Marcel Duchamp [\"mar-SELL\" doo-SHAHMP] readymade titled for being one of these things was signed \"R. Mutt.\"",
      "answer": "fountains (accept Upward Falling Fountain or Fountain)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Although not usually grouped with op art, this Dutch artist created many works based on illusions and mathematics, such as a seemingly infinite staircase in Relativity.",
      "answer": "M.  Escher [EH-shur] (or Maurits Cornelis Escher)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Chelation [kee-LAY-shun] involves the bonding of these species to metal ions.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Give this term for molecules or ions that bind to the central atom of a coordination complex.",
      "answer": "ligands [LIG-und]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Ligands typically satisfy this man's definition of bases, as they donate electron pairs.  This man's namesake \"dot diagrams\" are used to visualize bonding.",
      "answer": "Gilbert N(ewton) Lewis (accept Lewis base or Lewis dot diagram)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Ligands that can undergo chelation are described by this adjective, as they use more than one donor atom to bond to the central metal atom.",
      "answer": "polydentate ligand"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In this novel, journalist Peter Fallow investigates a hit-and-run accident that killed a young Black man in the Bronx.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this 1987 novel that depicts the downfall of the Wall Street bond trader Sherman McCoy.",
      "answer": "The Bonfire of the Vanities"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This author of The Bonfire of the Vanities wrote about the Mercury space program in The Right Stuff.",
      "answer": "Tom Wolfe [\"wolf\"] (or Thomas K(ennerly) Wolfe; do not accept or prompt on \"Thomas Wolfe\" or \"Thomas Clayton Wolfe\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Wolfe's book The Electric Kool-Aid Acid Test is about a journey taken by the Merry Pranksters and this author of One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest.",
      "answer": "Ken Kesey (or Kenneth Elton Kesey)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "During his confirmation hearings, this man denied that he had ever read the book The Exorcist.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this man who claimed he was the victim of a \"high-tech lynching\" during hearings in which he was accused of sexual harassment by Anita Hill.",
      "answer": "Clarence Thomas"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Thomas was testifying before the Senate Judiciary Committee, chaired at the time by this future vice president under Barack Obama.",
      "answer": "Joe Biden (or Joseph Robinette Biden Jr.)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Thomas was nominated to the Supreme Court by George H. W. Bush a year after Bush nominated this justice, who had previously served on the New Hampshire Supreme Court.  For lunch, this justice routinely ate an entire apple, including the core.",
      "answer": "David (Hackett) Souter [SOO-tur]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The last line of this poem repeats words like \"pleasing\" and \"prince\" from its first line.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this poem in which a man loses the title object and dreams that it is reborn as a woman on the far bank of a stream.",
      "answer": "Pearl (or Perle)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The anonymous Pearl Poet is also thought to have written this poem, whose title characters are a member of King Arthur's Round Table and the spirit who ensnares him in a \"beheading game.\"",
      "answer": "Sir Gawain and the Green Knight"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Pearl Poet may have also written this 14th-century poem, in which a corpse found underneath St. Paul's Cathedral tells its life story to the title bishop.",
      "answer": "St. Erkenwald"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This theorist coined the term \"holding environment\" to describe the role of the therapeutic setting.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "What pioneering object-relations theorist posited the \"true and false self\" and the \"transitional object\"?",
      "answer": "D. W. Winnicott (or Donald Woods Winnicott)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Winnicott wrote a book titled for this behavior \"and reality.\" The \"deep\" form of this usually recreational activity titles a Clifford Geertz essay on cockfighting.",
      "answer": "play(ing) (accept answers indicating playing games; accept Playing and Reality or Deep Play: Notes on the Balinese Cockfight)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Winnicott argued that the \"ego-relatedness\" stage enables the development of this capacity, which is crucial to avoid \"false life.\"  Paradoxically, this abi lity develops in the \"presence of the mother.\"",
      "answer": "capacity to be alone (or solitude; or be by one's self; prompt on \"independence\"; do not accept or prompt on \"loneliness\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In this film, Max's wife Kim notices that the protagonist is wearing the same fancy bracelet that Max bought for her.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this 2020 comedy by Emma Seligman about a young Jewish woman named Danielle attending an event honoring a recently deceased relative.",
      "answer": "Shiva Baby"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Danielle's father is played by actor Fred Melamed, perhaps best known for portraying Sy Ableman, the title character of this 2009 film set in St. Louis Park, Minnesota.",
      "answer": "A Serious Man"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Seligman has cited these directors of A Serious Man and Inside Llewyn Davis as an influence on Shiva Baby.",
      "answer": "Coen brothers (or Coens; or Joel and Ethan Coen)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A character in this story commits suicide with pills and sherry after discovering that her lover has taken Madge to a restaurant.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this short story that begins \"John and Mary meet-what happens next?\" and imagines six possible outcomes.",
      "answer": "Happy Endings"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "\"Happy Endings\" is by this Canadian author of The Handmaid's Tale.",
      "answer": "Margaret (Eleanor) Atwood"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Atwood novel cuts between Iris Chase Griffen's present life, her past life, and the title novel -within-a-novel, which is credited to her sister Laura.",
      "answer": "The Blind Assassin"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This criterion is superseded by the Ledoux [leh-DOO] criterion in the presence of composition gradients.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this criterion that predicts instability when the temperature gradient in a stratified fluid is super-adiabatic [AY-dee-uh-BAT-ik].",
      "answer": "Schwarzschild [SHWARTS-\"shield\"] criterion"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In terms of the gravitational constant G, speed of light c, and mass M, what is the Schwarzschild radius for a black hole of mass M?",
      "answer": "2GM/c2 [\"two G M over c squared\"]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Schwarzschild telescope eliminates both coma and this other aberration that distorts images made by mirrors with a namesake shape.",
      "answer": "spherical aberration"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This artist's study drawings include a 72-faced polyhedron studded with diamond peaks.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "What artist made a 15th-century drawing of a chalice that looks strikingly like a wireframe image used in modern 3D modeling?",
      "answer": "Paolo Uccello [oo-CHAY-loh] (or Paolo di Dono)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Uccello's wireframe chalice was a study for this drafting technique that depends on a vanishing point.",
      "answer": "linear perspective (or point-projection perspective; accept one-point perspective)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Uccello also made a wireframe study of a mazzocchio [mah-ZOH-kee-oh], a doughnut-shaped type of headgear shown in his Life of Noah frescoes in the Green Cloister of this church that also contains Masaccio's The Holy Trinity.",
      "answer": "Santa Maria Novella"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A portrait composed by this man shows his bearded assistant, Marcus Sparling, sitting aboard the \"Photographic Van.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this pioneer of British war photography, who founded the Photographic Society after  the Great Exhibition of 1851.",
      "answer": "Roger Fenton"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Fenton and James Robertson photographed the siege of Sevastopol during this war.",
      "answer": "Crimean War"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Two versions of Fenton's photo Valley of the Shadow of Death differ in the placement of these discarded items: either in the path of a dirt road, or lying in the adjacent ditch.",
      "answer": "cannon balls (or round shot or solid shot; do not accept or prompt on \"cannon\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Ali Smith's novel Girl Meets Boy is inspired by the myth of this character, whose poor parents Ligdus and Telethusa could not afford a dowry.  For 10 p oints each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this character who is born a girl, raised as a boy, and then prays to the gods to be transformed into a man before marrying Ianthe [EE-ann-thay].",
      "answer": "Iphis"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This Egyptian goddess responds to Iphis's prayers.  The syncretic deity Serapis [sih-RAY-pis] often replaced Osiris as her consort in Greco-Roman cults.",
      "answer": "Isis [\"EYE\"-siss]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Lapith woman was also transformed into a man, and given impenetrabl e skin, after being raped by Poseidon.",
      "answer": "Caeneus [kay-NEE-us] (accept Caenis)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Gary Martin's \"methods manual\" for this discipline uses Brent Berlin's classification of uses of Rapanea by the Tzeltal people as an example.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Mark Plotkin is a scholar within what interdisciplinary field that fuses biology and social science?",
      "answer": "ethnobotany (accept ethnobotanists; prompt on \"ethnoecology\" or \"ethnoecologist(s)\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Plotkin's wrote a book of \"tales\" of apprenticeship to one of these religious men who visit the spirit world in an altered state of consciousness.",
      "answer": "shamans (accept Tales of a Shaman's Apprentice)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Peruvian-American author discussed training with a Yaqui [YAH-kee] shaman in his 1968 book The Teachings of Don Juan.",
      "answer": "Carlos Castaneda (or Carlos Castañeda)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about dynamical systems:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This is the collection of points generated by applying a system's evolution function to a starting point.  This term is also used for the path of an astronomical body through space.",
      "answer": "orbit(s) or trajectory (or trajectories)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Conservative systems obey this Frenchman's recurrence theorem.  He lends his name to a \"map\" that plots the points where periodic orbits first intersect a section transverse to the system's flow.",
      "answer": "Henri Poincaré (accept Poincaré recurrence theorem or Poincaré map(s) or Poincaré section(s))"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This type of orbit connects a saddle point to itself.  Its \"hetero\" counterpart connects different fixed points.",
      "answer": "homoclinic orbit(s)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This U.S. ambassador facilitated a meeting in which Félix Díaz [FAY-leeks DEE-ahz] allied with a general to carry out a military coup [koo].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this ambassador who was recalled shortly after he helped to arrange the \"Pact of the Embassy\" during the Ten Tragic Days.",
      "answer": "Henry Lane Wilson"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Díaz and Victoriano Huerta [veek-tor-ee-AH-noh \"WARE\"-tah] overthrew this democratically elected Mexican president, who had earlier led the 1910 revolution that ended the Porfiriato [por-feer-ee-AH-toh].",
      "answer": "Francisco Madero [mah-\"DARE\"-oh] (or Francisco Ignacio Madero González or Francisco Ygnacio Madero González; accept Francisco Indalecio Madero González) [The Porfiriato was named after the dictator Porfirio Díaz, who was the uncle of Félix Díaz.]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A soldadera [\"sole\"-dah-\"DARE\"-ah] who fought for Francisco Madero may have inspired this popular revolutionary ballad about a woman who follows a military regiment \"madly in love with the sergeant.\"",
      "answer": "La Adelita [ah-day-LEE-tah]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The first \"journal\" of this type of music notes \"I have a 'Symphony of noises' in mind; after all, there has been a symphony of psalms.\"  For 10 poin ts each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Pierre Schaeffer's Cinq études de bruits [SAHNK ay-TOOD day broo-EE] are what type of music that involves the recording and manipulation of sounds on a medium like tape?",
      "answer": "musique concrète [\"music\" kohn-KRET] (or concrete music; do not accept or prompt on \"musique électronique\" or \"electronic music\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Schaeffer's musique concrète works include a symphony for this number of people, the number of channels in a monophonic recording.",
      "answer": "1 (or solo; accept Symphonie pour un homme seul or Symphony for One Man Alone)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This composer applied musique concrète techniques to a recording of a boy soprano in his Gesang der Jünglinge [geh-ZAHNG dair YOONG-ling-geh].  His 1957 compositon Gruppen [GROO-pen] calls for for three orchestras.",
      "answer": "Karlheinz Stockhausen"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The cabin in which one of these poems was written includes a plaque with the lines \"over all of the hills / peace comes anew.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Give this title of two German romantic poems, one of which was supposedly written under an oak.",
      "answer": "Wanderer's Nightsong (or Wandrers Nachtlied)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Those two poems titled \"Wanderer's Nightsong\" were written by this German author of the novel The Sorrows of Young Werther.",
      "answer": "Johann Wolfgang von Goethe [GUR-tuh]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The line \"tell, you stones, O speak, you towering palaces\" opens the first entry in this cycle of 24 poems, which Goethe wrote about a journey abroad.",
      "answer": "Roman Elegies (or Erotica Romana; or Romische Elegien)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Charlotte von Kirschbaum [shar-LOH-teh von KEERSH-baum] contributed significant amounts of this text, which rejects the idea of an abstract decree in its approach to the doctrine of election.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this unfinished, four-volume magnum opus of Swiss theologian Karl Barth [\"bart\"].",
      "answer": "Church Dogmatics (or Kirchliche Dogmatik)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Barth pioneered dialectical theology with a commentary on this long Pauline epistle addressed to churches in  an Italian city.",
      "answer": "Epistle to the Romans (or Letter to the Romans)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 1934 Barth wrote the essay Nein! in response to Emil Brunner, who had implicated Barth in an attempt to combine neo-orthodoxy with this extra-biblical argument for God.",
      "answer": "natural theology (or Natürliche Theologie)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This scientist co-developed the CLARITY technique, which uses hydrogels to render brain tissue transparent.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this scientist whose lab at Stanford published a 2005 paper describing the use of a protein from green algae called ChR2 to precisely create depolarization-mediated currents.",
      "answer": "Karl Deisseroth [\"DICE-uh-roth\"]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Karl Deisseroth's work formed the basis for this field, which designs systems to mani pulate the activity of neurons using light.",
      "answer": "optogenetics"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "ChR2 is an example of the \"channel\" type of these proteins.  In the eye, these proteins are activated by isomerization [\"eye\"-SAH-muh-ruh-ZAY-shun] of retinal [RET-in-al] to convert incoming photons to neural signals.",
      "answer": "rhodopsins (accept channelrhodopsins; prompt on \"opsins\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about epithets referring to thunderbolts in military history:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The twelfth of these largest units in the Imperial Roman Army was nicknamed fulminata [\"fool-me\"-NAH-tah] or \"thunderbolt\" for the insignia on its shields.  These units contained 3,000 to 6,000 men.",
      "answer": "legions (or legio; accept Legio XII Fulminata)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This Ottoman sultan was nicknamed \"the Thunderbolt\" after crushing a crusader army at the Battle of Nicopolis [nik-AH-puh-liss].",
      "answer": "Bayezid I (prompt on \"Bayezid\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A man of this name known as Keraunos [keh-RAU-nohs], or \"thunderbolt,\" seized the throne of Macedonia after the Battle of Corupedium [kuh-rup-EE-dee-um] and murdered Seleucus [suh-LOO-kus] Nicator.",
      "answer": "Ptolemy (or Ptolemaeus or Ptolemaios; accept Ptolemy Keraunos)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Warren Upham's two enduring publications are an encyclopedia of Minnesota geographic place names and a monograph that gave this body of water its name.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "What glacial lake drained south through the Traverse Gap into Glacial River Warren?",
      "answer": "(Glacial) Lake Agassiz [AGG-uh-see]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Louis Agassiz is the namesake of a glacier this state's Glacier National Park.",
      "answer": "Montana (accept MT [\"M-T\"])"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Agassiz is the namesake of a mountain that, from Flagstaff, blocks the view of this tallest mountain i n Arizona.",
      "answer": "Humphreys Peak (or Aaloosaktukwi or Dook'o'oosliid; prompt on \"Humphreys\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For functions f and g of variables p and q, this operation equals \"df/dp dg/dq\" [\"D-F D-P times D-G D-Q\"], minus \"df/dq dg/dp\" [\"D-F D-Q times D-G D-P\"].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Identify this operation named for a French physicist.",
      "answer": "Poisson bracket [pwah-SOHN \"bracket\"] (prompt on partial answer)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A variable A is a constant of motion if dA/dt [\"D-A D-T\"] equals the Poisson bracket of A with this quantity.  It represents the total energy of a system.",
      "answer": "Hamiltonian"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Paul Dirac introduced these constraints, whose Poisson bracket with all other constraints vanishes in a Hamiltonian system.  They are distinct from primary and secondary constraints.",
      "answer": "first class constraints"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A man with this surname ordered the fortification of Bunker Hill.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Give this surname of Artemas, a major-general who was made second-in-command of the Continental Army in 1776.",
      "answer": "(Artemas) Ward"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Another man surnamed Ward, Aaron Montgomery Ward, founded a dry goods store that became one of the first of these large retailers in the U.S. and competed with Macy's and Marshall Field.",
      "answer": "department stores"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A different Ward, Ward McAllister, popularized the notion that this many people comprised New York's high society in the Gilded Age, although McAllister's actual list contained only 150.",
      "answer": "400"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2010 the men's basketball team from this school won its only Big East Tourna ment championship.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this school, which lost in the Final Four of that year's NCAA tournament to eventual champion Duke in a game that its star Da'Sean Butler left due to a knee injury.  Jevon Carter [jeh-VAHN \"carter\"] later played for this school.",
      "answer": "West Virginia University (prompt on \"Mountaineers\" or \"WVU\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "That West Virginia team was coached by this man, who has coached at the school since 2007.",
      "answer": "Bob Huggins (or Robert Edward Huggins)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "West Virginia advanced to that Final Four with an Elite Eight upset of this top -seeded team, which was led by point guard John Wall and coach John Calipari.",
      "answer": "University of Kentucky (prompt on \"UK\" or \"Wildcats\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Chicago gangs are the subject of this man's first novel, Diversey [dih-VER-see].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this 20th-century American author whose novels include Long Remember and Spirit Lake, as well as one in which William Collins leads the \"Raiders.\"",
      "answer": "(Benjamin) MacKinlay Kantor [William Collins appears in Andersonville.]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Kantor wrote a 1961 book titled for this historical counterfactual.  Time -traveling South Africans supply AK-47s that prove decisive in this outcome in a 1992 novel.",
      "answer": "Confederacy winning the Civil War (accept answers indicating South or Confederacy or Confederate States or CSA winning the U.S. Civil War; accept If the South Had Won the War) [The second sentence refers to Harry Turtledove's The Guns of the South.]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Kantor's novel Glory for Me was adapted for the screen as The Best Years of Our Lives by this playwright, whose own works include Idiot's Delight and The Petrified Forest.",
      "answer": "Robert E(mmet) Sherwood"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Greece protested a treaty between Turkey and this country that would have established an exclusive economic zone.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "A \"Government of National Accord\" created after a 2011 NATO intervention signed that treaty on behalf of what North African country?",
      "answer": "Libya"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Turkey defended the treaty via this state-run news agency that, like state broadcaster TRT, is a mouthpiece for the ruling AKP.",
      "answer": "Anadolu Agency (or Anadolu Ajansi; prompt on \"AA\" or \"Anatolian (Agency)\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 2021 the deal was voided in Libya as incompatible with the United Nations convention that establishes a legal framework for maritime activities, which is almost always known by this six -letter acronym.",
      "answer": "UNCLOS [UNN-klahss or \"U-N-C-L-O-S\"] (accept UNCLOS III) [which stands for \"United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea.\"]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "These lifeforms are made from skin and cardiac muscle cells and designed using evolutionary algorithms.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these synthetic lifeforms developed in 2020 by a team including Sam Kriegman and Douglas Blackiston.",
      "answer": "xenobots [ZEE-noh-bots]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The first xenobots were created using cells from Xenopus laevis [ZEN-uh-puss LAY-viss], the \"African clawed\" species of this animal.",
      "answer": "African clawed frog(s) (accept African clawed toad(s))"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This two-word phrase refers to the way that the xenobots were designed via computer simulation.  This phrase is modeled on similar phrases like in vivo and in vitro.",
      "answer": "in silico"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Xenobots [ZEE-noh-bots] are synthetic lifeforms designed using evolutionary algorithms.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "The first xenobots were created using cells from Xenopus laevis [ZEN-uh-puss LAY-viss], the \"African clawed\" species of this animal.",
      "answer": "African clawed frog(s) (accept African clawed toad(s))"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Xenobots are made from skin cells and this type of tissue that is multinucleated [\"multi\"-NOO-klee-AY-tid] and striated [STRYE-ay-tid].",
      "answer": "cardiac muscle or cardiac myocytes or heart muscle (or myocardium; prompt on partial answers)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This two-word phrase refers to the way that the xenobots were designed via computer simulation.  This phrase is modeled on similar phrases like in vivo and in vitro.",
      "answer": "in silico [in SIL-ih-koh]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The last line of this poem repeats words like \"pleasing\" and \"prince\" from its first line.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Middle English poem in which a man loses the title precious object and dreams that it is reborn as a woman on the far bank of a stream.",
      "answer": "Pearl (or Perle)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The anonymous Pearl Poet is also thought to have written a poem in which this character is ensnared in a \"beheading game\" by the Green Knight.",
      "answer": "Sir Gawain (accept Sir Gawain and the Green Knight)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Pearl Poet was a contemporary of this friend of Geoffrey Chaucer who wrote Vox Clamantis [vox klah-MAHN-tiss] and Confessio Amantis [kohn-FESS-ee-oh ah-MAHN-tiss].",
      "answer": "John Gower"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Artemas Ward ordered the fortification of this site.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "William Prescott commanded the Patriot defense at what battle, where most fighting actually occurred at a site named for the Breed family?",
      "answer": "Battle of Bunker Hill"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Aaron Montgomery Ward oversaw one of these businesses which became prominent in the early 20th century.  Marshall Field's and Wanamaker's were this kind of business.",
      "answer": "department stores"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Ward McAllister popularized the notion that this many people comprised New York's high society in the Gilded Age, though McAllister's actual list contained only 150.",
      "answer": "400"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In this film, Max's wife Kim notices that the protagonist is wearing the same fancy bracelet that Max bought for her.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this 2020 comedy by Emma Seligman about a young Jewish woman named Danielle attending the title event.",
      "answer": "Shiva Baby"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Many reviewers compared the horror film-like tension in Shiva Baby to this 2019 film about the gambling addict Howard Ratner.",
      "answer": "Uncut Gems"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Seligman has cited these directors of No Country for Old Men and Fargo as an influence on Shiva Baby.",
      "answer": "Coen brothers (or Coens; or Joel and Ethan Coen)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about musique concrète [\"music\" kohn-KRET], which involves the recording, manipulation, and assembly of sounds on a medium such as tape:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The first of composer Pierre Schaeffer's Cinq études de bruits [SAHNK ay-TOOD day broo-EE]-the first ever musique concrète works-was based on the sounds of these vehicles.  Arthur Honegger depicted one of t hem in Pacific 231.",
      "answer": "trains or locomotives"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Schaeffer's other musique concrète works include a symphony for this number of people, the number of channels in a monophonic recording.",
      "answer": "1 (or solo; accept Symphonie pour un homme seul or Symphony for One Man Alone)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This composer applied musique concrète techniques to a recording of a boy soprano in his landmark Gesang der Jünglinge [geh-ZAHNG dair YOONG-ling-geh].  He called for three orchestras  in his Gruppen [GROO-pen].",
      "answer": "Karlheinz Stockhausen [\"STOCK-how\"-zin]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "U.S. ambassador Henry Lane Wilson facilitated the \"Pact of the Embassy,\" in which Félix Díaz [FAY-leeks DEE-ahz] allied with this general to carry out a military coup [koo].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this man who bombarded the capital city he was supposedly defending against the rebellion of Díaz.",
      "answer": "Victoriano Huerta [veek-toh-ree-AH-noh \"WARE\"-tah] (or José Victoriano Huerta Márquez)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Huerta and Díaz agreed to the Pact of the Embassy at the end of this February 1913 period, whose name refers to suffering endured by residents of Mexico City.",
      "answer": "Ten Tragic Days (or the Tragic Ten Days or La Decena Trágica)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Díaz and Huerta overthrew this president, who had led the 1910 uprising that began the Mexican Revolution and ended the Porfiriato [por-feer-ee-AH-toh].",
      "answer": "Francisco Madero [mah-\"DARE\"-oh] (or Francisco Ignacio Madero González or Francisco Ygnacio Madero González; accept Francisco Indalecio Madero González) [The Porfiriato was named after the dictator Porfirio Díaz, who was the uncle of Félix Díaz.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the field of ethnobotany:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Early ethnobotany included work among the Sámi [SAH-mee] people by this scientist, who published the tenth edition of Systema Naturae in 1758.",
      "answer": "Carolus Linnaeus [KAR-oh-luss lih-NAY-uss] (or Carl Linnaeus or Carl von Linné)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Ethnobotanist Mark Plotkin's works include some \"tales\" of apprenticeship to one of these people who visit the spirit world while in a state of altered consciousness.  Their name comes from a Tungusic language.",
      "answer": "shamans (accept Tales of a Shaman's Apprentice)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Ethnobotanist Weston La Barre studied the use of this drug.  The case Employment Division v. Smith held that firing someone for using it did not violate the free exercise clause.",
      "answer": "peyote [pay-OH-tee]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For functions f and g of variables p and q, this operation equals \"df/dp dg/dq\" [\"D-F D-P times D-G D-Q\"], minus \"df/dq dg/dp\" [\"D-F D-Q times D-G D-P\"].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Identify this operation named for a French physicist.",
      "answer": "Poisson bracket [pwah-SOHN \"bracket\"] (prompt on partial answer)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A variable A is a constant of motion if dA/dt [\"D-A D-T\"] equals the Poisson bracket of A with this quantity.  It represents the total energy of a system.",
      "answer": "Hamiltonian"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This man introduced the notion of first class constraints, whose Poisson bracket with all other constraints vanishes in a Hamiltonian system.  His namesake delta function is an infin itely tall, infinitely thin spike.",
      "answer": "Paul Dirac [dih-RAHK] (or Paul Adrien Maurice Dirac; accept Dirac delta function)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A child is attacked by a fairy king in this author's poem \"Erlkönig\" [AYRL-kur-neeg].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this author of the novel The Sorrows of Young Werther.",
      "answer": "Johann Wolfgang von Goethe [GUR-tuh]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Goethe wrote two poems of this title, one of which was supposedly written under an oak, the other of which w as written in on the wall of a cabin.",
      "answer": "Wanderer's Nightsong (or Wandrers Nachtlied)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A collection of elegies was inspired by Goethe's travels in 1768 and 1788 in what is now this country.",
      "answer": "Italy (or Italian Republic or Italia or Repubblica Italiana)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This artist made a 15th-century drawing of a chalice that looks strikingly like a wireframe image used in modern 3D modeling.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this artist of three paintings of the Battle of San Romano.",
      "answer": "Paolo Uccello [oo-CHAY-loh] (or Paolo di Dono)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Uccello's wireframe chalice was a study for this drafting technique that depends on a vanishing point.",
      "answer": "linear perspective (or point-projection perspective; accept one-point perspective)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Uccello made a wireframe study of a mazzocchio [mah-ZOH-kee-oh], a doughnut-shaped type of headgear shown in his Life of Noah frescoes in the Green Cloister of this church that also contains Masaccio's The Holy Trinity.",
      "answer": "Santa Maria Novella"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about military epithets referring to thunderbolts:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The twelfth of these largest units in the Imperial Roman Army, which contained 3,000 to 6,000 men, was  nicknamed fulminata [\"fool-me\"-NAH-tah] or \"thunderbolt.\"",
      "answer": "legions (or legio; accept Legio XII Fulminata)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This Ottoman sultan was nicknamed \"the Thunderbolt\" after crushing a crusader army at Nicopolis [nik-AH-puh-liss].",
      "answer": "Bayezid I (accept Yildirim Bayezid; prompt on \"Bayezid\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A man of this name known as Keraunos [keh-RAO-nohs], or \"thunderbolt,\" seized Macedonia after the Battle of Corupedium [kuh-rup-EE-dee-um].  The thirteenth of another line of kings of this name drowned while fleeing his sister's forces in 47 B",
      "answer": "Ptolemy (or Ptolemaeus or Ptolemaios; accept Ptolemy Keraunos or Ptolemy XIII)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A character in this story commits suicide with pills and sherry after discover ing that her lover has taken Madge to a restaurant.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Margaret Atwood short story that begins \"John and Mary meet. What happens next?\" and imagines six possible outcomes.",
      "answer": "Happy Endings"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Testaments is the sequel to this Atwood novel, in which fertile women in the Republic of Gilead are forced to produce children.",
      "answer": "The Handmaid's Tale"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Booker-winning 2000 Atwood novel cuts between Iris Chase Griffen's present life, her p ast life, and the title novel-within-a-novel, which is credited to her sister Laura.",
      "answer": "The Blind Assassin"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about gene expression:",
    "A": {
      "question": "To synthesize mRNA from a gene, RNA polymerase [puh-LIM-uh-\"RACE\"] must bind to what short region just upstream of the gene?",
      "answer": "promoter region"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The expression of a gene can be increased when an activator protein binds to one of these regions, which may be upstream or downstream from a gene and up to one megabase pairs away.",
      "answer": "enhancers"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This protein complex that holds sister chromatids [\"CROW\"-muh-tids] together during cell division appears to form the loops responsible for bringing enhancers and promoters together.",
      "answer": "cohesin [koh-HEE-zin]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about psychologist D. W. Winnicott:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Winnicott posited \"true and false\" versions of this concept.  Charles Cooley theorized a \"looking -glass\" version of this concept.",
      "answer": "self (accept true and false self or looking-glass self)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Winnicott wrote a book titled for this behavior \"and reality.\"  The \"deep\" form of this activity titles a Clifford Geertz essay on cockfighting.",
      "answer": "play (or playing games; accept Playing and Reality; accept Deep Play: Notes on the Balinese Cockfight)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Winnicott argued that the \"capacity to be alone\" develops in the \"presence of\" this kind of person.  Attachment to an adult with this role is tested in Mary Ainsworth's \"strange situation\" experiment.",
      "answer": "mother (prompt on \"parent\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Chicago gangs are the subject of this man's first novel, Diversey.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this author who told the story of a prisoner-of-war camp that houses a gang known as \"The Raiders\" in 1955 novel.",
      "answer": "MacKinlay Kantor [That novel is Andersonville.]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Kantor's Andersonville is set during this war, which is also the setting of Stephen Crane's The Red Badge of Courage.",
      "answer": "(American) Civil War"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Civil War is a popular subject of novels in this genre, including a 1961 novel by Kantor.  Harry Turtledove's Southern Victory series is in this genre.",
      "answer": "alternate history (or althist or AH; prompt on \"speculative fiction\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This island's Maho Beach is near an airport runway, leading planes to pass very closely over it.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Caribbean island that is divided between two European countries.  It was heavily damaged by Hurricane Irma in 2017.",
      "answer": "Saint Martin (or Sint Maarten)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Saint Martin lies east of this island, the largest U.S. territory in the Caribbean.",
      "answer": "Puerto Rico [PWAIR-toh REE-koh] (or Commonwealth of Puerto Rico or Estado Libre Asociado de Puerto Rico)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Today, control of Saint Martin is split between France and this European country, which also controls Aruba and Curaçao [kurr-uh-SAUW].",
      "answer": "The Netherlands (or Kingdom of the Netherlands or Koninkrijk der Nederlanden; accept Holland)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about British war photographer Roger Fenton:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Fenton was sent to document this war, in which British troops fought at the Battle of Inkerman.",
      "answer": "Crimean War"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Fenton's photographs depicted the siege of this Russian port and naval base, which was defended by the Malakoff Redoubt.",
      "answer": "Sevastopol (or Sebastopol)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Two versions of Fenton's photo Valley of the Shadow of Death differ in the placement of these discarded weapons: either in the path of a dirt road, or lying in the adjacent ditch.",
      "answer": "cannon balls (or round shot or solid shot; do not accept or prompt on \"cannon\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2010 the men's basketball team from this school won its only Big East Tournament championship.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this school, which lost in the Final Four of that year's NCAA tournament to eventual champion Duke.  It plays home games in Morgantown.",
      "answer": "West Virginia University (prompt on \"Mountaineers\" or \"WVU\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The 2010 West Virginia team was coached by this man, who has coached at the school since 2007.",
      "answer": "Bob Huggins (or Robert Edward Huggins)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "West Virginia advanced to the Final Four with an Elite Eight upset of this top -seeded team, which is coached by John Calipari [kal-ih-PAR-ee].",
      "answer": "University of Kentucky (prompt on \"UK\" or \"Wildcats\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the myth of Iphis, who was born a girl and prayed to the gods to be transformed into a man before marrying Ianthe [EE-ann-thay]:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Iphis lived on this island.  Zeus brought Europa to this island and gave her the bronze giant Talos as a  guard.",
      "answer": "Crete (or Kríti or Krete)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Iphis's prayers were answered by this Egyptian goddess, the wife of Osiris.",
      "answer": "Isis [\"EYE\"-siss]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Lapith woman was also transformed into a man, and given impenetrable skin, after being raped by Poseidon.",
      "answer": "Caeneus [kay-NEE-us] (accept Caenis)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the scientific work of Karl Schwarzschild [SHWARTS-\"shield\"]:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The Schwarzschild criterion predicts that this process will begin in a star when the temperat ure gradient is super-adiabatic [AY-dee-uh-BAT-ik].",
      "answer": "convection"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In terms of the gravitational constant G, speed of light c, and mass M, what is the Schwarzschild radius for a black hole of mass M?",
      "answer": "2GM/c2 [\"two G M over c squared\"]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Schwarzschild telescope eliminates both coma and this other aberration that distorts images made by mirrors with a namesake shape.",
      "answer": "spherical aberration"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Charlotte von Kirschbaum [shar-LOH-teh von KEERSH-baum] collaborated with this man on a text which rejects the idea of an abstract decree in its approach to the doctrine of election.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Swiss author of the unfinished, four-volume magnum opus Church Dogmatics.",
      "answer": "Karl Barth [\"bart\"]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Barth pioneered dialectical theology with a commentary on this long Pauline epistle addressed to churches in an Italian city.",
      "answer": "Epistle to the Romans (or Letter to the Romans)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Karl Barth was an influence on this author of Black Theology and Black Power who taught at Union Theological Seminary until his 2018 death.",
      "answer": "James (Hal) Cone"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This country's interim \"Government of National Accord\" was dissolved in 2021.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this country where the new Government of National Unity seeks to bring together rival parliaments that have operated in Tripoli and Tobruk [toh-BROOK].",
      "answer": "Libya"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Under the GNA, Libya signed an agreement to establish an exclusive economic zone with this country, whose disputed maritime border with Greece is defined by the Seville Map.",
      "answer": "Turkey (or Republic of Turkey or Türkiye Cumhuriyeti)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Critics argued that the deal violated the United Nations convention on this body of law governing maritime environments.",
      "answer": "law of the sea (accept United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea or UNCLOS)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "If a group has this property, the group's Cayley table is symmetric.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this property that makes a group abelian [uh-BEE-lee-un].",
      "answer": "commutative property or commutativity"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Given a non-abelian group, this is the name for the subgroup of elements that do commute with all the members of the group.  In other words, this subgroup is all a for which a g equals g a for every g in the full group.",
      "answer": "center of the group"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The center must be this type of subgroup since its left and right cosets [KOH-\"sets\"] are equal.  Equivalently, this type of subgroup is the kernel of a homomorphism of the group.",
      "answer": "normal subgroups"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these intervals used in music:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This interval consists of 12 half-steps, the distance between middle C and the C above it.",
      "answer": "(perfect) octave(s)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The use of this highly dissonant interval, sometimes called the \"devil in music,\" was shunned, but not banned, in medieval music.",
      "answer": "tritone(s) [\"TRY-tones\"] (accept augmented fourth(s) or diminished fifth(s); prompt on \"fourth\" or \"fifth\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The tonic and dominant of a major scale-such as the C and G in C major-define this interval.",
      "answer": "perfect fifth(s)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "L'Hôpital's [loh-pee-TAHL'Z] rule is used to evaluate these values.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these values that a function approaches but may not reach.",
      "answer": "limits"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "If a function equals its limit at a point, the function has this property at that point.",
      "answer": "continuity or being continuous"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "L'Hôpital's rule describes how to take limits of the form \"zero over zero\" and \"infinity over infinity,\" which are examples of this type of expression.",
      "answer": "indeterminate forms"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In a show on the Starz network, Stephen Amell [uh-MEL] and Alexander Ludwig [rhymes with \"good wig\"] play brothers who are part of a \"league\" for this activity.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "What type of athletic entertainment is the subject of the show Heels?",
      "answer": "professional wrestling (accept wrestlers or wrestles or wrestled; accept Duffy Wrestling League)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Alison Brie [bree] played a wrestler called \"Zoya the Destroya\" [ZOY-uh \"the\" dess-TROY-uh] in this Netflix show about a 1980s women's league.",
      "answer": "GLOW [\"glow\"] [\"GLOW\" stands for \"Gorgeous Ladies of Wrestling.\"]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Many wrestlers of the '80s are depicted in the sitcom Young Rock, which is based on the life of this film star who rose to prominence in the WWE [\"W-W-E\"].",
      "answer": "Dwayne (Douglas) Johnson (prompt on \"The Rock\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This European country has been governed by the Fifth Republic since 1958.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this country, whose Fourth Republic collapsed after having 21 administrations in its 12 -year existence.",
      "answer": "France (or French Republic or République française)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This French leader returned from retirement to lead the transitional government, b ecoming the first president of the Fifth Republic.",
      "answer": "Charles de Gaulle [sharl duh \"GOAL\"] (or Charles André Joseph Marie de Gaulle; do not accept or prompt on \"Gaulle\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A major reason for the Fourth Republic's collapse was the crisis involving t his French colony, which gained independence in 1962.",
      "answer": "Algeria"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The a and b parameters of the van der Waals [vahlz] equation account for deviations from this equation.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this equation that can be written as PV = nRT [\"P-V equals N-R-T\"].",
      "answer": "ideal gas law (or general gas law; prompt on \"gas law\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The ideal gas law does not account for molecular forces between \"induced\" examples of these structures, which produce London dispersion forces.",
      "answer": "(electric) dipoles [\"DIE-pole\"] (or instantaneous dipoles or induced dipoles)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The T in the ideal gas law stands for this quantity, which for an ideal gas equals the average kinetic energy of its constituent particles.",
      "answer": "(absolute) temperature (or thermodynamic temperature)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Instructions given to Moses called for this container to be two-and-a-half cubits long and covered with gold.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this wooden box that carried the tablets containing the Ten Commandments.",
      "answer": "Ark of the Covenant (or aron haberit)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This Old Testament book describes God giving instructions for the Ark of the Covenant to Moses on Mount Sinai.",
      "answer": "Book of Exodus (or Shmot)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Ark of the Covenant was kept in a sacred tent known in Hebrew as the mishkan [MISH-kahn] and usually translated as this word, which also names a Mormon choir.",
      "answer": "tabernacle (accept Mormon Tabernacle Choir)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about John Pierre Burr:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Burr was the son of founding father Aaron Burr and Mary Emmons, a servant born in this city .  In 1756 43 British soldiers died in a prison called this city's \"Black Hole.\"",
      "answer": "Calcutta (or Kolkata; accept Black Hole of Calcutta)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "John Pierre Burr became a \"conductor\" on this metaphorical network through which people escaped slavery before the Civil War.",
      "answer": "Underground Railroad"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "At some points in his career, Burr encouraged Black Americans to emigrate to this country.  It was founded in 1804 by Jean-Jacques Dessalines [dess-uh-leen].",
      "answer": "Haiti (or Republic of Haiti or Republique d'Haïti or Repiblik d' Ayiti)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about Ferris wheels:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The original Ferris wheel was built in this city when it hosted the World's Columbian Exposition in 1893.",
      "answer": "Chicago, Illinois"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This wheel in England was the tallest in the world when it was completed in 2000.  It stands on the south bank of the River Thames.",
      "answer": "London Eye (or Millennium Wheel)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "What is now the world's tallest Ferris wheel, the High Roller, is on the namesake \"strip\" of this Nevada city near the Flamingo casino.",
      "answer": "Las Vegas (accept Las Vegas Strip)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This poem's title character advises \"He prayeth best who loveth best / all things both great and small.\"  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this poem whose title character describes how a dead albatross that he killed with a crossbow was placed around his neck.",
      "answer": "The Rime of the Ancient Mariner"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This English poet wrote The Rime of the Ancient Mariner.",
      "answer": "Samuel Taylor Coleridge"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Ancient Mariner waylays a \"guest\" planning to attend one of these events, to whom he recounts his tale.",
      "answer": "wedding (or marriage or nuptials; accept the wedding-guest)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Pencil and paper ready.  For 10 points each -answer these questions about a cube whose edges each have a length of 2:",
    "A": {
      "question": "What is the volume of the cube?",
      "answer": "8 [V = s3 = 23 = 8]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "What is the length of any space diagonal of the cube, given that space diagonals have their endpoints on diametrically-opposite vertices [VUR-tis-eez]?  You have 10 seconds.",
      "answer": "2 times the square root of 3 or 2 root 3 or 2 radical 3 [d = sqrt(x2 + y2 + z2) = sqrt(22 + 22 + 22) = sqrt(22 * 3) = sqrt(22) * sqrt(3) = 2 root 3]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "What is the volume of the largest sphere that can fit inside the cube, given that the sphere would have a diameter of 2?",
      "answer": "4/3 pi [\"four-thirds pi\"] or 4 pi/3 or 1 1/3 pi (do not accept or prompt on \"4/3\" or \"1 1/3\") [V = (4/3) * pi * r2 = (4/3) * pi * (d/2)2 = (4/3) * pi * (2/2)2 = (4/3) * pi * 12 = 4/3 pi]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 1973 the Australian government controversially purchased this artist's Blue Poles-Number 11, 1952 for over one million Australian dollars.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this painter whose working technique involved sloshing, slinging, and dripping paint on large canvases.",
      "answer": "(Paul) Jackson Pollock"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Pollock's work was a milestone in a style of art known by this word, followed by the word \"expressionism.\"  In general, this word describes non-representational art.",
      "answer": "abstract (expressionism) (or abstract expression(ist))"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Pollock admired the work of José Clemente Orozco [hoh-ZAY klay-MIN-tay oh-ROHZ-koh], a muralist from this country.  Another muralist from this country painted Man at the Crossroads.",
      "answer": "Mexico (or United Mexican States or Estados Unidos Mexicanos) [Man at the Crossroads was created by Diego Rivera.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Police shot 69 unarmed Black protesters in the Sharpeville Massacre, a demonstration against these specific laws.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these laws that specifically limited the movement of civilians in 20th -century South Africa by requiring all citizens to carry namesake books noting their race.",
      "answer": "pass laws (accept passbook(s))"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Pass laws were integral to this system of segregation in place until the 1990s.",
      "answer": "apartheid [ah-PAR-tayd]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Defiance Campaign was an anti-pass law movement led by this political party to which Nelson Mandela belonged.",
      "answer": "ANC [\"A-N-C\"] (or African National Congress)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Danish scientist Hans Christian Ørsted [UR-sted] showed that an electric current creates this type of field.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this type of field that affects compass needles.",
      "answer": "magnetic field (accept B-field)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Earth's magnetic field is generated by currents due to movements of molten metal in this layer of the Earth.",
      "answer": "outer core (prompt on \"core\"; do not accept or prompt on \"inner core\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The direction of a magnetic field generated by a current is given by this rule.  It's also used to find the direction of a cross product.",
      "answer": "right-hand rule (do not accept or prompt on \"hand rule\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about animals in picture books:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The title bat is separated from her mother and befriends the young birds Pip, Flitter, and Flap in this book by Janell [juh-NEL] Cannon.",
      "answer": "Stellaluna [\"stella-luna\"]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This inquisitive monkey created by H.  and Margret Rey [ray] eventually leaves the zoo, and goes to live with the man in the yellow hat.",
      "answer": "Curious George"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "One of these animals named Olivia appears in picture books by Ian Falconer [\"falcon\"-ur].  In a series by Mo Willems, the elephant Gerald is best friends with one of these mammals.",
      "answer": "pigs (or Sus or Sus domesticus; accept swine or hogs or piglets; accept Piggie(s); accept Elephant and Piggie)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This country's closest point to the U.S. is in the islands of Bimini [bee-MEE-nee], which are about 50 miles east of Miami.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Caribbean archipelago whose districts include North Andros and Exuma.",
      "answer": "The Bahamas (or Commonwealth of the Bahamas)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This is the capital and most populous city of the Bahamas.",
      "answer": "Nassau [NAA-\"saw\"]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The tropical climate of the Bahamas is moderated by this warm oceanic current that originates in the Gulf of Mexico.",
      "answer": "Gulf Stream"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about fire in ancient Rome:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This emperor built his Golden House on land cleared by the Great Fire of AD 64, which he blamed on Christians.",
      "answer": "Nero (Claudius Caesar Augustus Drusus Germanicus)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This member of the First Triumvirate [\"try\"-UM-vih-rut], by some accounts the wealthiest Roman in history, gained some of his wealth by running a extortionary fire brigade.",
      "answer": "Crassus [\"CRASS\"-uss] (or Marcus Licinius Crassus)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "These six priestesses of the goddess Vesta [VESS-tuh] tended to an eternal flame in a temple in the Roman Forum.",
      "answer": "Vestal Virgins (accept Vestales)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For the first time, researchers in 2021 observed particles in certain environments reliably return to their exact starting positions.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "The phenomenon is a \"boomerang effect\" named for this branch of physics that describes behavior at atomic and subatomic scales when physical values become discrete.",
      "answer": "quantum mechanics (or quantum physics; accept quantum boomerang (effect))"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The quantum boomerang effect occurs in environments with a high level of this quantity.  It is proportional to the log of the number of microstates according to Boltzmann's formula.",
      "answer": "entropy"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The observed particles were stimulated with one of these devices that emits light by stimulated emission of radiation.",
      "answer": "laser(s)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A lack of the G6PD [G-six-P-D] enzyme leads to oxidative destruction of these cells.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these non-nucleated cells that contain hemoglobin to transport oxygen.",
      "answer": "red blood cell(s) (or erythrocytes or red blood corpuscle(s) or erythroid cell(s) or haematids; prompt on \"RBC(s)\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A glutamate-to-valine mutation in hemoglobin causes this condition which causes red blood cells to take a crescent shape.",
      "answer": "sickle cell disease or sickle cell anemia"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Both G6PD deficiency and sickle hemoglobin may help protect against this infect ious disease spread by Anopheles mosquitoes.",
      "answer": "malaria"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these common features of a baseball stadium:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Relief pitchers warm up in this area, which is typically in foul territory or beyond the outfield fence.",
      "answer": "bullpen(s) (prompt on \"pen(s)\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The edge of the outfield is lined with dirt known by this term, because it serves as an indicator that fie lders are close to a wall.",
      "answer": "warning track(s)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "To ensure that hitters can easily see a pitched ball, most parks have a solid, dark wall beyond center field known by this two-word term.",
      "answer": "batter's eye (accept batter's eye screen)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The term \"Yahgan\" [YAH-gahn] refers to the indigenous people of this archipelago [ARK-ih-PEL-uh-goh].  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "The Strait of Magellan [muh-JEL-lin] separates what archipelago from the South American mainland?",
      "answer": "Tierra del Fuego [\"tee-AIR-ah\" del FWAY-goh]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "South of Tierra del Fuego is this \"passage\" used by ships sailing around South America.  Like the Strait of Magellan, this passage is named for an explorer.",
      "answer": "Drake Passage (or Mar de Hoces) [after Sir Francis Drake]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Argentina and this long, narrow country to the west of Argentina share the islands of Tierra del Fuego.",
      "answer": "Chile [CHEE-lay] (or Republic of Chile or República de Chile)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Thomas Midgley helped to develop the first commercial one of these compounds, which is sometimes called \"R-12.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these refrigerants that were phased out by the Montreal Protocol.",
      "answer": "CFCs or chlorofluorocarbons [KLOR-oh-FLOR-oh-KAR-bunz] (accept Freons; do not accept or prompt on \"HCFC(s)\" or \"hydrochlorofluorocarbon(s)\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "CFCs exacerbated a \"hole\" in this atmospheric layer named for a molecule  consisting of three atoms of oxygen.",
      "answer": "ozone layer (accept ozone hole)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Ozone depletion may lead to increased cancer risk because the ozone layer absorbs most of this type of radiation from the Sun.",
      "answer": "ultraviolet or UV [\"U-V\"] (accept ultraviolet C or UV-C or vacuum ultraviolet or vacuum UV)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Critics of this politician often cite his role in the 2002 anti-Muslim riots in Gujarat [GOO-juh-raht].  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this leader of the nationalist party BJP.",
      "answer": "Narendra (Damodardas) Modi [nah-ren-drah moh-dee]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Modi is the current prime minister of this country.",
      "answer": "India (or Republic of India or Bharat(iya) Ganarajya)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 2019 Modi dissolved a state named for Jammu [JAH-moo] and this other region, reorganizing it into a pair of union territories.",
      "answer": "Kashmir (accept Jammu and Kashmir)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This poem's speaker muses \"I'd like to get away from earth awhile.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this poem whose title trees are described as clicking \"upon themselves / as the breeze rises\" after an ice storm.",
      "answer": "Birches"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "\"Birches\" is by this poet, who also wrote \"Stopping by Woods on a Snowy Evening.\"",
      "answer": "Robert (Lee) Frost"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This other poem by Frost is about a farmer whose neighbor quotes the adage \"good fences make good neighbors.\"",
      "answer": "Mending Wall"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The Southern Song and Northern Yuan were examples of these states that clung to power after dy nastic shifts.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Give this term for a small remnant ruled by a state that has been diminished by conquest or other losses.",
      "answer": "rump state"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Seleucid [sel-YOO-sud] Empire was reduced to a rump state in Syria after the conquests of Mithridates I [mith-ruh-DATE-eez \"the 1st\"] of this Asian empire, known for its horse archers' tactic of firing while retreating.",
      "answer": "Parthian [PAR-thee-in] Empire (or Parthia or Parthians or Arsacid Empire or Arsacids; accept Parthian shot)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Southern Ming became a rump state after this last dynasty of imperial China took power in 1644.",
      "answer": "(Great) Qing [cheeng] Dynasty (or Ch'ing Dynasty or Manchu Dynasty or Qing cháo)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these locations of wintry mazes:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The largest ice maze in the U.S. is in the town of Stillwater in this state's Minneapolis -St. Paul metropolitan area.",
      "answer": "Minnesota (accept MN [\"M-N\"])"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In 2021 a massive snow maze was constructed in Saint Adolphe in this Canadian Prairie province, which lies directly west of Ontario.",
      "answer": "Manitoba"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "At this European country's southern border along the Tatra Mountains, a large snow maze is among the attractions of Snowlandia in its so-called \"Winter Capital\" of Zakopane [zahk-koh-PAH-nay].",
      "answer": "Poland (or Republic of Poland or Rzeczpospolita Polska)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Virtual pairs of these particles and their antiparticles create a phenomenon called a \"sea.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "A proton consists of three of what particles, whose flavors include \"up\" and \"down\"?",
      "answer": "quarks (accept quark sea or sea quarks)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The annihilation of sea quarks produces these particles, which are found along with quarks in a namesake type of plasma.",
      "answer": "gluons [GLOO-ahnz] (accept quark-gluon plasma)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Because they have color charge, quarks and gluons have this property, meaning that they cannot exist in isolation.",
      "answer": "color confinement (accept confined)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the May Laws of 1873:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The May Laws were part of this empire's attempt to suppress the Catholic Church during a \"culture struggle.\"",
      "answer": "German Empire (or Germany; accept Deutsches Reich)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The German May Laws were the brainchild of this Prussian, who was nicknamed the \"Iron Chancellor.\"",
      "answer": "Otto von Bismarck (or Otto Eduard Leopold, Fürst von Bismarck)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "During the Kulturkampf, Bismarck promised that 19th-century Germany \"would not go\" to this place, an Italian fortress where medieval Emperor Henry IV [\"the fourth\"] did penance during the Investiture Controversy.",
      "answer": "Canossa [kuh-NOH-sah] (accept We will not go to Canossa or penance at Canossa or walk to Canossa)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about people Donald Trump fired by tweet:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Rex Tillerson claimed that he learned of his firing from this office from a tweet.  Mike Pompeo [pahm-PAY-oh] held this diplomatic office later in the Trump administration.",
      "answer": "(United States) secretary of state (prompt on partial answers)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In September 2019 Trump tweeted the firing of this national security advisor, whose memoir of his time in the Trump administration is titled The Room Where It Happened.",
      "answer": "John (Robert) Bolton"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Trump also used a tweet to dismiss this woman from her post as secretary of homeland security in April 2019.",
      "answer": "Kirstjen [KEERST-gen] (Michele) Nielsen"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "These numbers are the zeroes of cyclotomic [syk-loh-TAH-mik] polynomials.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Give this term for complex numbers that are solutions for x in the equation x to the n equals 1, where n is an integer.",
      "answer": "(nth) roots of unity (accept primitive roots of unity)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "There are n solutions for x to the n equals 1 according to this theorem, which states that a polynomial of degree n has n complex roots.",
      "answer": "fundamental theorem of algebra"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Sometimes a root of a polynomial is repeated, which is known by this term.  For example, \" x squared minus 2 x plus 1\" has 1 as its only root, but the root \"counts\" twice.",
      "answer": "multiplicity"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The 1999 Kargil War between India and Pakistan challenged many theories of international relations.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "The war violated this German philosopher's claim that democracies would not fight each other, made in his 1795 book Perpetual Peace.",
      "answer": "Immanuel Kant"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Both India and Pakistan had franchises of this fast food chain with a golden arches symbol, violating a theory similar to Kant's proposed by Thomas Friedman.",
      "answer": "McDonald's"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The war occurred despite both India and Pakistan having nuclear weapons, violating this theory with a three-word name that the threat of shared nuclear destruction prevents conflict.",
      "answer": "mutually assured destruction (or MAD)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This character describes a dream he had about being pursued by a shrouded traveler, whom he later realizes was Death.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this narrator of a 1957 novel whose opening section depicts a trip to San Francisco.",
      "answer": "Sal Paradise (accept either underlined portion)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Sal's travels across the U.S. and Mexico, and his friendship with Dean Moriarty, are depicted in this nov el.",
      "answer": "On the Road"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "On the Road is by Jack Kerouac [\"CARE\"-uh-wak], an author from this \"generation\" of 1950s counterculture writers that also included William S. Burroughs and Allen Ginsberg.",
      "answer": "Beat Generation (or Beat movement or Beats; accept beatnik)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these films featuring Anne Hathaway:",
    "A": {
      "question": "In 2012 Hathaway starred as Fantine [fahn-teen] in a film adaptation of this musical about Jean Valjean [zhawn val-zhawn].",
      "answer": "Les Misérables [lay mee-zay-RAHB] (accept Les Miz)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "With Cate Blanchett and Sandra Bullock, Hathaway appeared in this 2018 heist movie about female criminals who steal a necklace at the Met Gala.",
      "answer": "Ocean's 8 (do not accept or prompt on answers mentioning any other number)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Hathaway starred as a con artist who tries to scam a tech billionaire in this 2019 remake of Dirty Rotten Scoundrels.",
      "answer": "The Hustle"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "These structures are composed of bundles called fascicles surrounded by an envelope known as epimysium [EP-ih-MISS-ee-um].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these structures responsible for body movement, which include the triceps [TRY-seps].",
      "answer": "skeletal muscles (accept, but do not otherwise reveal, striated muscles; do not accept or prompt on \"smooth muscle(s)\" or \"cardiac muscle(s)\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In most cases, these tough bands of fibrous [FYE-brus] tissue connect muscles to bones.",
      "answer": "tendons (prompt on \"sinew(s)\"; do not accept or prompt on \"ligament(s)\") [Ligaments connect bone to bone, while tendons connect muscle to bone.]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This term refers to the banding of skeletal muscle that occurs because of the alignment of its functional units, or sarcomeres [SAR-koh-meers].",
      "answer": "striations [stry-AY-shuns] (or striated muscle)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Although this novel's title residence has a \"dreary name,\" it becomes the beloved home of the narrator Esther Summerson.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this 1853 novel that describes a decades-long legal dispute over the Jarndyce [JARN-diss] estate.",
      "answer": "Bleak House"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Bleak House is a novel by this British author, who was paid by the installment to publish serial novels such as David Copperfield and Oliver Twist.",
      "answer": "Charles Dickens (or Charles John Huffam Dickens)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Dickens followed Bleak House with this novel set in the industrial city of Coketown, where Sissy Jupe [joop] attends a school run by the \"facts\"-obsessed Thomas Gradgrind.",
      "answer": "Hard Times(: For These Times)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Antonio de Mendoza served as the first viceroy [\"vice\"-roy] of this territory.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this administrative unit created in 1535 that included modern-day Mexico and other colonies north of Panama.",
      "answer": "Viceroyalty of New Spain (or Virreinato de Nueva España)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Toward the end of New Spain's existence, 20 of these institutions were founded in what is now California.  Junipero Serra [hoo-NEE-\"pair\"-oh \"sarah\"] established nine of these religious centers.",
      "answer": "(Spanish) missions (or misiones)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Mexico became independent when the Spanish Empire began to disintegrate in this decade.  Napoleon's brother Joseph was driven out of Spain in the previous decade.",
      "answer": "1820s (prompt on \"20s\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer these questions about the chemistry of mayonnaise:",
    "A": {
      "question": "As a stable mixture of oil and water, mayonnaise is what kind of suspension made of two immiscible [ih-MIH-sih-bul] liquids?",
      "answer": "emulsion(s) (prompt on \"colloid(s)\" or \"colloidal (suspension)\"; do not accept or prompt on \"emulsification\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Mayonnaise's stability comes from the emulsifying agent lecithin [\"LESS-uh-thin\"], an example of what double-tailed compounds that often form \"bilayers\"?",
      "answer": "phospholipids [foss-foh-LIP-idz] (prompt on \"lipid(s)\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Mayonnaise is flavored by either vinegar or lemon juice, which are what type of substance whose solutions have pHs less than 7?",
      "answer": "acid(s) (or acidic substance(s))"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This author's plays include The Rules of the Game, which one of his later works featured as a play within a play.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this 20th-century author who wrote a play in which a rehearsal for The Rules of the Game is disrupted by the arrival of the title group.",
      "answer": "Luigi Pirandello [loo-EE-jee peer-un-DEL-oh]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The fraught relationship between a Father and a Stepdaughter is re-enacted in a Pirandello play about this many \"Characters in Search of an Author.\"",
      "answer": "six (or sei; accept Six Characters in Search of an Author or Sei personaggi in cerca d'autore) [Six Characters in Search of an Author begins as actors are rehearsing Pirandello's The Rules of the Game.]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In another Pirandello play, a group of actors led by Doctor Hinkfuss perform thi s title action, which involves making up scenes and dialogue without a script.",
      "answer": "improvise (or recitare a soggetto; accept improvisation or improvising or improvised; accept Tonight We Improvise or Questa sera si recita a soggetto)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about failed attempts to assassinate U.S. presidents:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The first presidential assassination attempt was made in 1835 against this seve nth president and signer of the Indian Removal Act, who beat his assailant with a cane.",
      "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This president was targeted twice in the same month, including by \"Squeaky\" Fromme [frohm], a follower of Charles Manson.",
      "answer": "Gerald Ford (or Gerald Rudolph Ford Jr. or Leslie Lynch King Jr.)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 1981 John Hinckley Jr. shot and wounded Ronald Reagan in an attempt to impress this actress who appeared in Taxi Driver.",
      "answer": "Jodie Foster (or Alicia Christian Foster)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about organisms found near hydrothermal vents:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This term refers to organisms that thrive in conditions inhospitable to most life.  Many of these organisms live in the high-temperature environments near vents.",
      "answer": "extremophiles [\"extreme-uh-files\"] (accept thermophiles or hyperthermophiles)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A so-called \"city\" of these animals lives among vents in American Samoa.  Moray [\"MORE\"-ay] and conger [rhymes with \"longer\"] are varieties of these snake-like fish.",
      "answer": "eels (or Anguilliformes; accept Eel City)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Many extremophiles use this process of carbon fixation powered by the oxidation of inorganic compounds rather than sunlight.",
      "answer": "chemosynthesis [KEE-moh-\"synthesis\"]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "While a man inspects this object, Pip plays a tambourine.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Identify this object from a 19th-century novel that is created for a Polynesian harpooner, and to which another character clings to survive after he is cast adrift.",
      "answer": "Queequeg's coffin (or casket)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Queequeg's [KWEE-kweg's] coffin saves Ishmael following the sinking of the Pequod [PEE-kwahd], a ship commanded by this obsessive captain.",
      "answer": "Captain Ahab"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Queequeg, Ishmael, and Captain Ahab appear in this Herman Melville novel about the hunt for a white whale.",
      "answer": "Moby-Dick(; or, The Whale)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about disappearances in southeast Asia:",
    "A": {
      "question": "In April 2021 the submarine Nanggala II [nahn-\"GALA\" \"two\"] disappeared in waters north of this Indonesian island.  Beaches near its city of Denpasar [den-PAH-sar] are a major tourist destination.",
      "answer": "Bali"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Flight 370, which departed from this country's capital of Kuala Lumpur [koo-AH-lah lum-POOR], disappeared in March 2014.",
      "answer": "Malaysia (accept Malaysia Airlines Flight 370)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Many disappearances of Tamil People on this island over the past 20 years have been linked to unmarked white vans-presumably connected to this island country's Sinhalese-dominated government.",
      "answer": "Sri Lanka [shree LAHN-kuh] (or Democratic Socialist Republic of Sri Lanka or Shri Lamka Prajatantrika Samajaya di Janarajaya or Ilankai Jananayaka Choshalichak Kutiyarachu)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these baseball teams who had first-year managers in the 2018 season:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Alex Cora-who began managing this team in 2018-parted ways with this team in 2020 but rejoined as its manager in 2021 after serving a suspension for his role in the Astros sign-stealing scandal.",
      "answer": "Boston Red Sox (accept either underlined portion; prompt on \"Sox\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Dave Martinez joined this team as manager in 2018, and led it to the 2019 World Series title over the Astros.",
      "answer": "Washington Nationals (accept either underlined portion; accept Nats)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 2018 Mike Shildt [shilt] took over for Mike Matheny [muh-THEE-nee] in managing this NL team.",
      "answer": "St. Louis Cardinals (accept either underlined portion; accept Cards)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about oaks in American history:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This Quaker founder of Philadelphia negotiated the purchase of lands from Lenape [LEH-nuh-pee] natives with a treaty signed under an oak tree in Graystones Forest.",
      "answer": "William Penn"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A royal charter given to this colony in 1662 was supposedly hidden from Governor Edmund Andros inside of an old oak tree that became known as the \"Charter Oak.\"",
      "answer": "Connecticut Colony"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The extremely large Emancipation Oak is on the campus of this Virginia university.  Booker T. Washington attended this school when it was an agricultural institute.",
      "answer": "Hampton University (or Hampton Agricultural and Industrial School or Hampton Institute)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the philosophy of free will:",
    "A": {
      "question": "In contrast to determinists, believers in free will sometimes are known by this label, shared with a third party in the U.S. political system.",
      "answer": "libertarians (or libertarianism; accept Libertarian Party)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This theologian, the author of City of God, asked how free will can coexist with God's foreknowledge in his 5th-century dialogue De libero arbitrio [DAY lee-BEAR-oh ARR-bee-tree-oh].",
      "answer": "St. Augustine [aw-GUS-tin (or) AW-guh-steen] of Hippo (or Aurelius Augustinus Hipponensis; accept Saint Austin)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Free will results from an unpredictable \"swerve\" of these objects, according to Lucretius's [loo-KREE-shus's] poem On the Nature of Things.  Their name was coined by Democritus [deh-MAH-kri-tuss].",
      "answer": "atoms (or atomoi)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the Statue of Liberty:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The Statue of Liberty's interior framework was designed by this French engineer, who a lso designed an iron lattice tower in Paris.",
      "answer": "Gustave Eiffel (or Alexandre Gustave Eiffel; accept Alexandre Gustave Bönickhausen)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This French sculptor designed the statue's exterior.  He never realized his plans to design a massive lighthouse on the Suez Canal.",
      "answer": "Frédéric Auguste Bartholdi [fray-day-reek-oh-goost bar-tohl-dee]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The green exterior of the Statue of Liberty comes from this pigment created by the weathering of copper.  It can be artificially created by applying acetic acid [uh-SEE-tik acid] to bronze.",
      "answer": "verdigris [VUR-duh-grees]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This territory's indigenous Kanak people called for a boycott of a 2021 referendum due to an ongoing period of mourning for local COVID deaths.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this island territory that rejected independence in that referendum.",
      "answer": "New Caledonia (or Nouvelle-Calédonie)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "New Caledonia is a territory of this European country, whose overseas regions include Guadeloupe [gwah-duh-LOOP].",
      "answer": "France (or French Republic or République française)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Kanak independence movement advocates a \"Melanesian\" form of this political philosophy, whose \"democratic\" type is often contrasted with Marxism-Leninism.",
      "answer": "socialism (accept Melanesian socialism or democratic socialism)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these monsters from picture books:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This \"lovable, furry\" blue Muppet from Sesame Street realizes that he is the title character at the conclusion of Jon Stone's The Monster at the End of This Book.",
      "answer": "Grover (accept The Monster at the End of This Book: Starring Lovable, Furry Old Grover )"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In a book by Julia Donaldson, a mouse intimidates this monster who has \"knobbly knees,\" a \"poisonous wart,\" and \"purple prickles all over his back.\"",
      "answer": "Gruffalo [\"GRUFF\"-uh-loh] (accept The Gruffalo)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A picture book by William Steig [styg] introduced this grouchy green ogre [OH-gur], who rides a donkey to the castle of a \"ghastly\" princess.",
      "answer": "Shrek (accept Shrek!)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In January 2022 this woman surpassed Matt Amodio's [uh-MOH-dee-oh'z] 38-game winning streak.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this woman who is the first openly trans contestant to qualify for a game show's Tournament of Champions.",
      "answer": "Amy Schneider"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Schneider is one of the winningest [\"winning-est\"] contestants in the history of this show once hosted by Alex Trebek [treh-BEK].",
      "answer": "Jeopardy!"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 2021 this former actress on The Big Bang Theory began sharing Jeopardy! hosting duties with Ken Jennings.",
      "answer": "Mayim (Chaya) Bialik [\"MY\"-im bee-AH-lik]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A conflict known by this name was ended by the Good Friday Agreement in 1998.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Ulster loyalists fought republicans in Ireland in a conflict with what generic-sounding nickname?",
      "answer": "The Troubles (or Na Trioblóidí)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Irish republicans during the Troubles mostly belonged to this Christian church, while loyalists were mostly Protestants.",
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church (or Church of Rome)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Irish nationalist paramilitary group with \"Provisional\" and \"Official\" incarnations participated in the Troubles.",
      "answer": "IRA [\"I-R-A\"] (or Irish Republican Army; accept Provisional IRA or Official IRA)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "One of these gems known as La Peregrina [peh-reh-GREE-nuh] has been owned by both Mary I and actress Elizabeth Taylor.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Identify this type of gemstone that gives an alternate name for boba or bubble tea.",
      "answer": "pearl (accept pearl (milk) tea)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Pearl is the daughter of Hester Prynne [prin] in this author's novel The Scarlet Letter.",
      "answer": "Nathaniel Hawthorne (or Nathaniel Hathorne)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "After a stint at the University of Tennessee, Bruce Pearl was hired as the men's basketball coach of this other SEC school whose former athletes include Charles Barkley and Cam Newton.",
      "answer": "Auburn University"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "These geological features are formed in orogenies [oh-RAH-juh-neez].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these tall geological features found in namesake \"ranges,\" like the Himalayas.",
      "answer": "mountains (accept mountain ranges or Andes Mountains or Himalayan Mountains)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Orogenies often occur near \"zones\" named for this process, in which a tectonic plate moves beneath another plate.",
      "answer": "subduction [\"sub-DUCK-shin\"] (accept subducting or subduction zones)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Subduction zones are found at this type of plate boundary in which the plates move toward each other.",
      "answer": "convergent plate boundary"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these areas around the globe with something in common:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The headquarters of Samsung and Hyundai [hun-day] are in Seoul [\"soul\"], the capital of this East Asian country.",
      "answer": "South Korea (or Republic of Korea or ROK or Taehan-min'guk or Han'guk; prompt on \"Korea\"; do not accept or prompt on \"North Korea\" or \"Democratic People's Republic of Korea\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Juba [JOO-bah] is the capital of this African country, which broke off from its neighbor and declared independence in 2011.",
      "answer": "South Sudan (or Republic of South Sudan; do not accept or prompt on \"Sudan\" or \"Southern Sudan\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 2008 this country fought Russia over the disputed region of South Ossetia [oh-SEH-tee-uh].  This country is the northernmost of the three \"Caucasian States.\"",
      "answer": "Georgia (or Sak'art'velo)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "An unnamed giant built the walls around this domain.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this home realm of the Aesir [AA-seer], the major Norse gods.",
      "answer": "Asgard [AZ-\"guard\"] (or Asgardr)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The mysterious giant built Asgard's walls with help from Svadilfari [SVAH-dil-far-ee], one of these animals who was later seduced by a shapeshifted Loki.",
      "answer": "horses (or stallions)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The builder of the walls of Asgard asked for Freya, and these two celestial objects, known as Mani and Sol, as payment",
      "answer": "(the) Sun   (Earth's) Moon (or Luna) (accept answers in either order)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This phenomenon's speed is measured by anemometers [ANN-uh-MOM-uh-turs].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these moving air currents, which include breezes and gusts.",
      "answer": "wind(s)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The effects of wind are quantified on this scale named for an Irish rear admiral, on which a strong breeze corresponds to \"Force 6.\"",
      "answer": "Beaufort [BOH-furt] (wind force) scale"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "These systems are ranked by wind speed on a five-category scale partly named for Herbert Saffir.  Their wind speeds must exceed 74 miles per hour.",
      "answer": "hurricanes (or (tropical) cyclones; accept typhoons or hurricane-force winds; do not accept or prompt on \"tornado(es)\" or \"whirlwind(s)\") [Hurricanes are categorized on the Saffir -Simpson scale.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This man succeeded his mentor, Johnny Torrio, as head of a group known as the \"Outfit.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this gangster who ordered a 1929 \"hit\" against his longtime nemesis Bugs Moran.",
      "answer": "Al Capone [kuh-POHN] (or Alphonse (Gabriel) Capone; prompt on \"Scarface\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The 1929 strike that Capone ordered against Moran was known as a \"massacre\" named for this February 14 holiday on which the attack took place.",
      "answer": "Valentine's Day (accept Saint Valentine's Day Massacre)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Capone was never implicated in the massacre, but after being convicted of tax evasion he was jailed at this federal prison on an island in San Francisco Bay.",
      "answer": "Alcatraz Federal Penitentiary (or Alcatraz Island; prompt on \"(The) Rock\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "During this woman's trial, she claimed her actions were influenced by her ex -boyfriend Ramesh Balwani [rah-MESH bahl-WAH-nee].  For 10 p oints each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this female Silicon Valley startup founder who in January 2022 was found guilty of wire fraud and conspiracy to defraud investors.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth (Anne) Holmes"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Holmes founded this company, which lied about the capabilities of its \"Edison\" machine to conduct medical tests with only a few drops of blood.",
      "answer": "Theranos [THAIR-uh-nohss]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Theranos's fraud was exposed in a 2015 article in this newspaper, whose name refers to a road synonymous with New York's financial sector.",
      "answer": "The Wall Street Journal (or WSJ)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Opera singer Joan Sutherland had the \"coloratura\" type of this vocal range.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this highest of the four standard vocal ranges.",
      "answer": "soprano (accept lyric soprano or coloratura soprano)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A soprano clef is a stylized version of this letter, placed on the lowest line of the staff.  The alto and tenor clefs are also stylized versions of this letter.",
      "answer": "C (accept C clef(s))"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A singer whose range lies between soprano and alto is often described by placing this five-letter Italian word before \"soprano.\"  It's also placed before \"forte\" in a dynamic meaning \"medium loud.\"",
      "answer": "mezzo (accept mezzo-soprano or mezzo-forte)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about lakes in the western U.S.:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This lake, which is the largest alpine lake in North America, is between Nevada and California.",
      "answer": "Lake Tahoe"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The construction of Garrison Dam created Lake Sakakawea, which is the largest man -made lake in this state that is governed from Bismarck [BIZ-mark].",
      "answer": "North Dakota (accept ND [\"N-D\"])"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This lake in northern Utah is a remnant of the prehistoric Lake Bonneville.  The Jordan River empties into this lake.",
      "answer": "Great Salt Lake"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these parts of a cell:",
    "A": {
      "question": "These organelles help break down long-chain fatty acids.  As a byproduct, they produ ce a namesake compound with formula H2O2 [\"H two O two\"].",
      "answer": "peroxisomes [H2O2 is hydrogen peroxide]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "These organelles are the site of translation, and they are responsible for assembling proteins.",
      "answer": "ribosomes [RYE-boh-sohmz]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Ribosomes are assembled in a structure within this central organelle of the cell.  It contains the chromosomes.",
      "answer": "cell nucleus [Ribosomes are assembled in the nucleolus.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Harold Bloom called this book the first modern novel.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this novel by Miguel de Cervantes [mee-GEL day sayr-VAHN-tayss] about a man who fancies himself a knight.",
      "answer": "Don Quixote [dohn kee-HOH-tay] (or The Ingenious Gentleman Don Quixote de la Mancha or El ingenioso hidalgo don Quijote de la Mancha)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In an iconic scene, Don Quixote tilts at some of these items that he mistakes for giants.",
      "answer": "windmills"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Don Quixote rides this bony, clumsy horse which he imagines as a beautiful steed.",
      "answer": "Rocinante [roh-see-NAHN-tay]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In England, these laws were called the Coercive Acts.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Give this collective name for four harsh laws Parliament passed in 1774 to punish colonists in Massachusetts.",
      "answer": "Intolerable Acts"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Intolerable Acts were a response to this destructive 1773 protest in which cases of a certain beverage were dumped into Boston Harbor.",
      "answer": "Boston Tea Party"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Intolerable Acts led colonists to form the first of these assemblies in Philadelphia.  Its second version, convened in 1775, drafted the Declaration of Independence.",
      "answer": "(First) Continental Congress (prompt on \"Congress\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer these questions about lunar space probes:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The first man-made probe to land on the Moon, Luna 2, was launched in 1959 by what C ommunist country that also launched Sputnik?",
      "answer": "Soviet Union (or USSR or Union of Soviet Socialist Republics or Sovietsky Soyuz or S.S.S.R. or Soyuz Sovietskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The first U.S. probe to study the Moon belonged to what program, whose probes 10 and 11 escaped the solar system while carrying engraved golden plates?  It preceded the Voyager program.",
      "answer": "Pioneer program (accept Pioneer Plates)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 2019 what country's lunar probe Chang'e 4 [chang-uh \"four\"] became the first to land on the far side of the Moon?",
      "answer": "China (or People's Republic of China or PRC or Zhongguo or Zhonghua Renmin Gongheguo; do not accept or prompt on \"Republic of China\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these American authors who lived as recluses:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This author, who wrote about the teenager Holden Caulfield in The Catcher in the Rye, lived reclusively in New Hampshire from 1961 until his death in 2010.",
      "answer": "J. D. Salinger [SAL-in-jur] (or Jerome David Salinger)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This author of the poem \"Because I could not stop for Death\" lived a secluded life in Amherst, Mass achusetts.",
      "answer": "Emily (Elizabeth) Dickinson"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This postmodern author of V. and The Crying of Lot 49 has not been publicly photographed since the 1950s and lives in an undisclosed location.",
      "answer": "Thomas Pynchon [\"PINCH\"-un] (or Thomas Ruggles Pynchon Jr.)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A number of progressives suggested that this man should retire following the 2020 elections.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this liberal Supreme Court justice who announced his retirement in January 2022.",
      "answer": "Stephen (Gerald) Breyer"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Democrats hope that Breyer's retirement opens the door for a future justice who will resist efforts to overturn this landmark 1973 abortion case.",
      "answer": "Roe v. Wade"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This man, who was the last Supreme Court nominee by a Democratic president, never received a congressional hearing and currently serves in the Biden administration.",
      "answer": "Merrick (Brian) Garland"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Pencil and paper ready.  A student received a score of 85 percent on a recent test.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Assuming each question was worth the same value, and no partial credit was given, what is the minimum number of test questions that would allow a student to answer exactly 85 percent of the questions correctly?",
      "answer": "20 questions [85% = 85/100 = 17/20, which is in lowest terms.]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "If there were 40 questions on the test, how many questions did the student answer correctly?",
      "answer": "34 questions [85% of 40 = 0.85 * 40 = (0.8 * 40) + (0.05 * 40) = 32 + 2 = 34]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "What percentage score must the student receive on a second test to raise her mean average for the two tests to 92 percent?  You have 10 seconds.",
      "answer": "99% [M = (85 + x)/2 = 92, so 85 + x = 184, and x = 99]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about things named after coffee:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This Baroque composer of the Brandenburg Concertos depicted Lieschen's [LEE-shen's] addiction to the drink in his humorous Coffee Cantata.",
      "answer": "Johann Sebastian Bach (or J. S. Bach)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Sun Microsystems developed this \"write once, run anywhere\" programming language whose logo is a coffee cup, and whose name is a nickname for coffee.",
      "answer": "Java"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Caffeine, which is named for being first isolated from coffee, works by blocking adenosine from accumulating in these gaps between neurons, across which neurons send signals.",
      "answer": "synapses"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about logical arguments:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This term refers to the statements in the body of an argument from which the argument's conclusions are drawn.",
      "answer": "premises"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This kind of argument defined by Aristotle [\"AIR\"-ih-stah-tul] deduces a conclusion from two premises.  \"All men are mortal, John is a man, therefore John is mortal\" is one of these arguments.",
      "answer": "syllogisms [SIH-luh-JIZMS] (or syllogistic argument)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The conclusion of a syllogism only has this property if the premises do.  This property is the opposite of falsehood.",
      "answer": "truth (or true)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these shapes related to circles:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Revolving a circle about an axis in the same plane and not through the circle's center produces this donut -like 3D shape.",
      "answer": "torus(es) (accept tori; accept toroidal surface(s))"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This hollow round shape is the 3D equivalent of a circle.",
      "answer": "sphere(s) (do not accept or prompt on \"ball\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This is the name for the ring-like region between two concentric circles.",
      "answer": "annulus [AN-yoo-luss] (accept annuli)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 1903 this country declared independence from Colombia.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Central American country that immediately authorized the building of a namesake U.S. -controlled canal.",
      "answer": "Panama (or Republic of Panama or República de Panamá)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This Republican president backed Panamanian secession from Colombia followin g Colombia's failure to ratify a canal treaty.",
      "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt (or Teddy Roosevelt or TR; prompt on \"Roosevelt\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This president signed a treaty with Panama's leader Omar Torrijos [toh-REE-hohss] to transfer control of the canal from the U.S.  The Mariel [mah-ree-EL] Boatlift from Cuba began when he was president.",
      "answer": "Jimmy Carter (or James Earl Carter Jr; accept Torrijos-Carter Treaty or Torrijos-Carter Treaties)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A British organization for members of this field publishes a journal called Ibis [\"EYE\"-biss].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this branch of zoology that studies birds.",
      "answer": "ornithology [OR-nih-THAH-luh-jee] (accept ornithologists)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Before 2021 a journal now called Ornithology was named after this flightless bird that went extinct in the 19th century.  It lived in coastal areas of the North Atlantic, including Canada and Iceland.",
      "answer": "great auk [awk] (or Pinguinus impennis; accept The Auk(: Ornithological Advances))"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A sister journal, also renamed Ornithological [OR-nih-thuh-\"logical\"] Applications in 2021, was previously named for this type of vulture.  This bird's \"California\" species has the largest wingspan of any bird in North Amer ica.",
      "answer": "condor (accept California condor; accept The Condor(: Ornithological Applications))"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Many authors have voiced a debt of gratitude to Edgar Allan Poe.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "This creator of Sherlock Holmes said that Poe's character C. Auguste Dupin [\"C\" oh-GOOST doo-pan] \"breathed life\" into detective fiction.",
      "answer": "Arthur (Ignatius) Conan Doyle"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "An acrostic [uh-\"CROSS\"-tik] poem dedicated to Poe is among the rare poems by this horror author, who is better known for creating the evil deity Cthulhu [kuh-THOO-loo].",
      "answer": "H. P. Lovecraft (or Howard Phillips Lovecraft)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This author of the novel It claims that Poe \"wasn't just a mystery-suspense writer.  He was the first.\"",
      "answer": "Stephen (Edwin) King"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the delta of the Danube River:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Most of the Danube delta lies in this Eastern European country, which contains the historical regions of Moldavia [mohl-DAY-vee-uh] and Wallachia [wah-LAY-kee-uh].",
      "answer": "Romania"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Danube River empties into this sea north of Turkey.",
      "answer": "Black Sea"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Danube's delta is the second-largest in Europe; the largest river delta is that of this river, the longest in Europe, which empties into the Caspian Sea.",
      "answer": "Volga River"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the various ways in which french fries are prepared:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Gravy and cheese curds are poured over french fries in this dish, which is especially popular in Canada.",
      "answer": "poutine [POO-teen]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In the Netherlands, fries are most commonly dipped in this condiment made from oil and egg yolks.",
      "answer": "mayonnaise"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 2016 McDonald's restaurants in Japan began selling fries coated with this ingredient, which forms the outer layer of Pocky.",
      "answer": "chocolate"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This person was known as the \"Maid of Orléans\" [orr-lee-OWN].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this person canonized in 1920, centuries after being burned at the stake by a pro -English bishop in 1431.",
      "answer": "(Saint) Joan of Arc (or Jeanne d'Arc; prompt on \"Joan\" or \"Jeanne\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Joan of Arc's birthplace at Domrémy [dohm-ray-MEE] is now located in this European country.",
      "answer": "France (or French Republic or République française)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Joan assisted a French king with this name in reaching his coronation ceremony.  The tenth French king with this name was overthrown in the July Revolution.",
      "answer": "Charles (accept Charles VII [\"the seventh\"] or Charles X [\"the tenth\"] or Charles-Philippe)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In the Gospel of John, this figure says \"unless you see signs and wonders, you will not believe.\"  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "What subject of the Gospels performs miracles including exorcisms, feeding a multitude, and walking on water?",
      "answer": "Jesus (the) Christ (or Jesus of Nazareth or Yesua or Yeshua or Iesous; accept any underlined portion)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Jesus miraculously turns water into wine while visiting this kind of celebration at Cana [KAY-nuh].",
      "answer": "wedding (accept marriage ceremony; accept wedding feast or marriage feast; prompt on \"feast\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Jesus tells Peter that he will find a coin for paying the tax of the temple at Capernaum [kuh-PUR-nay-um] in the mouth of one of these animals.  Peter's previous profession involved capturing these animals.",
      "answer": "fish"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The name of these features comes from a Norse word for \"to gush.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these geologic features that intermittently erupt superheated wate r and steam.",
      "answer": "geysers [\"GUY\"-zurs]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A geyser is a dramatic example of this geologic feature, which is a point where groundwater from an aquifer flows directly out on the surface.",
      "answer": "spring(s) (accept hot springs)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Geyserite [\"geyser\"-ite], which forms in the pipes of geysers, is mostly made up of this mineral.  This material common in sand is often made into moisture-reducing, gel-like beads.",
      "answer": "silica (accept silicon dioxide; prompt on \"quartz\" or \"SiO2\"; do not accept or prompt on \"silicate(s)\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "As of April 2022, there are less than 40 inmates at this location.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this detention camp created in 2002 during the \"War on Terror.\"  Located in the Caribbean, this place remains open despite calls for the president to shut it down.",
      "answer": "Guantánamo [gwahn-TAH-nah-moh] Bay detention camp (accept Gitmo; accept Camp Delta)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Guantánamo Bay camp is on this island, which an American-backed force attacked in the Bay of Pigs invasion.",
      "answer": "Cuba (or Republic of Cuba or República de Cuba)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This other prison was central to an Iraq War scandal in which U.S. soldiers were photographed mocking and torturing naked prisoners.",
      "answer": "Abu Ghraib [AH-boo GRAYB]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these countries with unusual flags:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Mount Everest is on the border of China and this country, which features the world 's only non-quadrilateral [kwahd-ruh-LAT-uh-rul] flag.",
      "answer": "Nepal (or Federal Democratic Republic of Nepal or Sanghiya Loktantrik Ganatantra Nepal)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "An AK-47 is featured on the flag of this country, which shares its name with the channel separating Madagascar from mainland Africa.",
      "answer": "Mozambique [moh-zam-BEEK] (or Republic of Mozambique or República de Moçambique; accept Mozambique Channel)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 2009 this country adopted a dual flag called the Wiphala [wih-PUH-luh] to represent its indigenous people.  The colonial Spanish silver mines at Potosí [poh-toh-\"SEE\"] were in what is now this country.",
      "answer": "Bolivia (or Plurinational State of Bolivia or Estado Plurinacional de Bolivia)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2019 a brick thrown by protestors killed janitor Luo Changqing [loo-OH chang-CHING] in this city.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this \"special administrative region\" that is currently led by Carrie Lam, who in April 2022 announced she would not seek another term.",
      "answer": "Hong Kong (or Hong Kong Special Administrative Region or Xianggang Tebie Xingzhengqu)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The protests were sparked by a bill that would have added China to the list of countries with which Hong Kong could engage in this legal process.",
      "answer": "extradition (accept extradite or extraditing; do not accept or prompt on \"deportation\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Despite the protests, this president of China ensured the passage of the Hong Kong National Security Law in June 2020.",
      "answer": "Xi Jinping [shee jin-peeng] (or Xí Jìnpíng; do not accept or prompt on \"Jinping\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This illness is sometimes colloquially called \"hydrophobia.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this disease transmitted by the bite of an infected mammal.",
      "answer": "rabies"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In the 1800s this French scientist developed the first effective human vaccine for rabies with Émile Roux [ay-meel ROO].  He also advanced the germ theory of disease.",
      "answer": "Louis Pasteur [LOO-ee pass-TUR]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Pasteur and Roux also developed the first vaccine for this bacterial infection, whose name refers to the coal -black lesions it forms on the skin.  Sheep are particularly susceptible to this disease.",
      "answer": "anthrax (accept Bacillus anthracis)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2021 a book named for this street was withdrawn from publication by the author's estate, due to \"hurtful\"  imagery.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "In a 1937 children's book, Marco imagines an increasingly fantastical procession along what title street?",
      "answer": "Mulberry Street (accept And to Think That I Saw It on Mulberry Street)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "And to Think That I Saw It on Mulberry Street was the first children's book by this writer and illustrator, who later wrote The Cat in the Hat.",
      "answer": "Dr. Seuss [sooss or soyss] (or Theodor Seuss Geisel)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The second children's book by Dr. Seuss was named for this boy, whose \"500 Hats\" incur the wrath of King Derwin.",
      "answer": "Bartholomew Cubbins (accept either underlined portion; accept The 500 Hats of Bartholomew Cubbins)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This religious movement began in the early 1900s with the Azusa [ah-ZOO-suh] Street Revival.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "The fastest-growing religious movement in the world is what evangelical Protestant movement whose practices include speaking in tongues?",
      "answer": "Pentecostalism (accept (classical) Pentecostal movement or Pentecostals)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Azusa Street Revival took place in this most populous city in Southern Cali fornia.",
      "answer": "Los Angeles, California (or L.)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Pentecostalism arose from the teachings of this man and his brother Charles, who were the British co -founders of the Methodist church.",
      "answer": "John Wesley"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The wheel on the center of the Indian flag symbolizes this concept.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Hindu concept which refers to living in proper accord with the cosmic order.",
      "answer": "dharma [DAR-muh]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Dharma is also one of the Three Jewels of this Indian religion founded by Siddhartha Gautama.",
      "answer": "Buddhism (accept Buddhist religion; accept branches such as Mahayana or Theravada Buddhism)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "One of the earliest references to dharma occurs in this oldest of the Vedas [vay-duz], which begins with the Gayatri [\"GUY-uh-tree\"] mantra.",
      "answer": "Rigveda [RIG VAY-duh]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This epoch's name comes from Greek words meaning \"whole\" and \"new.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this geological epoch that followed the Pleistocene [\"PLY\"-stuh-\"seen\"] and which most scientists reckon we are still currently in.",
      "answer": "Holocene [HAH-luh-seen] Epoch"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "\"Holocene\" is a song by this indie folk band whose debut album is called  For Emma, Forever Ago.  This band fronted by Justin Vernon is featured on Taylor Swift's song \"Exile.\"",
      "answer": "Bon Iver [bohn ee-VAIR]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The later part of the Holocene is sometimes called the Anthropocene [ANN-thruh-puh-SEEN] due to the impact of this species on the world's ecosystems.",
      "answer": "modern humans (or Homo sapiens)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This composer's dissatisfaction with the helicon [HEL-ih-\"con\"] led to the creation of his namesake variant of the tuba.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this composer of works named after The Washington Post and the Marine Corps motto \"Semper Fidelis\" [SEM-pur fih-DEH-liss].",
      "answer": "John Philip Sousa (prompt on \"sousaphone\" by asking \"Who's the composer?\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Sousa was dubbed the \"king\" of this genre often performed by military bands.",
      "answer": "march(es) (accept March King)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Sousa march, originally intended for his operetta [ahp-uh-RET-uh] The Devil's Deputy, was renamed after a U.S. landmark.  It was later used as the theme tune for Monty Python's Flying Circus.",
      "answer": "Liberty Bell March"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The gamma function shifts and extends this function to complex numbers.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this function that, for a positive integer n, is defined as \"n, times n minus 1, times n minus 2, and so on down to 1.\"",
      "answer": "(n) factorial function"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The factorial function is denoted by this punctuation mark.",
      "answer": "exclamation point or exclamation mark (accept bang)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This is the only value that is the result of the factorial function for two different numbers.",
      "answer": "1 [0! = 1! = 1]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the Battle of Actium [AK-tee-um]:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This future Roman emperor's fleet won the battle.",
      "answer": "Augustus Caesar (or Caesar Augustus or Octavian or Gaius Octavius or Gaius Julius Caesar Octavianus; do not accept or prompt on \"(Julius) Caesar\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "At Actium, Augustus's forces defeated his former ally Mark Antony, who was supported by this Egyptian queen.",
      "answer": "Cleopatra (VII Philopator)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "While Octavian and Mark Antony were allies, they joined with Lepidus [LEP-ih-duss] to form this group of rulers.",
      "answer": "Second Triumvirate [\"try\"-UM-vih-rut] (prompt on \"triumvirate\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This writer criticized \"meaningless words\" in his essay Politics and the English Language.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this author who invented the word \"doubleplusgood\" [\"double-plus-good\"] for a novel set in the totalitarian [toh-tal-ih-TAIR-ee-un] state of Oceania [oh-shee-AY-nee-uh].",
      "answer": "George Orwell (or Eric Arthur Blair)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Oceania is the setting of this Orwell novel, which also introduced the words \"doublethink\" [\"double-think\"] and \"unperson\" [\"un-person\"].  This novel is named for a year.",
      "answer": "Nineteen Eighty-Four (or 1984)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In Nineteen Eighty-Four, \"doubleplusgood\" is an example of this restricted form of English, which the government imposes so dissent will become \"literally unthinkable.\"",
      "answer": "Newspeak [\"new-speak\"]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about H II [\"H two\"] regions:",
    "A": {
      "question": "They are examples of the \"emission\" type of these large clouds of gas found in galaxies.  Their name comes from the Latin for cloud.",
      "answer": "nebulas or nebulae (accept emission nebulas or nebulae)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The phrase \"H II\" indicates that H II regions contain hydrogen in this state.  It typically requires 13.6 eV [\"E-V\"] of energy to shift an atom of hydrogen to this state.",
      "answer": "ionized (accept answers indicating that the hydrogen is ionized or has lost an electron; accept H+; prompt on answers indicating \"(the hydrogen is electrically) charge(d)\"; do not accept or prompt on \"excited\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "H II regions are often found where these objects have recently formed.  They include red dwarfs and blue supergiants.",
      "answer": "stars"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 1982 chemist Leo Paquette synthesized a compound with formula C20H20 [\"C twenty H twenty\"] whose carbon atoms form the vertices of one of these solids.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Platonic solid that has twelve faces.",
      "answer": "(regular) dodecahedron [doh-DEK-uh-HEE-drun] [C20H20 is called dodecahedrane.]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A large dodecahedron appears in Reptiles, a lithograph depicting tessellation [teh-suh-LAY-shun] by this Dutch artist.  His print Relativity depicts unusually arranged doors and staircases.",
      "answer": "M."
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Escher [EH-shur] (or Maurits Cornelis Escher)   A character named the Dodecahedron leads the protagonists to the court of the Mathemagician in Digitopolis in this 1961 novel.",
      "answer": "The Phantom Tollbooth [by Norton Juster]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This man was known as the \"Hero of the Two Worlds\" for his roles in both the French Revolution and t he American Revolution.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this French marquis [mar-KEE], who received a serious leg wound at the Battle of Brandywine.",
      "answer": "Marquis de Lafayette [lah-\"fie\"-ET] (or Marie-Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Lafayette and George Washington forced the surrender of Charles Cornwallis at this final major engagement of the American Revolutionary War.",
      "answer": "Battle of Yorktown (or Siege of Yorktown)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The first joint operation between American and French forces was an indecisive siege of Newport, an important port in this New England state.",
      "answer": "Rhode Island (accept RI [\"R-I\"]; accept Battle of Rhode Island)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Pencil and paper ready.  For 10 points each -answer these questions about an urn holding 7 purple marbles, [pause] 8 blue marbles, [pause] and 1 white marble:",
    "A": {
      "question": "If a single marble is randomly drawn, what is the probability that it is blue?",
      "answer": "1/2 or 50% or 0.50 or 1 in 2 [There are 7 + 8 + 1 = 16 total marbles, of which 8 are blue; 8/16 = 1/2.]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "How many white marbles need to be added to raise the probability of drawing a white marble to one-fourth, or 25 percent?  You have 10 seconds.",
      "answer": "4 white marbles [There is currently 1 white marble out of 16.  If w is the number of white marbles added, (1 + w)/(16 + w) = 1/4, so 4 + 4w = 16 + w, so 3w = 12, and w = 4.]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "What minimum number of purple marbles must be added to raise the probability of drawing a purple marble to a value strictly greater than the probability of drawing a blue marble?",
      "answer": "2 purple marbles [This requires having more purple marbles than blue marbles; adding 1 purple would make their count equal (8 each), but adding 2 would yield a greater number of purple marbles (9 versus 8).]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This representation of quantum mechanics splits a Hamiltonian into a free part that is solvable and a perturbation part that contains complex system dynamics.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this representation that unifies the Heisenberg [\"HIGH\"-zin-bairg] and Schrödinger [SHRAY-ding-ur] pictures.",
      "answer": "interaction picture (or Dirac picture)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In the interaction picture, these things and state vectors are both time-dependent.  These things must be Hermitian [\"her-mission\"] so that their associated observables have real values.",
      "answer": "operators"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The interaction picture is used in derivations of this physicist's \"golden rule.\"   Spin one-half particles such as electrons are named for this physicist.",
      "answer": "Enrico Fermi [\"FAIR-me\"] (accept Fermi's golden rule)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about Byzantine emperors who returned to the throne after being deposed:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This Byzantine emperor, the last from the Heraclian [huh-\"RACK\"-lee-un] dynasty, was known as \"the slit-nosed\" because his nose was amputated when he was deposed and exiled to Crimea.",
      "answer": "Justinian II (or Ioustinianos II; accept Justinian Rhinotmetos or Justinian Rhinotmetus; prompt on \"Justinian (the Slit-Nosed)\" or \"Rhinontmetos\" or \"Rhinotmetus\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Fourth Crusade returned to the throne this emperor from the A ngelos dynasty, who had been deposed and blinded by his brother Alexios III.",
      "answer": "Isaac II Angelos (or Isaakios II prompt on \"Isaac (Komnenos Angelos)\" or \"Isaakios (Komnenos Angelos)\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Isaurian emperor Zeno, who was briefly deposed by Basiliscus, ruled during the deposition of this last Western Roman Emperor, who himself was deposed by the barbarian general Odoacer [OH-doh-\"ACE\"-ur].",
      "answer": "Romulus Augustus (or Romulus Augustulus; prompt on \"Romulus\" or \"Augustulus\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these literary detectives associated with Oxford:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This creation of Dorothy Sayers is an aristocratic detective who help s his future wife, Harriet Vane, root out the author of poison pen letters to Oxford dons in Gaudy Night.",
      "answer": "Lord Peter (Death Bredon) Wimsey (accept either underlined name; accept 17th Duke of Denver)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Ronald Knox argued that references in \"The Adventure of the Missing Three -Quarter\" and other stories made it clear that this detective, who first appeared in A Study in Scarlet, attended Oxford.",
      "answer": "Sherlock Holmes (accept either underlined portion)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "After losing a scholarship to Oxford, this creation of Colin Dexter joined the Thames [temz] Valley Police; he is notable for his interests in crosswords, opera, and classic cars.",
      "answer": "Inspector Endeavour Morse (accept either underlined name)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Pliny [PLY-nee] the Elder records this sculptor's claim that, while his predecessors \"had made men as they really are,\" this man \"made them as they appeared to be.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "What sculptor's work likely survives only in copies, most notably a marble after his The Scraper pulled from a basement in Trastevere [trah-STEV-uh-ray] in 1849?",
      "answer": "Lysippos (or Lysippus)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Lysippos differed from the earlier master Polykleitos [pahl-ee-KLYE-tuss] by making the head one-eighth rather than one-seventh of the body; such ancient systems of human proportions are known by this term, from the Greek for \"standard.\"",
      "answer": "canon(s) of (body) proportions (or aesthetic canon(s))"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Lysippos was the court sculptor for this ancient conqueror, who is shown on a sarcophagus excavated from Sidon [SYE-dahn] fighting the Persians at the Battle of Issus.",
      "answer": "Alexander the Great (or Alexander III of Macedon or Aléxandros ho Mégas; prompt on \"Alexander\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This author died of tuberculosis in 1924, leaving his novel about K.'s struggles with a shadowy bureaucracy unfinished.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this author of The Trial and The Castle.",
      "answer": "Franz Kafka"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Though Kafka left instructions that his unfinished works were to be burned, this man, Kafka's literary executor, published them posthumously instead.",
      "answer": "Max Brod [broht]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "While visiting Brod, Kafka met this woman, who later became his fiancée.  A 1967 book collects some of Kafka's letters to this woman, who is the dedicatee of his story \"The Judgment.\"",
      "answer": "Felice Bauer (accept either underlined portion; prompt on \"F.\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This book refers to Robert McNamara [MAK-nuh-mair-uh] as the \"can-do man\" in the \"can-do era.\"  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this 1972 David Halberstam book that profiles a group of young advisors in the Defense Department who crafted flawed Vietnam War policies.",
      "answer": "The Best and the Brightest"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "David Halberstam's The Best and the Brightest profiles the \"Whiz Kids\" who came to Washington with this Democratic president in 1961.",
      "answer": "John F(itzgerald) Kennedy (or JFK)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Many of the Defense Department's \"Whiz Kids\" came from this nonprofit think tank, a corporation founded by the Douglas Aircraft Company in 1948.",
      "answer": "RAND Corporation (prompt on \"Research and Development (Corporation)\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about video games in which players must take unusual physical actions to progress:",
    "A": {
      "question": "In a Sega Genesis game starring this superhero team, characters such as Wolverine, Cyclops, a nd Nightcrawler must \"reset\" a computer by pressing the console's actual reset button.",
      "answer": "X-Men"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Phantom Hourglass, a 2007 handheld entry in this series, required players to physically close and open the DS to copy a map.",
      "answer": "The Legend of Zelda (accept The Legend of Zelda: Phantom Hourglass)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This NES adventure game, which stars the yo-yo-wielding Mike Jones, requires players to reveal a code by physically dipping a paper letter included with the game in water.",
      "answer": "StarTropics"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This series illustrates the emergence of modern multinationals using the examples of the Dutch conglomerate Philips and the fictional \"UGE\" [\"U-G-E\"].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Identify this TV series.  Margaret Thatcher personally invited Milton Friedman to England to debate with Nicholas Kaldor after decrying this series as \"biased.\"",
      "answer": "The Age of Uncertainty"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The BBC styled The Age of Uncertainty as the \"personal view\" of its presenter, this liberal economist who wrote The Affluent Society.",
      "answer": "John Kenneth Galbraith [gahl-BRAYTH] (or Ken Galbraith)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 1980 PBS aired this series, Friedman's pro-market rebuttal to The Age of Uncertainty, which was accompanied by a book of the same title co-written by Rose Friedman.",
      "answer": "Free to Choose(: A Personal Statement)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This solvent has been considered for the synthesis of MOFs [\"moffs\"] due to its green properties and adjustable solvent power.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this solvent, a supercritical fluid used in many extraction methods, such as the decaffeination of coffee.",
      "answer": "supercritical carbon dioxide (or sCO2 or supercritical CO2)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Supercritical carbon dioxide has applications in these processes for washing clothing without water, which normally use the solvent tetrachloroethylene [teh-truh-klor-oh-EH-thuh-leen], or \"perc.\"",
      "answer": "dry cleaning"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Other candidates for green solvents include these substances, which are often based on EMIM [\"E-M-I-M\"].  Unlike deep eutectic solvents, the components of these substances are exclusively discrete.",
      "answer": "ionic liquids (or ILs; prompt on \"ionic solvents\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A sonnet dedicated to this poet begins \"we laid him in a cool and shadowed grove / one evening in the dreamy scent of thyme.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this poet who himself wrote a sonnet beginning \"if I should die, thin k only this of me: / that there's some corner of a foreign field / that is forever England.\"",
      "answer": "Rupert (Chawner) Brooke"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This World War II-era poet wrote \"Sonnet to Rupert Brooke\" as well as the sonnet \"High Flight,\" which begins \"oh! I have slipped the surly bonds of Earth.\"",
      "answer": "John Gillespie Magee (Jr.)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Brooke was called \"the handsomest young man in England\" by this poet of \"An Irish Airman Foresees His Death\" and \"Easter, 1916.\"",
      "answer": "William Butler Yeats [rhymes with \"gates\"]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about statuses of near-citizenship:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Aristotle was among the prominent members of Athenian society who held this status as a long-term foreign resident of Athens who was subject to many of the burdens, but few of the privileges, of citizenship.",
      "answer": "metic(s) (or metoikos)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Civitas sine suffragio [SIH-vee-tas SEE-nah soo-FRAH-jee-oh], or \"citizenship without the vote,\" was a category in this republic, in which proposed citizenship reform helped lead to the downfall of Gaius Gracchus.",
      "answer": "Roman Republic (or Rome or Res publica Romana)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Between the World Wars, stateless persons could travel and be recognized as refugees with passports named for this Norwegian explorer.",
      "answer": "Fridtjof Nansen (or Fridtjof Wedel-Jarlsberg Nansen; accept Nansen passport(s))"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the process known as \"Megxit\":",
    "A": {
      "question": "\"Megxit\" refers to this man and his wife Meghan Markle opting to withdraw from the British royal family in 2020.",
      "answer": "Prince Harry (or Harry, Duke of Sussex)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The term \"Megxit,\" a reference to \"Brexit,\" was coined by this tabloid newspaper, which launched a Sunday edition in 2012 after the fallout from the News of the World phone hacking scandal.",
      "answer": "The Sun (accept The Sun on Sunday)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In October 2020 Harry and Meghan founded this non-profit organization based in Beverly Hills to replace the now-defunct Sussex Royal Foundation.",
      "answer": "Archewell [ARCH-well]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Actor Steve Martin, who plays this instrument, created an annual prize for players of it, whose past recipients include Danny Barnes and Rhiannon Giddens.  For 10 points eac h-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this circular-bodied string instrument used in bluegrass music.",
      "answer": "banjo(s)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The prize's 2019 winner, Victor Furtado [fur-TAH-doh], plays this rhythmic banjo style that, unlike the Scruggs and other styles, relies primarily on downpicking.",
      "answer": "clawhammer banjo (accept framming or frailing or banging or thrashing or thumb-cocking)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "When Furtado was twelve, he was invited to perform with Mike Snider at this weekly country music concert based in Nashville.",
      "answer": "Grand Ole Opry (prompt on \"Opry\") [Furtado was 19 when he won the prize.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about 2018 Broadway revivals centered on gay characters:",
    "A": {
      "question": "In 2018 a revival-record eleven Tony nominations were received by what two-part \"Gay Fantasia on National Themes\" by Tony Kushner?",
      "answer": "Angels in America(: A Gay Fantasia on National Themes)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "An all-gay cast appeared in a revival of a pioneering Mart Crowley play titled for the \"boys\" in one of these groups.  This kind of group is mentioned in the title of a history of the AIDS crisis by Randy Shilts.",
      "answer": "bands (accept The Boys in the Band or And the Band Played On)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "For a 2018 revival, Harvey Fierstein [\"fire\"-steen] created an updated version of this Tony-winning set of plays, which premiered in 1982.",
      "answer": "Torch Song Trilogy"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This relationship can be measured with Spearman's rho.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this relationship that, according to an adage, does not imply causation.",
      "answer": "correlation (accept linear correlation or rank correlation or correlation does not imply causation)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Spearman's rho is a statistic described by this word because no assumptions are made about the joint distribution of the two variables.  Statistical tests described by this thirteen -letter word are also called distribution free tests.",
      "answer": "nonparametric (accept nonparametric statistic or nonparametric tests)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Unlike Pearson's r, Spearman's rho is able to discriminate between the data sets in this English statistician's \"quartet\" designed to demonstrate the limitations of summary statistics.",
      "answer": "Frank Anscombe (or Francis John Anscombe)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The Tuva Republic lies at the border between these two countries.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these two countries.  The Selenga River originates in one of them before flowing north into Lake Baikal in the other.",
      "answer": "Russia (or Russian Federation or Rossiya or Rossiyskaya Federatsiya)   Mongolia (or Mongol Uls)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Tuva's cultural touchstones include khöömei [koo-may], a technique of this type of singing.  Its varieties include the whistle-like sygyt [suh-guht] and the ultra-deep kargyraa [kar-guh-rah].",
      "answer": "throat singing (accept overtone singing or chanting or harmonic singing)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "An international festival of throat singing is held every other year in this capital of Tuva.",
      "answer": "Kyzyl [KIZ-ul] (or Kizil)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This monarch shaved and broke a beard vow, leading Louise of Savoy to observe that kingly bonhomie [bon-oh-mee] lay \"not in the beards but in the hearts.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "According to Robert III de la Marck [roh-bair \"the third\" deh la \"mark\"], what king became upset after losing a wrestling match at a sumptuous 1520 diplomatic summit?",
      "answer": "Henry VIII [\"the eighth\"] of England (prompt on \"Henry\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The beard kerfuffle at the Field of the Cloth of Gold was resolved when Thomas Boleyn blamed th e shaving on this woman, Henry's first wife, who was from Aragon.",
      "answer": "Catherine of Aragon (or Catalina de Aragón)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Catherine entreated Henry to spurn an alliance with Francis in favor of Charles V [\"the fifth\"], who had been elected Holy Roman Emperor over both men on the strength of bribes and his sister's marriage to this king of Bohemia.",
      "answer": "Louis II (of Hungary) (accept Ludvik II or Ludovik II or Lajos II; prompt on \"Louis\" or \"Lud(o)vik\" or \"Lajos\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the early years of the Associated Press Athlete of the Year award:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The first male winner was Pepper Martin, who like Dizzy Dean was one of the players Branch Rickey assembled to play for this National League franchise's 1930s \"Gashouse Gang\" teams.",
      "answer": "St. Louis Cardinals (accept either underlined portion; accept Cards)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Both the first male and female repeat winners, Don Budge and Alice Marble, were selected for their accomplishments in this sport, also played by later winners Chris Evert [EV-urt] and Serena Williams.",
      "answer": "tennis (accept tennis players)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The first male golfer to win the award was this Italian-American.  His win at the 1935 Masters made him the first player to win a career grand slam consisting of all four modern professional majors.",
      "answer": "Gene Sarazen [SAIR-uh-zen] (or Eugenio Saraceni)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Jonathan Schaffer's paper \"On What Grounds What\" notes that people who make claims about grounding often \"retreat to\" claims about this relation.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "According to the Stanford Encyclopedia, property A has what relation to property B if \"there cannot be an A difference without a B difference\"?",
      "answer": "supervenience [\"super\"-VEEN-ee-entz] (accept strong or weak supervenience; accept answers indicating forms of the word supervene such as supervening)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Dispute exists about whether supervenience avoids or entails this process, which explains complex phenomena, such as consciousness, in terms of \"lower level\" phenomena, such as physical activity in the brain.",
      "answer": "reduction (accept reducing or reductionism or reductionist(s); accept strong or weak reductionism)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "David Lewis named a type of supervenience after this Scottish author of An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding.",
      "answer": "David Hume (or David Home; accept Humean supervenience)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "These objects correspond to terminals in a programming language's context -free grammar.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these objects that a scanner or lexer [\"lex-er\"] generates by matching regular expressions to strings in an input file.",
      "answer": "tokens (or lexemes)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "These programs build abstract syntax trees, or ASTs, from input tokens.  These subprograms of compilers are classified by whether they build the AST from the top-down or from the bottom-up.",
      "answer": "parsers"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Source code is compiled to bytecode, which is then interpreted in the standard C implementation of this programming language whose name derives from a British comedy group.",
      "answer": "Python (accept CPython; do not accept or prompt on \"Monty Python\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Tertullian suggested that this term could refer to some form of ear or head pain.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Give the term from the King James Bible used to name an ailment in a New Testament book.  After asking God to remove this thing, the man suffering from it is told \"my grace is sufficient for thee.\"",
      "answer": "thorn in the flesh (or Paul's thorn)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Paul describes his thorn in his second epistle to these people.  Paul's first epistle to them says that \"love is patient, love is kind; it does not envy.\"",
      "answer": "Corinthians (accept First Corinthians or Second Corinthians or First Epistle to the Corinthians or Second Epistle to the Corinthians)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Paul's thorn may have been a lingering form of this condition, which Paul briefly suffers in Acts of the Apostles.  Jesus heals Bartimaeus of this condition in Jericho.",
      "answer": "blindness"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "When Paris's Palais Garnier [pah-lay garn-YAY] held its inaugural concert in 1875, Gabrielle Krauss played the title character of an opera by this composer.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this composer whose 1835 grand opera La Juive [lah zhweev] is known in English as The Jewess.",
      "answer": "Fromental Halévy [hah-lay-VEE] (or Jacques-François-Fromental-Élie Halévy)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This tenor performer's final role was as Eléazar [el-ee-ah-sar] in Halévy's La Juive.  His 1903 RCA Victor recording of the aria \"Vesti la giubba\" was the first-ever record to sell a million copies.",
      "answer": "Enrico Caruso"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Halévy's nephew Ludovic [loo-doh-veek] was the librettist for this composer's comic operas La Belle Hélène [lah bel ay-LEN] and Orpheus in the Underworld.",
      "answer": "Jacques Offenbach (or Jacob Offenbach)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the career of Illinois senator Paul Douglas:",
    "A": {
      "question": "In the 1930s Douglas lobbied for the \"Chicago plan\" to severely restrict the multiplying activities of these institutions, including banning their \"fractional reserve\" structure.",
      "answer": "(lending) banks (accept savings and loans or savings banks)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Interpretations differ on why Douglas presented a pitcher of orange juice during this 1957 event, which began on August 28 and lasted just over 24 hours.",
      "answer": "Strom Thurmond's filibuster of the Civil Rights Act of 1957 (prompt on \"filibuster\"; accept James Strom Thurmond Sr. in place of \"Strom Thurmond\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "While a professor of economics at Amherst in 1928, Douglas co-authored an article with this fellow economist on the production of output by two inputs, such as capital and labor.",
      "answer": "Charles (Wiggins) Cobb"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The experience of this real-life figure was the inspiration for the play The Man in the Glass Booth.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this real-life person who, while handcuffed, is shaved by captor Peter Malkin in a 2018 film.",
      "answer": "Adolf Eichmann [\"IKE\"-mun]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Eichmann's trial in Jerusalem inspired philosopher Hannah Arendt to describe the \"banality\" of this concept, which she saw within Eichmann.",
      "answer": "evil (accept banality of evil)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Ward Churchill controversially used the phrase \"little Eichmanns\" to describe the people working in this New York complex during the 9/11 attacks.",
      "answer": "World Trade Center (or WTC; accept Twin Towers)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the ancient sculptor Lysippos [\"lie\"-SIP-ohss]:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Lysippos made his sculptural heads one-eighth-rather than one-seventh-of the body.  Such ancient systems of human proportions are known by this term, from the Greek for \"sta ndard.\"",
      "answer": "canon(s) of (body) proportions (or aesthetic canon(s))"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Lysippos was the court sculptor for this ancient conqueror, who is shown on a sarcophagus [sar-KAH-fuh-gus] excavated from Sidon [\"SIDE\"-un] fighting the Persians at the Battle of Issus [IH-suss].",
      "answer": "Alexander the Great (or Alexander III of Macedon or Aléxandros ho Mégas; prompt on \"Alexander\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Lysippos is the attributed original sculptor of a work named for Atalante and depicting this Greek god, but without his common attribute of the caduceus [kuh-DOO-see-uss].",
      "answer": "Hermes (accept Hermes of Atalante or Atalante Hermes; do not accept or prompt on \"Mercury\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Today, this solvent is the preferred solvent for many extraction methods, such as the decaffeination of coffee.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this solvent, a supercritical fluid that is also often used in its solid form.",
      "answer": "supercritical carbon dioxide (or sCO2 or supercritical CO2)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Supercritical carbon dioxide has applications in these processes for washing clothing without water, as a replacement for \"perc\" [\"perk\"], or tetrachloroethylene [TET-ruh-klor-oh-ETH-uh-leen].",
      "answer": "dry cleaning"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Other green solvents include this class of liquids which are molten salts that exist as a liquid at standard temperature and pressure.",
      "answer": "ionic liquids (accept liquid electrolytes; prompt on \"liquid salt(s)\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about statuses of near-citizenship:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Long-term immigrants and freed slaves in Athens could become metics [MET-iks] under the democratizing reforms introduced by this opponent of Hippias [HIP-ee-us] around 500 BC.",
      "answer": "Cleisthenes [KLYSE-thuh-neez]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Naturalization was impossible in this country until 1914; prior to that time, the status of \"denizen\" had to be granted by monarchs from the House of Hanover for foreigners to own land here.",
      "answer": "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland or U.K. (accept any underlined portion; accept England or Scotland or Wales or Ireland; do not accept or prompt on \"Northern Ireland\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In the U.S., \"lawful permanent residents\" are still issued a physical \"card\" of this color.",
      "answer": "green (card)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This author dedicated his story \"The Judgment\" to Felice Bauer [fay-LEET-zuh \"bower\"], who later became his fiancée.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this author whose literary executor, Max Brod [broht], did not carry out his instructions to burn his unfinished works.",
      "answer": "Franz Kafka"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Kafka died of tuberculosis [too-bur-\"cue\"-LOH-siss] in 1924, before completing this novel about K.'s struggles with a shadowy bureaucracy based in the title structure.",
      "answer": "The Castle (or Das Schloss)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Another of Kafka's posthumous [PAHSS-chuh-muss] works was this novel, which begins with the unexplained arrest of Josef K [YOH-sef KAH].",
      "answer": "The Trial (or Der Prozess)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Answer the following about the uncle and nephew Fromental [froh-men-tahl] and Ludovic Halévy [loo-doh-veek hah-lay-VEE].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Ludovic Halévy was the librettist for this French composer's operetta Orpheus in the Underworld, which popularized the can-can.",
      "answer": "Jacques Offenbach [zhahk AH-fin-bahk] (or Jacob Offenbach)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Ludovic Halévy also co-wrote the play Le Réveillon [luh ray-vay-awn] that became the basis for this Viennese composer's operetta Die Fledermaus [FLAY-dur-\"mouse\"].",
      "answer": "Johann Strauss II [YOH-hahn shtrowss \"the second\"] (or Johann Baptist Strauss or Johann Strauss the Younger or Johann Strauss Jr.; prompt on \"Strauss\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This tenor performer's final role was as Eléazar [el-ee-ah-sar] in Fromental Halévy's opera, La Juive [lah zhoo-eev].  His 1903 RCA Victor recording of the aria \"Vesti la giubba\" [VESS-tee lah JYOOB-bah] was the first-ever record to sell a million copies.",
      "answer": "Enrico Caruso"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the early years of the Associated Press Athlete of  the Year award:",
    "A": {
      "question": "The first male winner was Pepper Martin, one of the players Branch Rickey assembled to play for this National League franchise's 1930s \"Gashouse Gang\" teams.",
      "answer": "St. Louis Cardinals (accept either underlined portion; accept Cards)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Both the first male and female repeat winners, Don Budge and Alice Marble, were selected for their accomplishments in this sport, which was also played by later winners Chris Evert and Serena Williams.",
      "answer": "tennis (accept tennis players)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 1932 Gene Sarazen [SAIR-uh-zen] became the first male winner from this sport after winning both the U.S. Open and the British Open.",
      "answer": "golf(ing)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "One of this author's plays opens in an \"octagon room\" at Sir Robert Chiltern's house.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this Dublin-born author whose play An Ideal Husband opened in 1895, the same year he was arrested for \"gross indecency.\"",
      "answer": "Oscar Wilde [\"wild\"] (or Oscar Fingal O'Flahertie Wills Wilde)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This other Wilde play that opened in 1895 ended its London stage run soon after Wilde's arrest.  Jack and Algy [AL-jee] both pretend to have the title name in this farce.",
      "answer": "The Importance of Being Earnest(, A Trivial Comedy for Serious People)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "After being convicted, Wilde was incarcerated at this prison.  In a \"ballad\" named for this prison, Wilde claimed \"each man kills the thing he loves.\"",
      "answer": "Reading Gaol [\"redding jail\"] (accept The Ballad of Reading Gaol)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Before execution, computer code is \"tokenized\" or \"lexed\" into a stream of known strings with understood meaning.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Tokens are often recognized by matching against this kind of \"expression\" in which an asterisk signifies \"zero or more\" of the preceding pattern.",
      "answer": "regular expression(s) (or regexes or regexps)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The tokens are fed into this kind of \"top-down\" or \"bottom-up\" program that builds an abstract syntax tree.  The 'P' in \"grep\" abbreviates a form of this word.",
      "answer": "parser(s) (accept parsing program or parse program)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A compiler uses the abstract syntax tree to output machine code for later execution, unlike this kind of program that runs the code directly by examining the tree and implementing its operations.",
      "answer": "interpreter(s)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In June 1520 this English king met Francis I of France at a peace summit that devolved into an ostentatious display of wealth.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this king, who was accompanied to the Field of the Cloth of Gold by his wife Catherine of Aragon.",
      "answer": "Henry VIII [\"the eighth\"] of England (prompt on \"Henry\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Henry traveled to the meeting from this small English possession on the coast of France, which sits directly opposite Dover across the narrowest part of the English Channel.",
      "answer": "(Pale of) Calais [\"cal\"-ay]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The meeting at the Field of the Cloth of Gold was arranged by this Archbishop of York, whom Henry later charged with treason for failing to annul his marriage to Catherine.",
      "answer": "Thomas Wolsey (or Cardinal Wolsey or Thomas Woolsey)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Actor Steve Martin, who plays this instrument, created an annual prize for players of it; one winner of that prize was Victor Furtado.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this circular-bodied string instrument used in bluegrass music.",
      "answer": "banjo(s)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Furtado played on an album titled \"Masters of\" this technique, in which players place a hard cylinder, like a bottleneck, over one of their fingers and move it across the strings to produce g lissando [glih-SAHN-doh] or vibrato [vih-BRAH-toh].",
      "answer": "slide technique (accept slide banjo; accept slide guitar)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "When Furtado was twelve, he was invited to perform with Mike Snider on this country music show based in Nashville.",
      "answer": "Grand Ole Opry (prompt on \"Opry\") [Furtado was 19 when he won the prize.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The Fourier [foo-ree-ay] transform relates a function's representations in position space and the space named for this quantity.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this quantity, whose \"linear\" type equals mass times velocity.",
      "answer": "(linear) momentum (accept momentum space)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This quantum mechanics principle places a limit on simultaneous knowledge of both position and momentum.",
      "answer": "Heisenberg [\"HIGH\"-zin-bairg] uncertainty principle (accept either underlined portion)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The product of the standard deviations of momentum and position must be at least one -half this constant denoted by a modified letter.  The momentum operator equals minus i times this constant times the gradient operator.",
      "answer": "h-bar (or Dirac's constant; accept reduced Planck's constant; accept h over 2 pi or h divided by 2 pi; do not accept or prompt on \"Planck('s) (constant)\" or \"h\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 1918 Theodore Roosevelt called the persecution of these people \"the greatest crime\"  of World War I.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this ethnic group whose intellectual leaders in Constantinople were rounded up and deported on Red Sunday in 1915.",
      "answer": "Armenians (or hayer [hah-YEHR]; accept (but do not otherwise reveal) answers referencing the Armenian genocide)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In 1944 Raphael Lemkin coined this word to describe the Ottoman Empire's systematic killing of Armenians.  This word refers generally to the systematic destruction of a group of people.",
      "answer": "genocide"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In 1921 an Armenian assassin killed Mehmed Talaat, who had orchestrated Red Sunday; Talaat held this senior Ottoman title during the war, alongside Ahmed Djemal [JEH-mal] and Ismail Enver.",
      "answer": "pasha (or pasa; accept Talaat Pasha or Djemal Pasha or Enver Pasha; accept (the) Three Pashas or Üç Pasalar)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In this poem, Mary asks her husband to \"be kind,\" to which he replies \"When was I ever anything but kind to him?\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this poem in which a couple asks why the title character has not walked \"thirteen little miles\" to the house of his brother, rather than lying down in their barn.",
      "answer": "The Death of the Hired Man"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "\"The Death of the Hired Man\" is by this New England poet of \"Mending Wall.\"",
      "answer": "Robert (Lee) Frost"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "\"The Death of the Hired Man\" defines this location as \"a place where, when you have to go there / They have to take you in.\"  Another Frost poem describes a \"Burial\" at this place.",
      "answer": "home (accept Home Burial)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Spearman's rho is a \"coefficient\" measuring this relationship.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this relationship which, according to an adage, does not imply causation.",
      "answer": "correlation (accept linear correlation or rank correlation; accept correlation does not imply causation; accept answers indicating two variables are correlated)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Correlation coefficients range between these two numbers.",
      "answer": "-1 and +1 (accept answers in either order; do not accept or prompt on partial answers)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Spearman's rho measures correlation by assessing if two ordinal variables are related by a function with this property.  Functions with this property are always either nonincreasing or nondecreasing.",
      "answer": "monotonic [MAH-nuh-TAH-nik] (or monotonicity)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This man is called the \"can-do man\" in the \"can-do era\" in David Halberstam's book The Best and the Brightest.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this secretary of defense, whose young \"Whiz Kids\" helped him craft his Vietnam War policies.",
      "answer": "Robert (Strange) McNamara [MAK-nuh-mair-uh]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Many of the \"Whiz Kids\" mentioned in Halberstam's book once worked at this nonprofit think tank, a corporation founded by the Douglas Aircraft Company in 1948.",
      "answer": "RAND Corporation (prompt on \"Research and Development\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This deceased Arizona senator and Vietnam War hero wrote the preface to the most recent edition of The Best and the Brightest.",
      "answer": "John McCain (or John Sidney McCain III)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about video games in which players must take unusual physical actions to progress:",
    "A": {
      "question": "In a Sega Genesis game starring this superhero team, characters like Wolverine, Cyclops, a nd Nightcrawler must \"reset\" a computer by pressing the console's actual reset button.",
      "answer": "X-Men"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Phantom Hourglass, a 2007 handheld entry in this series, required players to physically close and open the console to copy a map.",
      "answer": "The Legend of Zelda (accept The Legend of Zelda: Phantom Hourglass)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "StarTropics, a game on this 8-bit console, requires players to reveal a code by physically dipping a paper letter included with the game in water.",
      "answer": "Nintendo Entertainment System or NES (or Famicom or Family Computer or FC; prompt on \"Nintendo\"; do not accept or prompt on \"Super NES\" or \"Super Nintendo\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Mr. White uses this story's title object to wish for 200 pounds, which he receives as compen sation after his son is killed in a workplace accident.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this horror story about a cursed item that Sergeant Major Morris brings to England.",
      "answer": "The Monkey's Paw"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This author of supernatural fiction wrote \"The Monkey's Paw.\"",
      "answer": "W. W. Jacobs (or William Wymark Jacobs)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The monkey's paw was cursed by a fakir [fuh-KEER] in what is now this country.  The backstory to Arthur Conan Doyle's novel The Sign of the Four includes a robbery near the Agra [AH-gruh] Fort in what is now this country.",
      "answer": "India (or Republic of India or Bharat(iya) Ganarajya)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A series presented by this man illustrates the emergence of modern multinationals using the examples of the Dutch conglomerate Philips and the fictional \"UGE\" [\"U-G-E\"].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "The BBC series The Age of Uncertainty was presented by what liberal economist who wrote The Affluent Society?",
      "answer": "John Kenneth Galbraith [gahl-BRAYTH] (or Ken Galbraith)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In 1980 PBS aired the series Free to Choose, this economist's pro-market rebuttal to The Age of Uncertainty.",
      "answer": "Milton Friedman"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Age of Uncertainty inspired a debate between Friedman and this Hungarian-born economist who is the first namesake of a type of \"efficiency\" that is less strict than Pareto [pah-RAY-toh] efficiency.",
      "answer": "Nicholas Kaldor, Baron Kaldor (or Káldor Miklós; accept Kaldor-hicks efficiency)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "The Tuva Republic lies at the border between these two countries.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name these two countries.  The Selenga River starts in one of them before flowing north  into Lake Baikal in the other.",
      "answer": "Russia (or Russian Federation or Rossiya or Rossiyskaya Federatsiya)   Mongolia (or Mongol Uls)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Tuvan people traditionally resided in these portable round tents, known as ger in neighboring Mongolia.",
      "answer": "yurts"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Tuva's cultural touchstones include khöömei [koo-may], a technique of this type of singing.  Its varieties include the whistle-like sygyt [suh-gut] and the ultra-deep kargyraa [kar-guh-rah].",
      "answer": "throat singing (accept overtone singing or chanting or harmonic singing)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "A 20th-century thinker from this country wrote the book The Revolt of the Masses.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this European country that was home to José Ortega y Gasset.  A friar from here, Bartolomé de las Casas, critiqued its \"destruction of the Indies.\"",
      "answer": "Spain (or Kingdom of Spain or Reino de España)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This Spanish-born philosopher wrote that \"those who cannot remember the past are condemned to repeat it\" in The Life of Reason.",
      "answer": "George Santayana (or Jorge Agustín Nicolás Ruiz de Santayana y Borrás)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Another Santayana book contrasts this attitude with \"animal faith.\"  Sextus Empiricus outlined the Pyrrhonian type of this outlook.",
      "answer": "skepticism (accept Skepticism and Animal Faith or Pyrrhonian skepticism)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the process known as \"Megxit\":",
    "A": {
      "question": "Megxit refers to the decision of this man and his wife, Meghan Markle, to withdraw from the British royal family in 2020.",
      "answer": "Prince Harry (or Harry, Duke of Sussex)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The term \"Megxit,\" a reference to \"Brexit,\" was coined by this conservative tabloid newspaper, which is the second-highest circulated paper in the U.K.",
      "answer": "The Sun"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Despite their withdrawal, Harry and Meghan are still formally known as the Duke and Duchess of this historic county.",
      "answer": "Sussex (accept Duke of Sussex or Duchess of Sussex)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about the career of Illinois senator Paul Douglas:",
    "A": {
      "question": "In the 1930s Douglas lobbied for the \"Chicago plan\" to severely restrict the multiplying activities of these institutions, including banning their \"fractional reserve\" structure.",
      "answer": "(lending) banks (accept savings and loans or savings banks)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Interpretations differ on why Douglas presented a pitcher of orange juice during this racist South Carolina senator's 1957 filibuster of the Civil Rights Act.",
      "answer": "Strom Thurmond (or James Strom Thurmond Sr.)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "During World War II, at the age of 50, Douglas completed training at this South Carolina \"isla nd\" that is a major site for new recruits in the U.S. Marine Corps.",
      "answer": "Parris Island (accept Marine Corps Recruit Depot Parris Island)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This adjective precedes \"England\" in the name of an upper-class Tory group led by Benjamin Disraeli [diz-\"RAIL\"-ee].  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "When applied to the word \"Turks,\" what adjective identifies an early 20th-century reform movement in the Ottoman Empire?",
      "answer": "young (or jön; accept Young England or Young Turks or Jön Turkler)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This man founded the Young Italy movement in 1831, and fomented many democratic revolts intended to promote Italian unification.",
      "answer": "Giuseppe Mazzini [joo-SEP-ee mat-ZEE-nee]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Young Bosnia [BAHZ-nee-uh] movement included Gavrilo Princip [GAHV-rih-loh \"PRINT-sip\"], who assassinated this Austrian archduke to ignite World War I.",
      "answer": "Archduke Franz Ferdinand (or Francis Ferdinand; prompt on partial answers)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Pencil and paper ready.  Consider a game in which players have a one -third chance of winning 10 dollars [pause] and a two-thirds chance of losing 4 dollars.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "If the game is played once, what is the expected value, in dollars, of the winnings?  You have 10 seconds.",
      "answer": "2/3 dollar(s) [((1/3) * 10) - ((2/3) * 4) = (10/3) - (8/3) = 2/3]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Given each turn has an expected profit of 2/3 of a dollar, what is the total expected profit after 15 games?",
      "answer": "10 dollars [15 * (2/3) = 30/3 = 10]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "As the total amount of money depends only on the state after the previous game, the game can be described by models named for what Russian mathematician?",
      "answer": "Andrey (Andreyevich) Markov [\"MARK-off\"] (accept discrete-time Markov process(es) or Markov chains or Markov models; prompt on \"Markovian (processes or chains or models)\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2018 accountant Scott Foster briefly became a celebrity for playing this position in a game.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this sports position played by emergency fill-in David Ayres in a February 2020 game after two players for the Carolina Hurricanes were injured.",
      "answer": "goalie(s) (or hockey goalies or hockey goaltenders)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "The Hurricanes were playing on the road in this team's Scotiabank [SKOH-shuh-bank] Arena.  This hockey team's rivalry with the Canadiens [kuh-nay-dee-ENZ] is the oldest in NHL history.",
      "answer": "Toronto Maple Leafs (accept either underlined portion)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The Maple Leafs have won this NHL championship trophy 13 times, second only to the Canadiens.",
      "answer": "Stanley Cup (or La Coupe Stanley; accept Lord Stanley's Cup)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2014 this state elected its first female senator, the Republican Shelley Moore Capito [\"CAP\"-ih-\"toe\"].  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this mountainous state with a politically influential coal industry.",
      "answer": "West Virginia (accept WV [\"W-V\"])"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In his 2022 State of the State address, this West Virginia governor lifted up his pet bulldog, and told actress Bette [bet] Midler to \"kiss\" the dog's \"hiney\" [\"HI\"-nee].",
      "answer": "Jim Justice (or James Conley Justice II)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Midler had insulted West Virginia in a tweet criticizing this Democratic senator.  Protesters have paddled kayaks [KYE-yaks] to the houseboat of this man, who opposes most of the Build Back Better legislation.",
      "answer": "Joe Manchin (or Joseph Manchin III)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This codeword indicated a successful ambush, but is frequently mistranslated as \"tiger.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Give this Japanese word repeated three times in the title of a 1970 film about the attack on Pearl Harbor.",
      "answer": "tora [toh-rah] (accept Tora! Tora! Tora!) [\"Tora\" is a homophone for the Japanese word for tiger.]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In the film Tora! Tora! Tora!, this leader of the Japanese Imperial Navy says that Japan has \"awakened a sleeping giant,\" a quote invented for the film.",
      "answer": "Isoroku Yamamoto [ee-soh-roh-koo yah-mah-moh-toh] (or Isoroku Takano; accept names in either order; accept Admiral Yamamoto or Admiral Takano)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Tora! Tora! Tora! includes anachronistic [uh-nak-ruh-NISS-tik] shots of a Pearl Harbor memorial on this Hawaiian island, where the attack took place.",
      "answer": "Oahu [oh-AH-hoo]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Characters in this \"Super Soul Musical\" sing \"Ease On Down the Road\" while traveling to the Emerald City.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Wicked witches are given the names \"Evamean\" [EH-vuh-\"mean\"] and \"Evillene\" [\"EVIL\"-leen] in what 1974 musical based on a novel by L. Frank Baum?",
      "answer": "The Wiz(: The Super Soul Musical \"Wonderful Wizard of Oz\") (do not accept or prompt on \"The (Wonderful) Wizard of Oz\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In a 1978 film version of The Wiz, the Scarecrow was played by this singer, who would later release the album Thriller.",
      "answer": "Michael (Joseph) Jackson"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A 2015 live TV adaptation of The Wiz featured this rapper and actress as the title character.  This co -star of Girls Trip received an Oscar nomination for playing Mama Morton in Chicago.",
      "answer": "Queen Latifah [lah-TEE-fuh] (or Dana Elaine Owens)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Miguel Alcubierre [mee-GHEL ahl-koo-bee-\"AIR-ray\"] proposed a device that would achieve this kind of motion.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Some relativistic [\"relative\"-ISS-tik] jets appear to move in what manner that exceeds a \"universal limit\"?",
      "answer": "faster-than-light or superluminal motion (accept FTL [\"F-T-L\"] motion or answers indicating above the speed of light; prompt on \"warp (speed or motion)\" or \"(Alcubierre) warp (drive)\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A superluminal [\"super\"-loo-muh-nul] jet is produced by M87 [\"M-eighty-seven\"], one of these galaxies found on the left side of Hubble's tuning fork diagram.",
      "answer": "elliptical [uh-LIP-tih-kul] galaxies (or ellipticals; accept supergiant elliptical galaxies or ellipticals; prompt on \"radio (galaxies)\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Apparent superluminal motion can also occur with this phenomenon, in which a delayed light signal arrives after being reflected.  A similar phenomenon occurs when sound reflects off a wall or distant mountain.",
      "answer": "light echo(s)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about detention of prisoners during the U.S. War on Terror:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Many detainees were held at a camp on this naval base in Cuba, which the U.S. has leased since 1903.",
      "answer": "Guantánamo [gwahn-TAH-nah-moh] Bay (accept GTMO or Gitmo; accept Guantanamo Bay Naval Base or Naval Station Guantanamo Bay)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This British international spy agency aided the CIA in performing \"extraordinary renditions\" of detainees to \"black sites,\" where the detainees were interrogated and tortured.",
      "answer": "MI6 [\"M-I-six\"] (accept Secret Intelligence Service or SIS)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "One suspected CIA black site was on Diego Garcia [dee-AY-goh gar-SEE-uh], an isolated atoll [AT-tohl] in the middle of this ocean.  U.S. forces buried Osama bin Laden [oh-SAH-muh bin LAH-den] at sea in this ocean.",
      "answer": "Indian Ocean"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about Johann Wolfgang von Goethe [GUR-tuh]:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Goethe's magnum opus [OH-puss] is a tragedy about this scholar, who wagers his soul with the demon Mephistopheles [MEH-fih-STAH-fuh-leez].",
      "answer": "Heinrich Faust [fowst] (accept either underlined portion; accept Doctor Faust or Faustus; accept Henry Faust; accept Faust: The First Part of the Tragedy or Faust. Der Tragödie erster Teil or Faust: The Second Part of the Tragedy or Faust. Der Tragödie zweiter Teil in fünf Akten)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Goethe rose to fame with a 1774 novel about the \"sorrows\" of this young man, which are caused by his unrequited love for his friend Charlotte [shar-LOH-teh].",
      "answer": "(Young) Werther [VAIR-tair] (accept The Sorrows of Young Werther or Die Leiden des jungen Werthers)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Goethe's poetry collection West-Eastern Divan [dih-VAN] was inspired by the works of Hafez [HAH-fiz], who wrote many poems called ghazals [GAH-zahlz] in this language also used by the poet Rumi [ROO-mee].",
      "answer": "Persian language (or Farsi)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In circuit diagrams, this point is represented by three parallel lines of decreasing length.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this point in a circuit that serves as an infinite charge sink.",
      "answer": "ground (accept answers indicating where the circuit is grounded)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Some antennae [an-TEN-ee] that transmit these waves need to be grounded to prevent a buildup of charge.  These waves are often AM [\"A-M\"] or FM [\"F-M\"].",
      "answer": "radio waves (prompt on \"electromagnetic (waves)\" or \"EM (waves)\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The ground node is typically defined to have a value of zero for this quantity.  The sum  of this quantity across all circuit elements in a loop equals zero by Kirchhoff's [KEER-kawf's] loop law.",
      "answer": "voltage (or electric potential; accept volts; do not accept or prompt on \"(electric) potential energy\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer these questions about intervals:",
    "A": {
      "question": "What interval exists between a given note and the next higher note with the same letter name, such as C to C?",
      "answer": "octave(s) [AHK-tiv]"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "What term describes intervals such as octaves, fourths, and fifths, whose pitches have small whole -number frequency ratios?",
      "answer": "perfect intervals (accept consonant [\"CON\"-suh-nunt] intervals or consonance)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This adjective describes intervals such as C to F-sharp, or D to G-sharp, that are one half-step larger than a perfect interval.",
      "answer": "augmented intervals (accept augmented fourths)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-name these people who contracted polio [POH-lee-oh]:",
    "A": {
      "question": "This future president was paralyzed from the waist down in 1921 from what doctors believed to be polio.",
      "answer": "Franklin D(elano) Roosevelt (or FDR; prompt on \"Roosevelt\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Because of polio, this artist's right leg was shorter than her left.  Her works include a Self-portrait on the Borderline Between Mexico and the United States.",
      "answer": "Frida Kahlo [FREE-dah KAH-loh] de Rivera (or Magdalena Carmen Frieda Kahlo y Calderón)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Israeli-American violinist plays sitting down because he contracted polio at age four.  He recorded the theme for the film Schindler's List.",
      "answer": "Itzhak Perlman [EET-zahk \"PEARL-man\"]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about Solway [SUL-way] Firth:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Like the Dee and the Ribble estuaries [ESS-choo-air-eez], Solway Firth is an inlet of this sea.",
      "answer": "Irish Sea"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "To the north of Solway Firth is Dumfries [dum-\"freeze\"] and Galloway, a region of this constituent [kun-\"STITCH\"-oo-ent] country of the U.K.",
      "answer": "Scotland (or Kingdom of Scotland or Rioghachd na h-Alba)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Solway Firth is near this self-governing island.  A breed of cat named after this island's residents has an unusually short tail.",
      "answer": "Isle of Man (or Mann or Mannin or Ellan Vannin; prompt on \"Manx (cat)\")"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This story is set during a period when an \"elf-queen\" danced \"in many a green meadow.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this story about a man who avoids execution by discovering what women most desire.",
      "answer": "The Wife of Bath's Tale (or The Tale of the Wyf of Bathe; prompt on \"(The) Canterbury Tales\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "\"The Wife of Bath's Tale\" is one of the Canterbury Tales written in Middle English by this author.",
      "answer": "Geoffrey Chaucer [CHAW-sur]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "A digression in \"The Wife of Bath's Tale\" recounts a story about a tattletale wife from this Roman author's Metamorphoses [met-uh-MOR-fuh-seez].",
      "answer": "Ovid [AH-vid] (or Publius Ovidius Naso)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "In 2020 protesters in the U.K. city of Bristol [BRISS-tul] tore down a statue of Edward Colston [\"COAL-stun\"] because of Colston's connection to this practice.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this practice, which often involved taking Africans across the Mid dle Passage.",
      "answer": "slavery (accept any answer indicating the holding of slaves or enslavement or human chattel or treating humans as property; accept the slave trade)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "After the statue was toppled, white supremacists in Bristol vandalized the grave of an enslaved man with this name, which was shared by the Roman general who defeated Hannibal [HAN-uh-bul] at Zama [ZAH-muh].",
      "answer": "Scipio Africanus [SKIH-pee-oh af-rih-KAHN-uss]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This Whig who represented Bristol in Parliament introduced a bill to ban slaveowners from sitting in the House of Commons.  He criticized revolutionaries in Reflections on the Revolution in France.",
      "answer": "Edmund Burke"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about brown algae [AL-jee]:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Brown algae get their color from fucoxanthin [\"FEW\"-koh-ZAN-thin], a pigment also found in these tiny algae whose cell walls are made of silica [SIL-ih-kuh].",
      "answer": "diatoms [DYE-uh-tahm] (or Bacillariophyceae or Diatomea or Diatomophyceae or Bacillariae or Bacillariophyta)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In brown algae, this organelle [\"organ\"-EL] has four membranes instead of two.  The Calvin Cycle occurs in the fluid-filled stroma [STROH-muh] of this organelle.",
      "answer": "chloroplast(s) [KLOR-oh-plast] (prompt on \"plastid(s)\")"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "This group of brown algae seaweeds are densely concentrated in underwater \"forests.\"",
      "answer": "kelp(s) (or Laminariales; accept giant kelps or kelp forests)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "Floods in this country's KwaZulu-Natal [kwah-ZOO-loo nuh-TAHL] province killed over 400 people in 2022.  For 10 points each-",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this country that has been governed by the African National Congress since 1994.",
      "answer": "South Africa (or Republic of South Africa; prompt on \"RSA\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "KwaZulu-Natal is the birthplace of this former South African president, who left office in 2018 and is facing an upcoming corruption trial.",
      "answer": "Jacob (Gedleyihlekisa) Zuma [ZOO-mah]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Zuma's trial is connected to a 1990s contract that supplied South Africa with these weapons.  The Saab JAS 39 Gripen [sahb \"J-A-S thirty-nine\" GRIP-en] and the BAE [\"B-A-E\"] Hawk are examples of these weapons.",
      "answer": "fighter jets (or fighters or military aircraft or airplanes; accept any underlined portion)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "During the 1950s this man worked as a motivational speaker for General Electric.  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this man who first made a political impression by giving the 1964 speech \"A Time for Choosi ng\" in support of Barry Goldwater.",
      "answer": "Ronald (Wilson) Reagan"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "In 1966 Reagan was elected governor of this West Coast state.",
      "answer": "California (or CA [\"C-A\"])"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "In the California governor's race, Reagan defeated Pat, a man with this surname.  Pat's son, who also had this surname, was governor of California in both the 1970s and 2010s.",
      "answer": "Brown (accept Browns; accept Pat Brown or Edmund Gerald Brown Sr. or Jerry Brown or Edmund Gerald Brown Jr.)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This island contains the city of Hagåtña [huh-GAHT-n'yuh], whose name derives from a Chamorro [chuh-MOR-oh] word for \"blood.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Andersen Air Force Base is on what Micronesian [\"micro\"-NEE-zhun] island controlled by the U.S.?",
      "answer": "Guam [gwahm] (or Guåhan)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "Guam is part of these islands, which form the Philippine [FIL-uh-peen] Sea's eastern border with the greater Pacific Ocean.",
      "answer": "Mariana [\"marry\"-AH-nuh] Islands (or Marianas)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "The \"brown tree\" variety of these reptiles is an invasive species that has devastated Guam's birdli fe.  The \"sea\" types of these animals are sometimes mistaken for eels.",
      "answer": "snakes (or Serpentes; accept serpents; accept brown tree snakes or sea snakes or sea serpents)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This title character feels \"elephantishly [\"elephant\"-ish-lee] uneasy\" while listening to the marital woes of Paul Riesling [REESS-ling].  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "What realtor from the city of Zenith [ZEE-nith] briefly becomes a rebel, and supports the socialist Seneca Doane [SEN-uh-kuh DOHN]?",
      "answer": "George F(ollansbee) Babbitt (accept either underlined portion)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "This American author of Main Street parodied mindless \"boosterism\" [\"BOOSTER\"-ih-zum] in his 1922 novel Babbitt.",
      "answer": "(Harry) Sinclair Lewis"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Lewis also wrote this novel about the fascist Buzz Windrip, who is elected president of the U.S.  Sales of this novel surged after the election of Donald Trump.",
      "answer": "It Can't Happen Here"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer these questions about theoretical \"shells\":",
    "A": {
      "question": "What structures have a \"shell model\" that predicts \"magic numbers\" of component particles -such as 2 and 82-that make these structures especially stable?",
      "answer": "atomic nuclei [NOO-klee-\"eye\"] (or atomic nucleus; accept nuclear shell model; do not accept or prompt on \"atom(s)\")"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "For volumes of revolution, the shell method and disk method are two ways of setting up what operation to calculate those volumes?",
      "answer": "volume integration (or volume integrals [IN-tug-rulz]; accept definite integrals or definite integration; accept answers indicating a function is integrated)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Isaac Newton proved that a spherically symmetric [sim-\"metric\"] shell exerts zero of what force on objects inside of it?  Newton derived this force's inverse -square law.",
      "answer": "gravity or gravitational force (accept (Newton's) law of universal gravitation)"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "For 10 points each-answer the following about Mexico in World War II:",
    "A": {
      "question": "Mexico entered the war in 1942, after two Mexican tankers were sunk by this type of German ship.",
      "answer": "U-boats (accept submarines or Unterseeboote)"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "A Mexican flying squadron that saw action in the Philippines [FIL-uh-peenz] was named after the Eagle warriors of this empire, which fought Hernán Cortés [\"air\"-NAHN kor-TEZ] in the early 16th century.",
      "answer": "Aztec Empire or Aztecs (or aztecas or Aztec Triple Alliance; accept Aztec Eagles or Águilas Aztecas; accept Tenochcas [teh-NOHCH-kuz] or Excan Tlahtoloyan)"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "During World War II Mexico was governed by a predecessor to this political party.  This party and its predecessors held national power between 1929 and 2000.",
      "answer": "PRI [pree or \"P-R-I\"] (or Institutional Revolutionary Party or Partido Revolucionario Institucional) [The PRI's predecessors were the National Revolutionary Party, which existed from 1929 to 1938, and the Party of the Mexican Revolution, which was replaced by the PRI in 1946.]"
    }
  },
  {
    "prompt": "This author wrote \"old time is still a-flying\" in a poem that warns \"having lost but once your prime / you may forever tarry.\"  For 10 points each -",
    "A": {
      "question": "Name this 17th-century British poet who advised \"gather ye rosebuds while ye may\" in \"To the Virgins, to Make Much of Time.\"",
      "answer": "Robert Herrick"
    },
    "B": {
      "question": "\"To the Virgins, to Make Much of Time\" is a poem in this genre [ZHAHN-ruh], whose two-word Latin name means \"seize the day.\"",
      "answer": "carpe diem [\"CAR-pay\" DEE-um]"
    },
    "C": {
      "question": "Herrick's contemporary Andrew Marvell [\"mar\"-VEL] wrote this carpe diem poem that describes \"Time's wingèd chariot hurrying near.\"",
      "answer": "To His Coy Mistress"
    }
  }
]